<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The fall of Babylon in vsurping ecclesiastical power and offices And the miserable estate of them that pertake of her fornications.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1634</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 247 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 50 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00901</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1101</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101521</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837332</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837332</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1648</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00901)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1648)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 822:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The fall of Babylon in vsurping ecclesiastical power and offices And the miserable estate of them that pertake of her fornications.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 72 [i.e. 92], 4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted in the yeare of our Lord,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Amsterdam] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1634.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from STC.</note>
                  <note>P. 92 misnumbered 72.</note>
                  <note>The last two leaves are blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1648:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1648:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE FALL OF BABYLON IN VSVRPING ECCLE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SIASTICALL POWER AND OFFICES. AND THE MISERABLE ESTATE of them that pertake of her fornications.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Revelation 18.4.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Come out of her my People, that ye be not pertarkers of her ſinnes, and that ye receyve not of her plagues.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprinted in the yeare of our Lord.</hi> 1634.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:1648:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1648:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was a question prophetically aſked of thoſe times, wherein the Church and truth of God ſhould ſuffer greatest perſecution and oppoſition, <hi>why doe the Heathen rage,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 2.</note> 
               <hi>and the People imagine a vaine thing? The Kings of the Earth ſet themſelves, &amp; the Rulers take counſell together againſt the Lord, and againſt his Chriſt, ſaying: Let us breake theire bands aſunder, and caſt theire cords from us.</hi> But for all theſe forces and deviſes of men, who are not Iewes indeed, Chriſtians indeede, but Gentiles and Heathen. Yet, ſaith God, <hi>have I ſet my King upon my holy hill of Syon;</hi> and that as he ſaith, to have <hi>the Heathen for his inheritance,</hi> and <hi>the ends of the Earth for his poſſeſſion:</hi> eyther to rule them by <hi>the rod of his power,</hi> by the revealed word, or to <hi>break them in pieces like a Potters veſſel:</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or it had beene ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yde, <hi>He ſhall judge among the Nations.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 2.</note> Well therefore is it added, <hi>Be wiſe now therefore o ye Kings, be inſtructed ye Iudges of the earth: Serve the Lord with feare,</hi> &amp;c. For as the Church of God in generall, ſo every true member of it, will be ready to ſay,<note place="margin">Chap. 33.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord is our Iudge, the Lord is our Lawgiver, the Lord is our King;</hi> and that therefore it were a happy thing, if Princes and States would be pleaſed to conſider, that they are onely Lords over men properly and directly, as they are theire ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and not as they are Christs Diſciples, Chriſtians, and ſpiritually his ſubjects; withall, that God is not pleaſed with
<pb facs="tcp:1648:3"/> unwilling worſhippers, whereby neyther Chriſtian ſocieties are bettered, nor the perſons themſelves: For while all are compelled to a conformitie, eſpecially if it be in things not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the word of God, many haveing preſently theire Religion in reſpect of mans authority, &amp; not of Gods, become Hypocrites, Timeſervers, and a kinde of Atheists: &amp; which is worſe, ſuch men, by theire formalitie, though they have litle elſe in them, doe oft attaine authority in ſuch Churches, and thereby get dominion over mens faith in other things. For though in the primitive times, the Biſhops of Rome had no ſuch ample power, yet the fi st ſtep to it was that of impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing conformitie in things deviſed by men, &amp; by them coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted indifferent and innocent, if not proffitable and neceſſary; which power beeing graunted them, they ſoone got authority over all Miniſters and People; and then ſo much over Kings, that in verie pollicie, they thought it theire beſt courſe to hold all theire ſubjects, in matters of Religion, to the obedience of the Church of Rome, rather then to adventure the danger of her diſpleaſure; whereby they brought both themſelves, and theire ſubjects into a far worfe thraldom, then that of the Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian bondage.</p>
            <p>What reaſon then is there, that this power, thus Popiſhly taken up, ſhould ſtill be maintayned againſt the poore ſubjects? From the beginning it was not ſo. For the Ancients finding the burden impoſed by Heathen Tyrants to be intollerable, ſayde,<note place="margin">Tertull.</note> 
               <hi>that it is no propertie of Religion, to compell to Religion: which ought to be taken up freely; that no man is forced by the chriſtians againſt his will,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lactanc.</note> 
               <hi>ſeeing he that wants faith and devotion is vnſerviceable to God:</hi> and that <hi>God, not beeing contentious, would not be worſhipped of the vnwilling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in deede after he had manifeſted his whole truth, &amp; the new Ieruſalem, his true church, if theſe things would
<pb facs="tcp:1648:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> not ſerve to convince men, he ſaith. <hi>He that is vniuſt, let him be vniuſt ſtill, and he that is filthie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev, 22.</note> 
               <hi>let him be fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie ſtill: and he that is righteous, let him be righteous ſtill.</hi> Yet doe I not denie all compulſion to the hearing of Gods word, as the meanes to worke religion, &amp; common to all ſorts good and bad; much leſſe excuſe civill diſobedience, palliated with religious shewes and pretences, vſed by Annabaptiſts &amp; others, or condemne neceſſarie reſtraint of publik idolatrie, &amp; the excerciſe of all erronious religions: So as theſe rules of reaſon be held inviol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ble: That the bond betweene Magiſtrate and ſubject is eſsentially civill; but religious accidentally only, th ugh eminent: So that he is only to hinder and puniſh that which God would have hindred and puniſhed; and to cheriſh that only which God would have cheriſhed; and not by the cunning of prevaricators, who ſerve not the Lord Ieſus, but theire owne bellies, to be drawne either to hold them guiltie that follow Gods Teſtament, or thoſe guiltleſſe, <hi>who erre in theire hearts</hi> &amp; practiſes, <hi>becauſe they have not known his waies;</hi> nor indeede will know them; whence it may come to paſſe, that he that perſecutes the chu ch of Chriſt, &amp; defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth the Synagogne of Satan may thinke he doth God ſervice; when he hath rather cauſe to feare that he helpeth his grand ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie the devill. I have therefore endeavoured to ſhew theſe things in the fall of Babylon; and withall, that as the chriſtian Magiſtrate hath his power of Magiſtracie from God, which his Chriſtianitie ſerves to ſanctifie and direct; ſo vndoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he is to vſe it for God and his honour, and that in his true worſhip in which he is eſpetially honoured, and only againſt the contrarie. The world doth ring of three complaints.</p>
            <p n="1">1. When a State profeſſeth the reformed Religion, &amp; hath Churches governed by Elders, as neere as it can to the practiſe of the primitive Churches; yet by a tolleration, or connivance gives leave to Annabaptists, Arminians, Lutherans, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists,
<pb facs="tcp:1648:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> and others, to have Churches in the ſame Cities.</p>
            <p n="2">2. When a State is of the Popiſh Religion, and maintaynes it, yet both gives abſolute tolleration to the reformed Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and contemnes it, as in France.</p>
            <p n="3">3. When a State profeſſeth the Proteſtant Religion, and withall a hierarchie, traditions and Ceremonies, which are Romiſhe, commanding all to a conformitie in them, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding all confutation of them, and of ſome other Popiſh &amp; Arminian tenets and practiſes, much connived at.</p>
            <p>In the two first, men ſay, if Sathan have a Synagogue or Throne in the one ende of a Citie, yet Christ hath a Throne in the other; his Temple is open, and his Servants have liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to ſerve him, as the primitive Churches did; neyther is any man compelled to other; they may freely preach &amp; write against all errours; This cannot be ſayde of the third; and therefore, if a poore Chriſtian, that would flie out of Babylon, be forced to dwell in one of them, let him learne by Christs word, in which he ought to take up his habitation.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:1648:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE FALL OF BABYLON IN VSVRPING ECCLESIA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STICALL POWER AND OFFICES.</hi> And the miſerable eſtate of them that pertake of her Fornication.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE church of Epheſus, who had only left her firſt love in ſom few things,<note place="margin">Rev. 2.3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> in zeale againſt them that were evill, in trying the Spirts, in la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and patience, which may ſeme to be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſmale faults, in reſpect of thoſe which may be found in the churches of theſe times, was yet told by Chriſt that ſhe was <hi>fallen.</hi> The church of Thiatira did but ſuffer the woman Iezabel to teach people, that they might eate things ſacrificed vnto idols,<note place="margin">Verſ. 20, 21.22.</note> and yet Chriſt ſaith this was to <hi>ſeduce them to commit fornication. And I gave <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er ſpace to repent of her fornication, and ſhe repented not. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ll caſt her into a bedde, and them that commit fornication with her into greate tribulation, except they repent of theire deedes. And J will kill her children with death, and all the churches ſhall know that I am he that ſearcheth the reines and the hearts.</hi> He ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth her <hi>charitie, and ſervice, and faith, and patience,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 19.</note> 
               <hi>and ber works, and the last to be more then the firſt;</hi> And yet all this will not ſerve, if ſhe preſume to teach any thing that he hath not taught, if ſhe doo not <hi>keepe his wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to the end,</hi> but give a libertie where he gives none; If this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> fault be not repented of,<note place="margin">Verſ. 26.18</note> he who is the Sonne of God, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> whoſe eies are as a flame of fire, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es it might not be win<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>d at, that it ſhould be ſeverely pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, and much more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen a church tranſgreſſeth in many
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:1648:5"/> things, for therefore he addeth <hi>And I will give vnto every one of you according to your works.</hi> But this our gracious Lord hath not only warned churches of the myſterie of iniquitie, the generall Apoſtacie after Antichriſt, the fall of Babylon, and the cup full of abominations and filthines of her fornications, whereof ſhe would make the nations to drinke; but hath alſo by his Servants convinced her, and all that commit fornication with her of all thoſe abhominations. Pleſſes ſheweth how the myſterie of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie was oppoſed in all ages. And when theſe could not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile with them, to make them leave theire wicked works; but the laſt were ſtill more, and worſe then the firſt, Chriſt-ſuffered heavie judgments to fall on them, declared in the viſion of the trumpets: where among, the reſt, that of the ſixt is remarkable; whereby is ſignified the comming in of the Turkes with fire and ſword,<note place="margin">Rev. 9.16.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8.</note> &amp; the greate ſlaughters they ſhould make amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g chriſtians. And yet it is ſaide, <hi>The reſt of the men which were not killed by theſe plagues, repented not of the works of theire hands, that they should not worship devils, &amp; idols of gold &amp; ſilver, &amp; braſſe &amp; ſtone &amp; of wood, which neither can ſee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Premoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to all Chriſtian Monarchs pag. 87. De cultu Adorat. lib. 3. diſp. 1. cap. 5.</note> 
               <hi>not heare nor walke.</hi> That they worſhip de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils while they receyve doctrines of devils, is a thing true enough: And howſoever, King Iames hath ſhewed it to be fulfilled in them, ſaying. <hi>As for worſhipping of devils; looke youre greate Ieſuited Doctor,</hi> Vaſques: <hi>and as for all the rest, it is the maine doctrine of the Roman church. And then it is ſubjoined in this text.</hi> Neither repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted they of theire murders, nor of theire ſorceries, nor of theire fornication nor of theire thefts. By <hi>theire murders, theire perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are meant, and bloodie maſſacres. For theire ſorceries, conſider of theire</hi> Agnus Dei, <hi>that will ſlaken fire, of the hallowed ſhirts, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ſorts of Reliques; and alſo of prayers that will preſerve men from the violence of ſhot, of fire, of ſword, of thunder, and ſuch like dangers; And judge if this be not verie like to ſorcerie and incantation of char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes. By theire fornication is meant, both theire ſpirituall fornication, and corporall, by reaſon of the reſtraint cf theire churchmen from mariage: They are guiltie of theft, in ſtealing from God the titles and greatnes of power due to him, and beſtowing it upon theire head <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Antichriſt</hi> (I will adde one thing, by vſurping other Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:1648:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> offices, and depriveing them of theire places, who were ſet aboute his throne.) <hi>As alſo by heaping up treaſure with theire ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gling wares, and marchandiſe of the Soules of men, by Iubiles, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons, Reliques, and ſuch like ſtrong deluſious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When theſe Iudgments would not reclaime them, Chriſt ſent forth Meſſengers, One Angel,<note place="margin">Rev. 14.6.</note> haveing an everlaſting Goſpel <hi>to preach vnto them that dwell on the earth:</hi> which the beſt expoſitors take to be meant of <hi>Wickliſe,</hi> or of him with Iohn Huſſe and others: And there followed another Angel, ſaying,<note place="margin">Verſ. 8.9.</note> 
               <hi>Babylon is fallen, is fallen which, many</hi> take to be meant of <hi>Luther</hi> and others. <hi>And the third Angell followed</hi> them, <hi>with a loud voice,</hi> denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing <hi>eternal</hi> damnation to every one that ſhould <hi>worſhip the Beaſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 15.6.</note> and his image, and <hi>receive his marke in his forhead, or in his</hi> hand. Yea the Lord ſent out of the Temple ſeaven Angels, <hi>haveing the ſeaven laſt plagues, clothed in pure and white linnen.</hi> After the four firſt had powred out theire vials,<note place="margin">Chap. 16.9.</note> In ſteade of amending them, it is ſaide, <hi>they blaſphemed the name of God, which hath power of theeſe plagues:</hi> that is, they blaſphemed the word of God, by which, beeing cleered, they were now ſcorched, as by fire: they blaſpheme the true and bright ſhining ſenſe, which now was ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted: <hi>And they repented not to give him glory.</hi> So when the fift Angel powred-out his vial upon the ſeate of the Beaſt,<note place="margin">Verſ. 10.</note> 
               <hi>and his Kingdom was full of darkneſſe:</hi> which ſeemeth to be donne in Pleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes his hiſtorie of the papacie, and the like works: by which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede his Kingdom, which many had thought to proceede from the light of Gods truth, appeared to be full of darkneſſe: For all this in juſtifying of it, they blaſpheme the <hi>God of heaven,</hi> and as it is added, <hi>they repented not of theire deedes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 12.</note> Therefore no marvaile if the next be powred out on the river Euphrates to drie vp the waters of it, that the way of the Kings of the Eaſt may be prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to deſtroy Babylon (where the river, as Babylon it ſelfe, mount Sion, Ieruſalem, the Temple and other things muſt needes be myſticall) and at the powring out of the ſeaventh vial ſhe comes <hi>in remembrance before God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 19.</note> to give her the cup of his wrathe, and then God calleth to his people to take heede of <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking of her ſinnes,</hi> that they receive not of her plagues.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:1648:6"/>
            <p>For as Chriſt ſaide of that Iezabel in Thiatira, <hi>J will caſt her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a bed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 2.</note> 
               <hi>and all that commit fornication with her into greate tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> So wee may be ſure will be donne vnto them that continue in any of the Babylonian corruptions. For conſider the meaning of that laſt clauſe, <hi>and all that commit adulterie with her.</hi> Which is not meant of them only that then lived in the boſom of that church, but of all others that then, or after ſhould fall into that her firſt errour; yea though they ſhould be, at enmitie with her, for her after errours, or not know her: there are none exempted that fall into the ſame errour, only, <hi>As many as have not this</hi> doctrine: marke, and ſo for the doctrine of the Nicolaitans, of Babylon, or any other: therefore if a man forſake all Babylons errours, ſave one; if he hold but one of the firſt, as this aboute Biſhops, which is the roote of all the reſt, he committeth adulterie with her in that, he pertaketh of her ſinnes, and may receive of her plagues. She hath many others. It is true, that all nations have drunk of them. The reformed churches have therefore diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered and abandoned them: Among which, the church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land will not acknowledge that, though ſhe retaine dioceſſan Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, theire courts &amp; power, in impoſing divers Romiſh cuſtoms, canons, and ceremonies, that yet theeſe are any part of the Babylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian corruptions, for which ſhe is taxed in the holy Scriptures, and at the laſt rewarded. Some, ſeeing Biſhops beare ſuch ſway in the church of England, do plainly affirme that they are of God, and ordained in the new Teſtament, knowing that other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſo greate power and authority in the church cannot be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,<note place="margin">Gal. 3.15.</note> ſeeing the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>though it be a mans Testament: yet if it be confirmed, no man diſſanulleth or addeth thereto,</hi> much leſſe to Gods. Others there are, that if you tell them, it was an inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Romaniſts, and other Clergie men, after the death of the Apoſtles: they ſo much reverence that church of Martyrs, that they care not much whether it be of the Apoſtles, or them, which is a verie greate follie and vanitie, ſeeing our Lord taxeth ſo many churches of thoſe times with greate corruptions, and it hath beene manifeſted that the church of Rome, both in this caſe, and many others, did quickly grow worſe then them all; that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:1648:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> many were the preſumptions and burdens, ſhe laide on the church; that the foundation of dioceſſan epiſcopacie, was ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the paſtors of greate cities, to be alwaies preſidents of Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods; which ſo increaſed theire authority, that in time the title of Biſhops came to be reſtrained to them, who beeing in ſuch power, were as readie to take it, as others in flatterie to give it.</p>
            <p>And why then ſhould ſo much be aſcribed to theire Synods, ſeeing ſo many fooliſh and preſumptious things were determined by them? As abouts Temples, Altars, Maſſes, veſtments, holy water, orders, Metropolitans, all verie ſuperſtitious, and ſo much for theire owne glorie, that An ichriſt roſe out of them? Our Lord ſaith, <hi>he that ſpeaketh, of him ſelfe ſeeketh his owne glorie:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 7.18.</note> 
               <hi>but he that ſeeketh his glorie that ſent him</hi> (by ſpeaking his truth, as in the two verſes before) the ſame is true and <hi>no vnrighteouſnes is in him:</hi> which argues,<note place="margin">Alſo chap. 8.38.</note> that they who ſpeake any thing beſides his revealed will, who ſpeake any thing beſides his truth, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund what he hath not commaunded, they are falſe and ſeeke theire owne glorie, yea, &amp; there is much vnrighteouſnes in them; they defile a church, they ſpeake that which they have ſeene with theire father; and that therefore thoſe prelates, who ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned theſe things ſought theire owne glorie, defiled the church, and were guided by other ſpirits, then the Spirit of Chriſt, who only <hi>taks</hi> of Chriſts, and ſhewes vnto men.<note place="margin">Chap. 16.13.14.</note> Which is alſo plaine by this, that, to theire owne glorie, they are more obſerved then the commaundements of God, as Lent, and other things then deviſed. So Teleſphorus ſought his owne glorie,<note place="margin">Platina in Teleſphor.</note> when he or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, <hi>That in the night of Chriſts birth day, three maſſos ſhould be celebrated, the firſt at midnight, when Chriſt was borne in Bethelem, the ſecond at the breake of day, when he was known to the Shepheards, the third at the time of the day when he was nailed on the croſſe: for after that hower it was forbidden to celebrate it.</hi> Becauſe Paul ſaith <hi>As oft as ye eate this bread, and drinke this cup, ye ſhew the Lords death:</hi> therefore in the primative church, they oft received the Sacrament, commonly once every Lords day; which was well. But this was no warrant for them to deviſe to ſhew his death by a kinde of Sacrifice, as Alexander firſt invented,<note place="margin">See Plati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Alex.</note> and ſomtime
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:1648:7"/> twiſe or thriſe in a morning in this ſuperſtitious manner: which ſoone ſerved hypocrits for a pretence of leſſe preaching, or hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe the word, growing ignorant, and making the maſſe, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained in thoſe times, the chiefe part of their religion, which muſt needes be much to theire glorie (in an Antichriſtian ſenſe) that ſpeaking of themſelves deviſed it, and were ſo followed in it.<note place="margin">Idem in Eleuther.</note> And ſo in ordaining dioceſſan Biſhops, Archbiſhops and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs after the example of the flamins, Archflamins, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toflamins, as Platina and others ſhew. Indeede all ordinances did greatly increaſe theire glorie, were they never ſo fooliſh; becauſe they, beeing in honour, had ſt ll flatterers to defend them, and perſwade obedience to them. Therefore, reade Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſus, Platina and others that write theire lives, and you ſhall finde there was then ſcarſe any. B. of Rome, that did not invent ſom ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, leaſt he ſhould be thought an ill huſband in increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the glorie of his Sea.<note place="margin">Idem in Zepherin. an. 198. Idem in Caliſt. and in Steph. 1</note> Zepherinus ordained <hi>that the cup in the Sacrament ſhould be of glaſſe, and no more of</hi> wood: as <hi>it was before. This was after altered and commaunded to be of gold, ſilver or pewter.</hi> Caliſtus <hi>ordained that there ſhould be a faſt thriſe a yeare on the ſatur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day for corne, wine and oyle,</hi> which after was <hi>changed to the faſt at fower times.</hi> Stephen 1. ordained <hi>that Prieſts ſhould not weare holy garments, but in the church and in celebrating holy rites, leaſt if they did otherwiſe, they ſhould fall into the ſinne of Balthaſar, who touched the holy veſſels with prophane hands.</hi> In the times of the Apoſtles, before preſbyters wore ſuch garments, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fore Surpleſſes, coapes and ſuch veſtments were taken from the h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>athen, there was litle neede of ſuch an ordinance. Howſoever the Scriptures do ſo forbid prophane cariage at all times, and in all Chriſtians, that this needed not to keepe prieſts from beeing drunke in theire Surpleſſes. What ſhould I ſpeak of hallowing grapes on the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, and ſuch like fooliſh ordinances? The verie ſhame of thoſe ages, and of them that ſo much reverence theire inventions, and canons for theire Antiquitie. But it is rather, becauſe Vrbanus made one which enricheth the Prelates; becauſe Dioniſius limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the confines of divers dioceſſes, and Cajus diſtinguiſhed the orders; becauſe though in all theſe things, they ſpake of them
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:1648:7"/> ſelves, yet they were confirmed in the councell of Nice who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede ſought Chriſts glorie, and ſpake out of his Teſtament in her creede. But whether ſhe ſpake of her ſelfe, or of theeſe Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of Rome, and theire inventions and cuſtoms, in her other Canons aboute Biſhops, the Reader may finde by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, if he doe but obſerve that rule of Chriſt:<note place="margin">Ioh. 7.17.</note> 
               <hi>If any man will doe his will,</hi> that is, be ordered by it, <hi>he ſhall know of the doctrine whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be of God, er whether J ſpeake of my ſelfe:</hi> Men can not know the truth in this point, becauſe they are not willing to know it, much leſſe to doe it, and hold it faſt, as they are willed.</p>
            <p>But becauſe God hath ſuffered dioceſſan Biſhops ſo many hundred yeares, and hath not ſodainly ſlaine them, when they began to innovate, as he did Nadab, Abihu, and Vzza, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men are ſo fooliſh, as to thinke he is ſo well pleaſed with the invention, that now it ſhould not be ſo much as queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; when they know, if that argument were good, the like might be ſaide for Antichriſt, who began to riſe and raigne with them: yet will not men ſee it. Much leſſe will they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, that as for leſſer preſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptions in the Corinthians, Paul ſaith, <hi>for this cauſe many are weake and ſick, and many ſleepe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.21.31.</note> ſo God pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed theſe, as well at theire firſt riſing, with the perſecutions, as ſince, with many plagues ſpiritual &amp; temporall.<note place="margin">Eccl. 8.11. Pſa. 50.21.</note> 
               <hi>Becauſe ſentence against an euill vvorke is not executed ſpeedily, therfore the heart of the Sonnes of men is fully ſet in them to doe euill. J kept ſilence and thou thoughteſt that I vvas altogether ſuch a one as thy ſelfe.</hi> That is wel enough pleaſed with thy works: <hi>But I vvil reproue thee and ſet them in order before thine eyes:</hi> and as the Prophet ſheweth,<note place="margin">Ier. 5.1.3.4.5. Iſa. 26.9.10.11.</note> God inflicteth his puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts on a citie or people, to make them <hi>ſeeke</hi> his <hi>truth</hi> and to bring them to the knowledge of it: O <hi>Lord are not thine eyes vpon the truth? thou haſt ſtricken them, but they haue not grieued, for they know not the way of the Lord, they haue broken the yoke &amp; burst the bonds. When thy Judgments are in the earth, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the world will learne righteouſnes.</hi> The godly will, <hi>but let fauour be ſhewed to the wicked, yet will he not learne righteouſneſſe:</hi> Nor yet when the hand of God is vpon them:<note place="margin">Exod. 32, 34.</note> 
               <hi>When thy hand is lifted vp, they will not ſee: But they ſhall ſee &amp; be aſhamed for their
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1648:8"/> enuie at the people:</hi> and as he ſaith in a like caſe. <hi>In the day vvhen I viſit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 12.1. Habak. 1.13.</note> 
               <hi>I will viſit theire ſinne vpon them.</hi> In the meane time, why ſhould any godly man be ſo moved at their proſperitie, as to put forth his hand to their wickedneſſe? or in diſcontent to ſay, <hi>wherfore doth the way of the wicked proſper, wherefore are all they happy, that deale verie trecherouſly?</hi> For then he will make them to ſee, that his church is called <hi>the Tabernacle of the Testimonie. The Temple of the Tabernacle of the Testimonie in heauen was opened;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 15.5. Chap. 11.19.</note> 
               <hi>And ther was ſeene in it the Ark of his Teſtament.</hi> To ſhew vs; that as, vnder the firſt Teſtament, all things concerning the Prieſts &amp; the ſervice, was to continue according to the firſt inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 2.28</note> ſo ought it to be vnder the new. <hi>I did giue,</hi> ſaith God, to Elie) <hi>vnto</hi> the <hi>howſe thy Father all the offerings made by fire,</hi> to let him know, they ought to haue been contented with what God had giuen them, and not to take more, as his Sonnes did: the Teſtimonie was as well concerning the office and right of the Prieſts as other things, there was not any thing to be ſuffered of coueteouſnes, ambitious vſurpation, or humane inuention.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 19.19.20.</note>So was it to be vnder the new Teſtament. For when God by Moſes had ſpoken of Chriſt, and that which he ſhould ſpeake <hi>in his name,</hi> it is added in the next words, <hi>But the Prophet which ſhall preſume to ſpeake a word in my name, which I haue not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded him to ſpeake, euen that Prophet ſhall die.</hi> And when Chriſt ſaith,<note place="margin">Reu. 22.18.</note> 
               <hi>If a man ſhall adde vnto</hi> theſe <hi>things, God ſhall adde vnto him the plagnes written in this booke;</hi> wee are not onely to take it of thruſting things into the text, or adding to it; but of ſpeaking, and in his name impoſing on Churches and people things in religion, which he commaunded not. God ſo taxed this fault in the Iewes,<note place="margin">Iſa. 29.13. Mat. 15.8.</note> that he counted all things yea theyr verie worſhipping of him to <hi>be vaine,</hi> while this was ſuffered. Becauſe in the primatiue Church, men did not ſtriue to ouercome the intruding of inuentions, by holding faſt Chriſts works vnto the end, but let in, now a litle and then a litle, the truth was daily betrayed and loſt, and ſo it muſt needes be where they are maintained, the leſſer preſumptions make way for the greater. Gods word and truth is his glorie;<note place="margin">Pſa. 4.3.</note> But, ſaith he, <hi>how long will ye
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:1648:8"/> turne my glorie into ſhame?</hi> yet this they doe, who would make it defend, or allow, the inventions and precepts of men. This is a harlot like trick, to giue, her huſbands goods and glorie, to her adulterers; But as Iſrael and Iudah did it, ſo haue Chriſtian Churches. Thou ô Rome waſt at firſt a famous Church, but like them,<note place="margin">Ezech. 15. Eſa. 48.8. chap. 1.</note> thou didſt <hi>truſt in thine owne beautie and playedſt the harlot becauſe of thy renowne;</hi> thou didſt deale very trecherouſly <hi>and waſt called a tranſgreſſor from the wombe. How ſoone did the faithfull citie become an Harlot? It was full of judgment, righteouſnes lodged in it. But now murderers &amp;c, The Prophets Propheſie falſly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 5.31.</note> 
               <hi>and the Prieſts beare rulle by theire meanes, and my people loue to haue it ſo: and</hi> what will they <hi>doe in the end thereof?</hi> I anſwer they made a like cuſtom, and long continuance a warrant for theire inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as they doe, that vpon like grounds defend euill. They <hi>deſpiſe the Law of the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos. 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>And their lies cauſed them to erre after which their Fathers walked.</hi> They would rather doe as their Fa hers had donne and taught, then as God commaunded. By reaſon thereof men talke in vaine, that tell them of Gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. <hi>They cannot hearken:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 6.10.</note> 
               <hi>Behold the word of the Lord is vnto them a reproach: they haue no delight in it. I haue written to him the greate things of my Law, but they where counted as a ſtrange thing.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 8.12.</note> And the reaſon is well giuen, <hi>Can the Ethiopian change his ſkin? Or the Leopard his ſpots?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chap. 13.23.</note> 
               <hi>then may ye alſo doe good that are accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to doe evill.</hi> All men are ſubject to finde excuſes, and even to wreſt the Scriptures to defend ancient cuſtome<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>It was Gods gracious promiſe vnto them for all this:<note place="margin">Iſa. 1.25.26. Chap. 2.12.</note> 
               <hi>I will purge away thy droſſe: And I will reſtore thy Iudges as at the firſt, &amp; thy counſellours as at the beginning.</hi> Wee ſaw he hath promiſed as much in the caſe of his church: <hi>for the day of the Lord of hoſts ſhalbe upon every one that is proud and loftie, that is lifted up, and he ſhall be brought low.</hi> In the meane while, wee muſt know,<note place="margin">Chap. 5.1.</note> he <hi>planted a vinyard in a very fruitfull hill, and he fenced it: he looked that it ſhould bring forth grapes, and it brought forth wild grapes:</hi> therfore he <hi>tooke away the hedge thereof, and it was not digged and pruned</hi> as it ſhould be. So was the hedge taken from the church in the time of the perſecutions, when ſhe brought forth the wilde grapes of mens
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1648:9"/> inventions.<note place="margin">Iſa. 24.5. Ezech. 5.6 Amos. 2.4</note> Men will confeſſe it was for ſome ſinne, as Iſrael was alwaies plagued, <hi>Becauſe they tranſgreſſed the lawes, changed the ordinance</hi> (marke, changed the ordinance) <hi>brake the everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting covenant.</hi> Though they kept it in fundamentall points of religion, yet with Korah, and Vzzah they brake and changed it in Eccleſiaſticall order, ſervice and ceremonies, which opened the gap to greater tranſgreſſions. Had they continued in his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, doubtles they had never beene ſo afflicted, he would have beene to them as he promiſed to Iſrael,<note place="margin">Exod. 34.24.</note> 
               <hi>I will cast out the nations before thee, and enlarge thy borders: neither ſhall any man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire thy land, when thou ſhalt goe up to appeare before the Lord thrice in the yeare;</hi> he would ſo have ruled theire enemies hearts: but when men obſerve not his ordinances, or like the Angels keepe not theire firſt eſtate, then by his plagues, he ſeekes to abate theire pride. Now wee ſhall have ſeene that in the primative church, the Clergie did ſoone decline from his waies in ſuch things, &amp; were plagued,<note place="margin">Iſa. 9.16. Chap. 52. Chap. 42.24. Chap. 8.16</note> both they and theire people. <hi>For the Leaders of this people cauſe them to erre, and they that are led of them are deſtroied. So, they that rule over them make them to howle, and my name con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuallie every day is blaſphemed. Who gave Jacob for a ſpoile, and Jſrael to the Robbers? Did not the Lord, he against whom wee have ſinned? for they would not walke in his waies, &amp;e.</hi> And therfore he ſaith <hi>binde up the Testimonie, Seale the law among my Diſciples,</hi> Certaine that lived deſpiſed in corners, and perſecuted, even of ſome of theire owne brethren, while <hi>he hid his face from the howſe of Jacob.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 2:30. Iſa. 57.17.</note> 
               <hi>For,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>in vaine have I ſmitten your children they received no correction: your owne ſword hath devoured your Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets &amp;c. For the iniquitie of his coveteouſnes was I wroth and ſmote him. J hid me and he went on frowardly in the way of his owne heart.</hi> So that Coveteouſnes hath in all ages beene the roote of all evill,<note place="margin">Ier. 6.13.</note> eſpecially in church-men. <hi>For every one is given to coveteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> (and what followeth thereupon) <hi>from the Prophet to the Prieſt, every one dealeth falſely: And they bend theire tongue like theire bow for lies</hi> (ſuch as are for theire honour or proffit) <hi>but they are not valiant for the truth.</hi> Such was the fruite of coveteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and ambition in Elies Sonnes; ſuch in Gehezi, in Ziba and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1648:9"/> others, as well of the Prieſts as of the people; and ſuch hath it ever beene as well in the chriſtian, as in the Iewiſh churches. There was doubtles a luſt of the eies after the pride of life, a ſeeking after preheminence and authority in the Biſhops of Rome from the verie death of the Apoſtles. Theire deviſes to ſuperintend over neighbour churches, or pariſhes, and theire Decrees in theire Synods, wherin they for the moſt part ruled all for theire owne glorie, do ſufficiently declare it: this was the foundation of theire greatnes. And ſom deſire there might be of filthie lucre: but the firſt open proofe recorded is that decree of Vrbanus,<note place="margin">Platina in Vrban. 1.</note> 
               <hi>that the church might receive from the faithfull, inheritance of lands:</hi> This was aboute the yeare 224. For before times the preaching Biſhop was maintained by that which the ſeaven Deacons gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for the poore and church vſes, as both Damaſus and Platina ſhew in the life of Evariſtus, who died for the Truth in the yeare 109. and was, it ſeemes, the laſt of the vncorrupt Paſtors of that litle flock in Rome. He preſumed not to make ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; And ſo as Hegeſippus ſaith, <hi>to the times of Trajan, or therea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouts, the church continued cleane and vndefiled, as a virgin;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſeb. lib. 3. c. 26. &amp; lib. 4. c. 21.</note> 
               <hi>but ſince that ſacred companie left the world, the conſpiracie of iniquitie began to worke with open face.</hi> They tell vs indeede of an ordinance that his predeceſſor Annaclet made againſt Clergie mens nouriſhing of long haire, in head or beard:<note place="margin">Platina in Anaclet. 1. Cor. 11.14.</note> which haveing reſpect to that of the Apoſtle, ſeemed tollerable. But the Apoſtles words were ſufficient, what neede ſuch an ordinance? yet if he made it, that ſerved for a pretence, that they might make others. The like may be ſaide of that commaund of his, <hi>that the conſecration beeing ended, all the faithfull ſhould communicate, or they that would not, ſhould goe out of the church.</hi> Theſe theire beſt preceps were ſteps to intollerable preſumptions in others; as in Alexander who, ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Euariſtus, ordained holy water, the maſſe and other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, which others increaſed: So was this of Vrbanus a ſtep to extreme coveteouſnes, and many other corruptions.</p>
            <p>Cyprian yeeldeth this reaſon of the perſecution of Decius,<note place="margin">Cyprian lib. de lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis.</note> 
               <hi>Becauſe every man ſlept in the coveteous deſires of his owne heart, it was high time for God to awak them with his rod; There was no longer
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1648:10"/> any devotion left in the prieſts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Anno 253</note> 
               <hi>no ſincere faith in miniſters, no mercie in theire works, no government in their manners &amp;c. The Biſhops them ſelves who ſhould have ſerved for a ſpurre and patterne of well doeing, abandoning theire holy functions and forſaking theire flocks, goe a gad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding into other countries, haunting marts and faires for filthie lucres ſake, litle caring to relieve theire hungrie and ſtarving brethren, ſo themſelues might haue money at will; getting lands by fraude, and money by griping vſurie: and what did wee not deſerue for theſe ill doeings?</hi> The Churches, ye ſee; were not the more purified, but more defiled after dioceſſan Biſhops were ſet vp. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer this ſhewes theire follie, who aſcribe ſo much to the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and holines of thoſe times. Euſebius giues the like reaſons of the perſecution of Diocleſian,<note place="margin">Platina in Marcel.</note> as Platina obſerveth, <hi>ſaying, Euſebius imagineth that it was permitted of God for the corrupt man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, with the too much libertie and indulgence of the Christians, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiallie of the Clergie, to bridle whoſe perverſnes, the divine justice or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained this perſecution, while he ſaw diſſembling in theire countenance, fraud in their hearts, and deceite in theire words. For theſe ſtriving among themſelves with envie, pride, enmities, hatreds, ſeemed to ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iour more of a tyrannie then of the Priesthood, alltogether forg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng the Chriſtian pietie, and rather profaning then celebrating the divine miſteries. But what then,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>doe we think will becom of our age, Wherein our vices are increaſed to that height, that they haue ſcarce left for vs a place of mercie with God? How litle Religion is there, and that rather diſſembled then true?</hi> (he might haue ſaide, and that rather after mens inventions, then Gods ordinances) <hi>what corrupt manner &amp;c.</hi> Euſebius ſay more, yet I haue choſen to allege him in Platinaes words, to keepe malicious mindes from pretending deceite, in alleadging it.</p>
            <p>Men may well thinke, that when with conſtantine there en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred ſuch a deale of peace and plentie, there muſt needes be more corruption. Theire owne Authors ſhew it; for Baronius ſaith,<note place="margin">Baron. in 324. art. 78. &amp; 79.</note> Conſtantine, <hi>in the 24 yeare of his raigne, ordained that the Biſhops ſhould from that time forward haue the ſame Priueliedges, which the idolatrous Prieſts had enjoyed in times paſt. They had,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>as chiefe among them Rex Sacrificulus, who in ſolemne feasts was wont to watch and haue an eye ouer the rest. They had alſo theire
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:1648:10"/> Soueraigne Pontife,</hi> Pontifex Maximus, <hi>Arbitrator of all queſtions ariſing among them: and who can think,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that Conſtantine could longe endure that theſe ſhould exceede Chriſtians in pompe and glorie?</hi> He might haue ſaide, that the Biſhops of Rome could long endure it? Howſoeuer this was the goodly reaſon of theire greatnes, contrarie to that of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Luk. 22.</note> 
               <hi>the Kings of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles exerciſe Lordſhip ouer them, &amp;c. but ye ſhall not be ſo:</hi> Yet Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius ſheweth the Pope and Cardinals to haue the honour in riding, clothing and other things, that theſe Pontifes had. It appeares in Platina, on the like of Eleutherus, that the power of Biſhops, Archbiſhops and Patriarchs was taken from the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of theſe pagans: they were then onely held in titles of like nature: but now in the power, pompe and riches of them. Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor Virgil alſo acknowledgeth that many things haue com into the Church of Rome from the Hebrewes, the ancient Romans,<note place="margin">De invent rerum. l. 5. c. 1. Book of the Iubile ſee the Root of Romiſh Rites.</note> and other Pagans. M. Derlincourt proueth this out of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Mande, Gratian, and divers others of their owne Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors; and among other things, that the dignities and power of Biſhops, Archbiſhops, and Patriarchs, were taken from the heathen. And for theire wealth Cedrenus in his Hiſtorie ſaith, that Conſtantine <hi>in the</hi> 26 and <hi>27 yeares of his Empire laboured to pull downe the idols, and to conuey theire rents and revenues to the Churches.</hi> From this greatnes of dignitie and wealth, there ſoone followed a greatnes of power and tyranie, in impoſing the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Lawes, aboute ſupremacie, worſhipping of images, praying to Saints, ſingle life of Prieſts, purgatorie, pardons, and the like. Was not Babylon fallen in all this? Was not here a manifeſt change of Chriſts ordinances, aboute Biſhops and other things?</p>
            <p>Excommunication was at firſt a puniſhment inflicted by many, not of one. But they haueing made one breach,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 6. and 2. Theſſ. 3 14. Hiſtor. of the counc. of Trent. l. 4. p. 331.</note> to ſet vp a kinde of dioceſſan Biſhops, the myſterie of iniquitie could not reſt there; but as one ſaith, <hi>the members of the Churches, neglecting theire duties, at laſt left all to the Biſhops, who out of ambition embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced it, and, the perſecutions ceaſing, erected a tribunall, which was much frequented. That yet they judging honestly at the first, Conſtantine
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1648:11"/> made a Law, that there ſhould lie no appeale from the Sentences of the Biſhops: which authority they abuſing, that Law aboute</hi> 70 <hi>yeares after was revoked by Arcadius and Honorius, and one made that they ſhould not be thought to haue a court: which was executed in Rome it ſelfe, and after by <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alentinian</hi> ſtrengthened by another Law to that purpoſe. This was not digging vp the roote of the myſterie of iniquitie, by taking away this dioceſſan power and reſtoring the Elderſhip, whereof not onely Princes, but euen Clergie men were now growne ignorant, but lopping the branches, which after grew and ſpread more then euer: for this power <hi>thus taken away was reſtored by Juſtinian, who,</hi> 500 <hi>yeares</hi> after Chriſt, <hi>eſtabliſhed vnto them a court and audience.</hi> And after the power of Biſhops greatly increaſed, <hi>when they came to be Councellours to King and Princes,</hi> and to beare offices vnder them, as to be Chancellours, Treaſurors and the like. Whereby theire Canons, power, traditions and Ceremonies, came to be receiued with the greater authority, and no man durſt gainſay them, were they never ſo ſuperſtitious, popiſh, and tyranicall. All this came from theire firſt preſumptions, in not abiding in the ordinance and Wiſdom of God, touching the Ederſhip, as they were wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, but giue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng a kinde of authority and ſuperintendencie to the Paſtor or Biſhop of greate cities, ouer the leſſer townes and all preſbiters aboute them. For thus Biſhops, by that meanes, encroached from one ſtep to another, till at laſt the verie name of the preſbiterie grew odious vnto them, as it doth now to the Biſhops and theire defenders in England: where all proofes of it are prohibited, and more carefully kept from Princes and people, then any Popiſh Doctrine, and as if they were as dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, as the Blaſphemies of Arrius, and other monſters. And thus blinded by ambition, coueteouſnes and flatterie, <hi>they despiſe the Law of the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos. 2.</note> 
               <hi>and theire lies cauſed them to erre after which theire Fathers walked:</hi> they would rather doe as theire Fathers had donne and taught, then as God commaunded: And thus wee ſee that the Lord may ſay vnto them,<note place="margin">Mal. 3.7.</note> 
               <hi>Euen from the dayes of your Fathers, ye are gon away from mine ordinances, and haue not kept them.</hi> And which is a greater miſchiefe, the antiquitie of this
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1648:11"/> wicked wandring, is made an authority againſt the old and good way, as againſt a foolerie, and againſt all that ſeeke it as againſt Hypocrites, fooles, and Schiſmatikes: By reaſon whereof,<note place="margin">Ier. 6.10.</note> men talke in vaine that tell them of Gods ordinance, or the new Ieruſalem, wherein they ſhall be reſtored: <hi>they cannot hearken: Behold the word of the Lord is vnto them a reproach,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 6.12.</note> 
               <hi>they haue no delight in it.</hi> God writeth to them <hi>the greate things of his Law, but they are counted as a ſtrange thing:</hi> groundles and mad opinions, worthy impriſſonment, baniſhment and what not? It is a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull thing, that men ſhould profeſſe to liue in the light and obedience of the Goſpel, and yet like hypocrites deſpiſe it in any thing, as they doe in matter of the preſbiterie, and thoſe gracious promiſes of the new Ieruſalem, which are confirmed and ſealed in the new Teſtament with the blood of the Sonne of God. I confeſſe, it is thus in many of the gentrie and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, becauſe they are not ſuffred to ſee any proofes of it: If any be not willing to ſee them, that is worſe. But in the Prelates, many Clergie men, yea and ſom Princes, who haue ſeene proofs of theeſe things, or might if they would, and yet ſcorne and reject them, as follie, and matters of reproach, and worthy cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection &amp; perſecution, it is a plaine treading <hi>vnder foote the Sonne of God,</hi> who hath<note n="*" place="margin">Reu. 1.1.11.19. and Ioh. 16.13.</note> reuealed the Father in theeſe things, <hi>and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the blood of the couenant an vnholy</hi> thing, wherewith the new Teſtament was ſanctified, confirmed or dedicated, as the firſt covenant was with the blood of beaſts: yea, this is to doe deſpite vnto the Spirit of grace, which firſt ſhewes vs Gods grace in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining theſe things, and after in promiſes of reſtoring them.</p>
            <p>And indeede ſeeing it is manifeſt,<note place="margin">Act. 14. chap. 20.28. 1. Pet. 5.2. Tit. 1.9.</note> that the Apoſtles <hi>ordained Elders in euery Church</hi> that theire office was <hi>to feede the flock, ouer which the Holy Ghoſt made them Biſhops;</hi> that they were to <hi>take the overſight thereof,</hi> by ſound Doctrine <hi>to convince the gainſayers,</hi> reproue, correct and inſtruct in righteouſnes; and if this would not ſerue, after the firſt and ſecond admonition to excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, in and with the conſent of the congregation, who can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, but that all this is of the ſubſtance of religion neceſſarie to the ſalvation of the people, and proper to euery Proſbyter.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:1648:12"/> Euery man will be readie to confeſſe, that it is better there be a Pilot, a Maiſter, and a Maiſters mate, in euery ſhip, to watch ouer the ſame, and all that is in it, as the Lord in Wiſdom ordained Elders to be Biſhops in euery Church, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, to watch over it, and all the Soules therin, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them in his Teſtament a card, and rules to ſteere and ſaile by, the word of God, beeing theire Rudder, then that there ſhould be but one in a whole fleete, one Biſhop in a dioceſſe, and all the reſt but ſhadowes, or leſſer wheeles, to be led and moved by him, as it came to paſſe by the wiſdom and encroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of men: wherby Biſhops neither leaving the brethren, nor yet the presbyters any voice in cenſures, or part in the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, doe themſelves bring in the inventions and evils Chriſt would keepe out, get dominion over mens faith, and by theire power, and traditions, make the word of none effect in divers perticulars. A thing which is expreſly forbidden in the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament. <hi>My brethren be not many Maiſters, knowing that wee ſhall receive the greater condemnation:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 3.1.</note> that is, becauſe in the cauſes and controverſies of hereticks,<note place="margin">Pſal. 100.</note> Schiſmatiks and other delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents, it is ſaide of the word, <hi>Rule thou in the midſt of thine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: He ſhall judge amonge the nations:</hi> the Preſbyters and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the church doe but rule and judge by him, as ſteeres men by the Rudder, judges and jurots by the law, not by theire owne inventions or pretended authority: And therfore our ſaviour, who was againſt all ſuch dominion in the church, ſaith to his Diſciples,<note place="margin">Mat. 20.25. Chap. 123.8.</note> 
               <hi>The Princes of the Gentiles exerciſe dominion over them: But ye ſhall not not be ſo. Be not ye called Rabbi: for one is your Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, even Chriſt, and all ye are brethren.</hi> Therfore when there is cauſe of accuſing or cenſuring any, he doth not ſay, Tell the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, but <hi>Tell the church.</hi> And accordingly in the times of the Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Chap. 18.17.</note> and longe after, as the epiſtles of Cyprian do manifeſt, they were judged by the word in an aſſemblie of preſbyters and brethren, as the inceſtuous Corinthian: which ſhewes us, that neither one man, nor the preſbiters alone, were judges in ſuch caſes, but the church: which by the Scriptures either cleered or cenſured any perſon accuſed, as by the word of God he appeared,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1648:12"/> either guiltie or not guiltie: for ſo doth the word judge among the nations: And therfore ſeeing, God hath ſo ordained, and it was in the primitive church ſo practiſed, it is not a thing indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, as ſome thinke, whether Preſbyters or dioceſſan Biſhops hold the government, but in effect a matter of ſalvation, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially to every church, and by conſequence to every Soule in it; as the well or ill guiding of a ſhip concerneth the ſalvation of every paſſenger embarqued in it. For though in a tempeſt, ſome are ſaved without good Pilots, and ſome in the ſhipwrack by a board: yet others are not without ſkilfull ſea men: and ſoe in the church, but for the moſt part not without helpes in govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. God hath in nothing given this to one in a dioceſſe, and his officials, but to the preſbyters of every church, elected accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his ordinance.</p>
            <p>For though the proviſion of Biſhops and Paſtors have beene ſomtime in the hands of the Clergie and people; ſomtimes in the hands of K ngs and Patrons: then in the hands of Popes. and then againe in the hands of Kings and patrons, as now in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t, as many have proved, for the firſt ſeaven or eight hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares after Chriſt, the people in moſt places did chooſe them, according to the practiſe of the primative church, and the power given them in the new Teſtament: For ſo ſaith Cyprian, <hi>The people have principallie the power either to chooſe ſuch priests as are worthy or to refuſe ſuch as are vnworthy.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cypri. 1. Epiſt. 4. Act. 14.23 Beza. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not. in Act. 14. Tit. 1.</note> And ſo ſaith Luke, <hi>They ordained them Elders in every church by election. Where,</hi> ſaith Beza, <hi>the force of the word</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>is to be noted, that wee may know that Paul and Barnabas caried nothing by private will, nor exerciſed any tyranie in the church, nor lastly did any ſuch thing, as at this day the Romiſh harlot or her pages doe, whome they call ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</hi> And by this place, ſaith he, <hi>must that be vnderſtood, I left thee in Creete to ordaine them Elders in everie citie, as I had appointed thee;</hi> that is by election, as the Apoſtles left it to the church and people there aſſembled to chooſe one in the place of Iudas:<note place="margin">Beza An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not. in Act. 1.</note> 
               <hi>And they appointed two. Nothing,</hi> ſaith Beza, <hi>is here caried privately by Peter, as by one endued with a more excellent dignitie, but publickly and by the ſuffrages of the whole church:</hi> So, as he ſheweth, were
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:1648:13"/> the ſeaven Deacons choſen; and ſo is that to be vnderſtood, <hi>Lay hands ſodainly on no man,</hi> that is to make him a preſbyter, amd ſo give him a part in this charge of the Elderſhip till he be tried, the church or people have choſen him, and praier be made for him, as at the election of Mathias and the ſeaven Deacons. It is ill for the Soules of Kings, Biſhops and patrons, and indeede worſe for the church, that any one of theſe have the choice or confirmation of Paſtors, helpers &amp; Elders, which are lawfull cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, or of dioceſſan Biſhops, Deanes, prebends and others which are vnlawfull: For this makes divines flatter all ſuch Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Patrons and Prelates or theire favourites, and ſo is cauſe of exceeding greate corruption and hipocriſie in church and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth. For by this meanes Princes, Prelates and theire fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourites, though they doe what they liſt in religion, ſhall be ſure to be flattered in it, as the popes were, as ſoone as ever they grew greate, and to have any power over the Clergie: and this indeede made them attempt what they liſt, and carrie or obtaine it, while verie few durſt call it incroaching or corruption, ſuch was and ſuch is the fruite of this power in the church, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God would neither commit the election or confirmation of his miniſters, nor the government to one in a dioceſſe, but to the preſbyters and members of every church as aboveſaide. Men will not ſee theſe things: but if wee tell them, theſe all doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to the decrees of Chriſt; to ſtop our mouthes, with thoſe Iewes and others <hi>of the baſer ſort,</hi> they ſay, <hi>Theſe all doe contrarie to the decrees of Ceſar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 17.5.7.</note> 
               <hi>ſaying, that there is another King, in theſe caſes, namely Christ:</hi> making a verie heinous matter of it, that wee are ſo bold as to affirme it. But it were to be wiſhed that they would ſo give vnto Ceſar the things that are Ceſars, as not to take from God the things that are Gods to give them to Ceſar. Theſe are things that have been manifeſted to be Gods. Why then will they perſwade Kings, that they doe God ſervice and ſhew love to his church, his Ieruſalem, while they ſtrengthen the Prelates that vſurpe theſe offices, ſuppreſſe the verie name of the preſbiterie, and make Princes beleeve that as they doe more or leſſe vphold theire hierarchie, ſo God will more or leſſe bleſſe them &amp; theirs.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:1648:13"/> Wherein they reaſon like Baronius,<note place="margin">Baron. in an. 452,</note> who ſpeaking of the law of Valentinian abovementioned, which curtailed the power of Biſhops, ſaith <hi>That the making of it incenſed the wrath of God, and cauſed Attila with the Hunnes to come downe upon the Empire.</hi> When that was rather becauſe he left them ſo much power as he did, and did not rather reduce them to that order and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer wherein the Apoſtles left them, taking away all that which made the word of God in divers particulars of none effect, or is contrarie to his ordinances, though it had been given them by Emperours or Synods. They ſhould have all knowne, that it is <hi>the King eternall and immortall, who is only wiſe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 1.17. Iſa. 30.22. Pro. 8.</note> mark that word <hi>onelie wiſe,</hi> eſpecially in Spirituall things: The Lord <hi>is our Iudge, the Lord is our lawgiver the Lord is our King.</hi> Chriſt beeing the wiſdom of God ſaith, <hi>By me Kings raigne and Princes decree ju<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtice:</hi> that is, when what they can, they governe according to Gods revealed wiſdom. Much more then in matters of religion; they are not ſet in the throne, to doe and require the doeing of theire owne will, but Gods, as David acknowledged, and therefore ſaide, <hi>Give thy judgments ô God</hi> (thy judgments, not mens, not mine) <hi>to the King, and thy righteouſnes to the Kings Sonne.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 70.1 2. Chron. 29.23. 2 Sam. 22.51. 1 Chro. 29 11.12.</note> So it is ſaide, <hi>Solomon ſate on the throne of the Lord inſteade of David his father;</hi> who is ſaide to be Gods King. Every king therefore ſhould acknowledge God King of his kingdom, as David of his, <hi>Thine o Lord is the greatnes, &amp; the power &amp; the glorie, &amp; the victorie, and the majeſtie: for all that is in the heaven &amp; in the earth is thine: thine is the kingdom o Lord, &amp; thou art exalted as head above all:</hi> that is, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> above Kings, who beeing ſet on the throne of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that is to ſee his word, his lawes &amp; Statutes obſerved, to ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp; the righteouſnes thereof: for then doe they bring theire glorie &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to the new Ieruſalem:<note place="margin">Hoſ. 2.19.</note> then is he maried to them and theire pepole <hi>ín righteouſnes, in judgment, in loveing kindnes &amp; in mercies,</hi> as he promiſeth: that is when Kings make prieſts, and people live and doe according to the order which he appointeth them in his word, as both Hezechiah and David himſelfe did, when he ſaw Vzza ſlaine for breaking that order. He ſits on the throne of the Lord that gives his power &amp; ſtrength to God and to his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:1648:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> as the Kings, which are the hornes of the Beaſt, gave theire power and ſtrength vnto the Beaſt, to enforce his lawes, rites and errours on theire people, which was a war againſt the lambe; But at laſt, as is graciouſly promiſed, <hi>The lambe ſhall over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 17.</note> 
               <hi>For he is the Lord of Lords and King of Kings.</hi> If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they will be ſaide to ſit on his throne, they muſt doe the like for Chriſt againſt Antichriſt, and all enemies of his truth, ſeeing God hath ſet his King vpon his holy hill of Sion, to rule all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in matters of religion, and therefore addeth <hi>Be wiſe now therefore o ye Kings.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 2.</note> Let it not be ſaide your ſubjects dwell where Sathan hath his throne for Antichriſt or any other. David knew the true wiſdom when he ſaide,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 22.22.</note> 
               <hi>J have kept the waies of the Lord, and have not wickedly departed from my God: for all his judgments were before me,</hi> &amp;c. And when in an aſſemblie of all his Princes, Captaines,<note place="margin">1. Chro. 28 1.8.9.</note> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to them, <hi>Keepe and ſeeke for all the com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th Solomon and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, but if</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>re did God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e a King among his Sonnes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 paragraph">
                     <desc>〈1 paragraph〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> He w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s a King indee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or God, ſeeing he thus raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,<note place="margin">pſa, 47.3.</note> and in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enſe had ever ſuch ſayi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gs in his mouth <hi>God is the King of all the Earth; The ſhields of the eart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> belong unto God. For the Lord is a greate God, and a grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> King above all Gods. The holy one of Iſrael is our King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The prelates and theire adherents ſay, there muſt be order in the church<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> dioceſſan Biſhops to be over others,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Objection</note> queſtion and reje<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers. God hath not appoin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> therefore Kings and councels <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> I anſwer this is to ſay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> God hath not had a ſufficient <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rch, and to accuſe his Teſtament of inſufficiencie, as if th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d not as well provided for his church in this caſe, as in others<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when yet for theſe ends, he ordained Elders to be Biſhops <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> every congregation. Now all his ordinances are perfect. <hi>His worke is perfect:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut 32.4</note> 
               <hi>for all his waies are judgment.</hi> He is God and changeth not: therefore to ſay, that this was only for the times
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:1648:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> of the Apoſtles, and as the church increaſed and thoſe times changed, the wiſdom of men might provide better, is a greate preſumption: yet ſuch hath beene the wiſdom of the fleſh,<note place="margin">Act. 15.18</note> and of the world to thinke ſo: But <hi>knowne vnto God are all his works from the begining of the world.</hi> Men cannot in time better them. If the Elderſhip had not beene ſufficient, he would either never have ordained it, to be ſo ſoone aboliſhed, or have foretold and given authority to his church to ordaine dioceſſans. This he did not, but for bad to adde to his word,<note place="margin">Mar. 13.34</note> becauſe himſelfe <hi>gave au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to his ſervants,</hi> the Apoſtles, <hi>and to every man his worke.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.11.12.</note> And by them he hath ſet ſufficient officers in the church, <hi>for the perfecting of the ſaints, for the worke of the ministrie,</hi> &amp;c. And what can wee have more. If men would but ſee it, the Elders in the Reformed churches do better looke to the order God requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, then dioceſſan Biſhops do or can. For this order is ſhewed in his Teſtament: That is per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>: and he ſaith,<note place="margin">Deut. 12.32. Gal. 3.15.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not adde thereto, nor dim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſh fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m it.</hi> It <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> true<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> us like Vzz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, doe more then Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> commaundeth; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ey look to diver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> things that Elders doe not once look afte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is then after mens tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and commaundements, <hi>which turne from the truth,</hi> are po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh, tyranical and ſuperfluous while by obſtinate defending theſe, <hi>they make diviſions and contentions,</hi> contrarie to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolike doctrine, and ſo <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ve not the Lord Jeſus Christ,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 16.</note> 
               <hi>but theire owne bellie, and by good words and faire ſpeeches deceive the hearts of the ſimple;</hi> this is not to vphold the church of Chriſt, but theire owne kingdom.</p>
            <p>It will be ſaide ſome of them ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d written well, yea confirmed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eſſed Heret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> but theire numbe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> did in the chur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h of Rome, wherein ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Biſhops, Monkes and Ieſuits confute ſom he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>ks and preach well in all things ſave for the maintenance of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ire orders and ſuperſtition: So doe Engliſh prelats. How ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at hath beene as well if not better performed by other mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> at home and in the reformed churches.<note place="margin">Hiſtor. of the coun. of Trent. p. 24.</note> There have beene divers honeſt Popes, who have confeſt ſom errours in the power and practiſe of the church; as of late Adrian 6. who ſending to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:1648:15"/> the Diet of Noremberg confeſſeth many corruptions in the ſea and Church of Rome, and promiſeth reformation: But this makes the calling of Popes neuer a whit the more Lawfull or neceſſarie. As it was with Popes, ſo it is with Biſhops, the better ſom of them haue beene, the worſe for the Church: for they doe but hold vp the reputation of the office, and ſo hold way for worſe ſucceſſors &amp; theire traditions.</p>
            <p>Neyther is it better for the ſuppreſſing of heritikes and leude liuers, that one in a dioceſſe hath this power: for he cannot looke to all the Clergie, much leſſe to all the people, though he ſhould minde nothing elſe: How then can he doe it, if he be a counſellour of Eſtate, and a judge in the Starchamber and high commiſſion? Among the Clergie in England (and much more among the people, many are ſaide to be drunkards, coueteous, contentious, hereticall, Arminians, non reſidents, dumbe mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, zealous defenders of canons and ceremonies, preaching litle elſe, Popelings, dunces, drones, perſecutors of thoſe that preach and heare the word diligently. If the Biſhop who cannot looke to all, ſee not the moſt of them, countena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce others, or be by any meanes made to connive, they may keepe theire Churches, and others from preaching in them, and doe no good, but much hurt in them: which is not ſo in the Churches of France, where there are few, or rather none of this kinde: that diſcipline hath eaſy meanes to remedie theſe things, both in the Clergie and people, or rather indeede, it preventeth them; ſo much better is that which God ordained, then that which men after invented to mend it. Againe becauſe the Biſhop might be hereticall or wicked, to helpe that, they ordained Archbiſhops, and becauſe ſome Archbiſhops might be ſuch, they ordained Patriarchs, and becauſe ſome of them might be corrupted, (as they were) they admitted of Appeales, and ordained a Pope, and then becauſe he might erre, or be wicked, as Liberius, Honorius, Iohn 13 and others, they were forced to affirme the Pope cannot erre, and in all theſe things, men were ſtill perſwaded to contribute to theire honour, wealth and power, as neceſſarie to the kingdom of God: and therfore ſtill as this honour and power increaſed,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:1648:15"/> the Scriptures were by flatterers wreſted to defend it: therfore though in the invention of dioceſſan Biſhops, there was not ſo greate coueteouſnes, ambition and wickednes; yet the proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it, to bring it to its grouth, was onely to make <hi>themſelves fat with the offerings of the people,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 2.29.</note> as God ſaith of the preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious innovations and coveteous deſires of Elies Sonnes. Thus from the firſt ſtep in ordaining dioceſſan Biſhops, the myſterie of iniquitie could not reſt till it came to the height. Some will ſay, it hath not yet donne ſo in England. But what remedie is there in the meane againſt the Appealer, or any wicked Prelate, non reſident, or other delinquent? If, as of late in the Star<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber, Biſhops ſet themſelves to defend the vſe of Images in Churches, yea thoſe of the Trinitie; what other Biſhops, or Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters dare oppoſe them in pulpit or print? They, beeing greate and able to prefer others, are ſure to be flattered and followed, and by this meanes theire honour and power beeing daily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, they may prevaile in theſe and many other caſes, as the Church of Rome did in theeſe and the like: theire office ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth not <hi>make ready a people prepared for Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 11.</note> but rather for Antichriſt. If the witneſſes will Propheſie againſt them, it muſt alſo be in ſackcloth, bonds and impriſonment: for they haue obtained, or rather retained, ſo much Romiſh power, as to bring them to it, and puniſh all that reproue them: God telleth them of <hi>Babylon the greate, the Mother of Harlots,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chap. 17,</note> to ſhew them, ſhe may haue daughters, there may be Babylon the leſſe, yea many leſſer Babylons, Harlots in corruptions and forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations.</p>
            <p>The counſellors of the Parliament of Paris oppoſed againſt the authority that the councell of Trent gaue to the Biſhops in this kinde, where the Eccleſiaſticall authority they ſaide,<note place="margin">Hiſtor. of the coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cell of Trent. lib. 8. p. 819.</note> 
               <hi>was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged beyond its bounds, with the wrong and diminution of the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, by giueing power to Biſhops to proceede to pecuniarie mulcts, and impriſonment against the laitye, whereas no authority was giuen by Chriſt to his miniſters, but meere and pure ſpirituall; that when the Clergie was made a member and part of the policie, the Princes did by fauour allow the Biſhops to puniſh inferiour Clergie men with tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:1648:16"/> puniſhments; but to vſe ſuch kinde of puniſhments against the laiques, they had neither from the Law of God, nor of man, but by vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation onely.</hi> Yet commonly the moſt grievous they inflict, is for taking part with the Apoſtles in defenſe of the preſbiterie, taxing the Prelates of worldly policie and tyranie, or for ſome diſobedience, or irregularity to theire power, inventions and ceremonies: wherein note theire hypocriſie, who in the meane will not permit men to preach againſt images, Altars, bowing to them &amp;c. Much leſſe any thing that ſheweth the preſbiterall gouernment to be ordained of God, and neceſſary: when indeede it is theire owne office that is not neceſſary, ſeeing it onely ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth for ſuch things to perſecute men for the Teſtimonie of Ieſus, and more to force vnneceſſarie, then neceſſarie ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies. For kneeling in prayer, good order, and reverent geſture in the Church, are vſed in the french Churches, as commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and neceſſarie: and yet in men that in thoſe other th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngs are diſobedient to the truth, theire verie prayers are abhominable, and but mockeries, much more theire owne deuiſed cringes and geſtures, as in Papiſts who abound in ſuch things, and as if a man ſhould with all order and reverence bow his body to the King, his chaire of Eſtate, Image or ſeale, and yet deſpiſe, or neglect, many of his wholſom Lawes and commandements. The orders and ceremonies which God ordained are indeede to religion, as the barke, or leaues to a tree, that is, a comely part of it; but as for other ceremonies, and inventions, with theire pretended ſignifications, which beeing deviſed by man, are more then are in the reformed Churches of France, or were in the Apoſtles time, they are not to the religion and truth of God, as they ſay, like the barke to the tree, which if it be taken off, the tree withereth; but as the ivye to the oake which ſeemes to adorne and embrace it, but indeede binds, ſhadowes, and by degrees waſts and deſtroyes it. For theſe ſhewes ſerve many for a reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and a cloake of perſecution, and the power of Biſhops ſerues for a tyranous terrour to keepe men from p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aching and writing the truth, and ſetting theire names to theire bookes in the caſes of the hierarchie, traditions, Altars, images, pelagianiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:1648:16"/> or the like and conſequently to beget flatterie and luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warmneſſe in Clergie and people, and eate out that loue and zeale of the truth in all things, that they either doe now, or may hereafter, prohibit or maintaine: Such was, and ſuch is the fruite of theire power: and therfore certainly it is not of God, but of men, of the world, of the coueteous luſt of the eyes, and of the pride of life; and therfore what matters it who gaue it them, whether councels or Kings; they cannot make black white, nor euill good, nor that Lawfull which is ſo unlawfull and perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to the Kingdom of God. Conſtantine no doubt thought he had offered a greate ſacrifice to God, in giueing them ſo much as he did, other Emperours, Kings therfore haue augmented it: But he that forbiddeth to adde to his word, or take from it ſaith, <hi>to obey is better then</hi> ſacrifice.<note place="margin">1. Sam. 15.</note> Therfore Aſa to doe that which was right in the eyes of God, did not vrge his owne, or other mens inventions,<note place="margin">2. Chro. 14.3.4.</note> but <hi>tooke away the Altars of the ſtrange Gods, and the high places and Images,</hi> other Kings had erected, <hi>and commaunded Judah to ſeeke the Lord God of theire Fathers, and to doe the Law</hi> (marke) <hi>and the commaundement.</hi> Chr ſt beeing <hi>the King of Kings and Lord of Lords,</hi> though Kinges as his depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties haue greate power in matters of Religion, yet that is ſo, as in theeſe things not ſo ſeeke theire owne, but Gods will donne in ear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h, as it is in heauen; I, ſaith he,<note place="margin">Ioh. 8.26. chap. 6.34. Tract. 40.41.54.</note> 
               <hi>ſpeake to the world thoſe things which I haue heard of him. J came not to doe mine owne will, but the will of him that ſent me.</hi> He ſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e this that was the eternall word and Wiſdom of God, yea <hi>verie God and eternall l fe.</hi> For indeede he was not his owne wiſdom &amp; word, but the Fathers, as Auguſt n doth m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>feſt on theeſe &amp; the like places of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell: And ſhall not Kings then, who are but his Deputies, much more ſay it, yea &amp; doe it? either by cauſing the word of God to be faithfully taught in theire cities, as David and Iehoſhaphat, or by rooting out all monuments and ſtumbling blocks of ſuperſtition and idollatrie, and by ſuffering theire ſubjects to preach freely againſt them, and to worſhip the Lord <hi>in the beautie of holineſſe,</hi> as Hezechiah and Ioſiah did: that is, in a word, by cauſing theire ſubjects to worſhip God aright, and take his marke in the puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:1648:17"/> of his ordinances; and not to worſhip the Beaſt and take his mark, in receiving, profeſſing, and defending his corrupt tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and ceremonies. For to ſerve God, and make others ſerve him <hi>in the beautie of holineſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 110.3.</note> is to make men ſerve him in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe of the truth, according to all that is written in his Teſtament Ioſ. 1.8. and not with cathedrall ſervice and muſick, after the pompous traditions and inventions of Prelates and theire Canons, as ſome infer. For the Image of God is renewed in all <hi>righteouſneſſe and holines of the truth;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.24.</note> and if God would not that wee ſhould be again in bondage to the rudiments, which himſelfe ordained in the ceremoniall law, Chriſt haveing nailed them to his croſſe, much leſſe to thoſe which the pope and church of Rome, or other men have invented or eſtabliſhed: It were good that Princes and theire chaplains would think of that,<note place="margin">Ezra. 7.21.</note> 
               <hi>whatſoever is commaunded by the God of heaven,</hi> that is in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of religion, <hi>let it be diligently donne;</hi> where mark, he ſaith not commaunded by Kings; <hi>for why ſhould there be wrath against the Realme of the King and his Sonnes?</hi> That is, either for neglecting Gods commaund, or vrging inventions of men: for therfore wee are willed <hi>not to thinke of men,</hi> and theire power, <hi>above that is written.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.6.</note> It is the neceſſity of conformitie impoſed upon Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters that furniſheth them, as it did the Papiſts, with arguments to defend traditions, humane precepts, and Canons againſt this truth, and ſo to make a fearfull war againſt God. Which I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve not ſo much of them, who haveing ſubſcribed, follow theire miniſtrie, preach the word, and never ſpeake of Engliſh traditions, hopeing God will reforme them, as of thoſe that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend and preach them;<note place="margin">Iſa. 1.</note> never thinking that God may ſay vnto them, <hi>who required theſe things at your hands?</hi> What Goſpell is this? How doth it helpe the Kingdom of God? What know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, what fai h, what holineſſe of the truth doth it worke?</p>
            <p>They yet ſtrive to juſtifie theſe ordinances, and all the power of the prelates,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.40.</note> ſaying, the Apoſtle ſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h, <hi>Let all things be donne decently and in order:</hi> therfore Synods may ordaine dioceſſan Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and all ſuch Canons as are in England, and doubtleſſe the will of God is, that they ſhould be obeied. I nſwer the Apoſtle
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:1648:17"/> by this decencie and order, can not meane any thing that ſhall overthrow any of the ordinances of God, or make his word of none effect in any particular. He ſpeakes it of things before mencioned in his Epiſtle.<note place="margin">Chap. 11.21. Chap. 12.</note> There were divers who did eate theire ſuppers when they came to the Sacrament, <hi>one is hungrie and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is drunken:</hi> this was not decently and in order. <hi>If any man hunger let him eate at home.</hi> The holy Ghoſt giveth divers gifts of wiſdom, knowledge, healing, fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th, prophecie, tongues, &amp;c. to divers members of the ſame body. If the one of them ſhould ſay of the other, <hi>I have no neede</hi> of thee: this were not to doe things decently and in order. He wiſheth them to covet the beſt gifts, rather to <hi>prophecie then to ſpeake with tongues;</hi> that men praying, or prophecying, ſhould be vncovered,<note place="margin">Chap. 14.</note> that women ſhould be covered, and not ſpeake in the church: and above all, he there ſpeaketh of prophecying one by one, &amp; of others holding <hi>theire peace,</hi> and judging or trying the Spirits: And ſo of theſe, and the like things, then in vſe,<note place="margin">Rev. 2.24.</note> he ſaith <hi>let all things be donne decently and in order.</hi> As for theſe new inventions of Biſhops and Synods, Chr ſt himſelfe ſaith, <hi>I will put vpon you no other burden, but that which ye have alreadie hold faſt till J come;</hi> And ſhall men thinke that they may doe it? Are there any true Chriſtians that will not ſee that the offices of d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oceſſan Biſhops, who burden the church with ſup rſti ious rites, are not <hi>de jure divino,</hi> not of God, but of men? That they w re raiſed to this height and power, after the example of the Biſhop and church of Rome, who in thoſe firſt ages was imit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d by the moſt? So truly is ſhe called <hi>the mother of fornications and abhominations of the earth;</hi> That they, beeing ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with power, ſerve chiefely to ſuppreſſe the truth in theſe &amp; other po nts, to get and have dominion over mens faith, bring in Arminianiſme or other like errours, forbid confutation of them, exalt humane traditions, Romiſh inventions and ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and like Egiptian taſkemaiſters to burden the churches with them, make miniſtors that they dare not ſee theſe evils, leaſt it ſhould hinder theire preferment, or they ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of theire liveings, or ſilenced for ſpeaking againſt them, whileſt they ſee that others flatter or extoll them, and they ſerve
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:1648:18"/> thouſands for a religion, and inſteade of that which Chriſt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, as alſo for a cloake of poperie, mocking and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution.</p>
            <p>It will be ſaide the Canons &amp; ceremonies are not impoſed as matters of faith, but of order, and are counted things indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent; and therfore innocent, and not ſo hurtfull as you make them. I anſwer 1. So were they at the firſt in the Roman church, but they grew into greater authority, and ſo do theſe among thouſands in England, as ſleight a matter as ſome make of them. If things indifferent and innocent, why are they preſſed with ſuch power? For they are more vrged and obſerved by many then the Goſpel: In whoſe mindes theſe impoſers &amp; preachers of ceremonies only leave Chriſt a name, while like vſurpers, they carrie away the power of a King and kingdom: and therfore an offence againſt them is more puniſhed, and more ſkorned by ſuch popelings, newters and temporiſers, then an offence againſt the Goſpel: who yet in all theſe things count themſelves the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſubjects, the better Chriſtians. 2. That in the booke of Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, which is of matters of faith, miniſters are made to ſubſcribe to this, that <hi>the church hath authority to ordaine</hi> theſe things: that muſt be by ſom power given them in Gods word, and that is as much as to make them matters of faith and neceſſity. For that is in effect implied: If, as they ſay, God have given every national church this authority, then his will is that theſe things ſhould be religiouſly obſerved and obei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, and to breake them is ſinne. Thus they are or ought to be of faith:<note place="margin">Rom. 14.23.</note> 
               <hi>for whatſoever is not of faith is ſinne.</hi> But, as wee proved, the Papiſts take many of theſe cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, and even the office of dioceſſan Biſhops and Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops from the heathen, and from the daily encroachings of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, therefore how ſhould the ſubſcribing to them, in this tyra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, be of faith &amp; no ſinne? eſpecially ſeeing they doe many waies turne from God?</p>
            <p>I denie not, but that ſom things that the Apoſtles vſed are indifferent, and may be altered for time and place, as preaching and adminiſtring the Sacraments in the night and in mens how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.<note place="margin">Act. 8.36.</note> This may be donne in the day and in Temples. Philip and the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:1648:18"/> Eunuch went both downe into the water, others neede not to doe ſoe. But ſuch things altered, or added by Synods, ought to be verie few, and ſuch onely as neceſſity, and not pretended conveniencie require. For ſo ſay the Apoſtles and Elders,<note place="margin">Act. 15.22 28.</note> 
               <hi>with the whole Church</hi> at Ieruſalem: <hi>It ſeemed good to the Holy Ghost &amp; to vs to lay vpon you no greater burden then theeſe</hi> neceſſarie <hi>things.</hi> Marke they ſay <hi>neceſſarie things.</hi> I grant that ſome things the Church hath altered are neceſſarie in ſome Churches, as that the whole body ſhould not be dipped in Baptiſme, nor men forced to ſtand vncouered in ſuch cold countries, as Ruſſia and Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, while Moſes and the Apoſtles are read, as they did of old, and as now they doe in prayer, and ſinging of Pſalmes: other order may be taken for a Reader to reade the Scriptures and begin the Pſalmes, alſo for the manner of collecting almes, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vp a pulpit with water for Baptiſme, and a table conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently placed on the communion day: for at other times there needes none. But vnder pretext that the Church hath this power, it is moſt abſurd to ſay, it may giue authority to dioceſſan Biſhops and Archbiſhops, theire courts, power and proceedings, the oath <hi>ex officio,</hi> theire fining, impriſoning, ſuſpending, ſilen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, and ſo many ceremonies, Altars, canons, cuſtomes, and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, as are in England, more then were in the Apoſtles time, or then are in the reformed Churches of France, Germanie, Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia and other countries; and whereof there is no neceſſitie, but much miſchiefe, as beeing many of them Popiſh and ſnares ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to poperie, tyrannicall, and cauſing grievous ſchiſmes.</p>
            <p>Which if Queene Elizabeth did not aboliſh; conſider how ſhe found the land, what policies and tempers ſhe vſed, how ſhe ſuffered, as King Edward had donne,<note place="margin">Cand. lib. 1. p. 16.28 and 77.</note> the ſame ſervice in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh, which was before in Latin, <hi>ſome vaine things omitted,</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Prieſts to hold theire liueings, if they would but take the oath of ſupremacie: that there w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re therfore but 80. in the whole land that refuſed it; how the Iudges, and many of the nobilitie, Iudges in Parliament, were ſtill Papiſts for many yeares after her coronation, as the Reader may finde in Camden: withall that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all theeſe tempers, which ſhe thought thoſe times
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:1648:19"/> required, ſhe ſo loued the Goſpell and was ſo far from beeing an enemie to the reformation of Geneva, that ſhe, as a meanes vnder God, eſtabliſhed it in Scotland, France and the Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands, her forces did it. Againe conſider that the beſt acts that euer any King of Iudah did, in the reformation of religion, were no excuſe for his or theire leauing the high places vntaken away, that prouinciall and dioceſſan Biſhops, theire ſeas, pompe, power and traditions, are like thoſe high places: And laſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what way, or wherein, do theeſe things edifie and further the Kingdom of God, the ſaueing knowledge of his truth, and the true preaching of his Goſpell, whereby it is wro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght? for the ſame is the power of God to ſaluation, and that by which he hath brought many nations, and the verie thoughts of the heart <hi>to the obedience of Chriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 10.5.</note> Haue the hierarchie, ceremonies and ordinances likwiſe beene the ouerthrow of poperie, and mightie weapons to caſt downe the ſtrong holds thereof, &amp; to convince and ouercome Papiſts, or other hereticks and wicked livers? or doe they not rather ſtrengthen the Papiſts in theire religion, and make them ſay, the Biſhops know well enough that the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh is the true religion, for all or the moſt of theeſe things were taken from the Church of Rome? And this was the reaſon, that not onely diuers Prieſts kept theire liueings, but for the firſt eleuen yeares of Queene Elizabeth, moſt of the Papiſts came to Church;<note place="margin">L. Cooke de Iure Regis Eccleſiaſt. fol. 34.</note> knowing that conformitie to the ſervice and ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies doe not make a Proteſtant: that they, and euen the hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie it ſelfe, were of a Romiſh invention and cuſtom.</p>
            <p>All which ſheweth that things were not rightly founded in the Engliſh reformation, as in the reformed Churches of France and Germanie: where if any would leaue the Church of Rome, and become a proteſtant, he commeth to the Elders of the Church, is well inſtructed and informed by them; after he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth into the publike congregation, all men looking vpon him with loue and ioy, as vpon one that commeth to be maried; he is asked queſtions to this purpoſe 1. Whether he hold the Doctrine of the old and new Teſtament to be of God and ſufficient to ſalvation 2. That in the Sacraments the ſignes are called by the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:1648:19"/> things ſignified. 3. That the Pope of Rome is Antichriſt and the Church of Rome the whore of Babylon, the mother of forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations. Theeſe and the like: to which he haueing publikely aſſented, there is no doubt of his ſinceritie: If they had a parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Proteſtants, they neede not feare his fidelitie, nor any mans elſe among them: for all men make this profeſſion, vnles they be borne and bred in it, and then they doe it by Catechiſme: which things Church Papiſts will neuer doe; neither will the Pope diſpence with them to doe ſoe: whereas in England, where neither at the firſt, nor euer ſince, there was euer any ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, if a man be but conformable to the Church in owtward ceremonies, take the oath of allegeance, and communicate, he paſſeth for a Proteſtant, he may be choſen into any office of the common wealth, be a Parliament man, and yet in his practiſe a Church Papiſt, an Arminian, lukewarne, a ſemie-Papiſt, or a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poriſer: no man dares account him ſuch: yea he thinks that he ought to be more regarded then the moſt ſincere Chriſtian, whome he calleth a puritan. Thus the hierarchie, ſervice and ceremonies are ſhelters, and cloaks to divers Religions, cauſe infinitie factions and diviſions; and are therfore very ill for the ſervice of godly and juſt Princes: And this is the reaſon,<note place="margin">Note.</note> that there hath come ſo litle good of late Parliaments, yea ſo much hurt, theire members, beeing by this meanes of divers religions, and ſome of them readie to ſide with the ſtrongeſt, as beeing themſelves of a corrupt or none at all, like many of them that beare ſway and haue voyces in the election of knights and Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes: euery one would haue them of his owne Religion and faction: which was the reaſon that the Duke and his adherents found ſo many friends among them, and had ſo many Prelates and Clergie men to cloake and defend his doeings. It is ſtrange that men will not ſee, that an imperfect reformation in the Church of England, is the vaile and ſhelter to couer and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend theeſe and many other corruptions; which if the preſbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie had beene reſtored could neuer haue ſtood with the name of Proteſtants, or good Subjects. Sir Robert Cottens adviſe ſheweth that the Land did greatly ſuſpect the Duke and others
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:1648:20"/> of Popiſh practiſet: Ye ſee the hierarchie brings out ſuch Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants: And is it not ſo in the greate pariſhes and corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of London, and indeede almoſt of all England, wherein commonly ſuch Proteſtants beare office, and all the ſway?) Yet they held with the Prelates, and the Prelates with them, which was thought enough to paſſe them for Proteſtants, though they were ſuſpected of trecherie to the Churches beyond the Seas: where they ſay, the Engliſh can neuer be at true vnitie among themſelves, much leſſe with other Proteſtants, while the hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie ſtands: vnder which as vnder Daniels tree ſuch and ſo many kindes of Beaſts doe ſhelter themſelves:<note place="margin">Dan. 4.21.</note> and therfore the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments laboured in vaine againſt theeſe factions, as alſo againſt the Appealer, D. Iackſon, Coſen and his cooſening deuotions; the Biſhops for theire owne ends, taking part with them all, would in theeſe caſes haue all the power, like the Phariſes that <hi>ſhut vp the Kingdom</hi> of God, <hi>not entring in themſelves</hi> for the loue of it to worke a due reformation, and yet hindring others that would. This is the order they preſerve, and theeſe, and the like, are the fruits of maintaining theire hierarchie.</p>
            <p>The moſt zealous members of the parliaments, loth to be accounted puritans, thought to vphold the hierarchie and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, and yet to reforme, and prevent theeſe things and ſo to make the hierarchie, canons and ceremonies, which indeede are Popiſh, bring forth fruite vnto Chriſt. Divers greate divines, beeing capable of Biſhopwricks or other preferments, are of the ſame hope; never conſidering that not onely gifts, but euen the expectation of them, <hi>blinde the eyes of the wiſe;</hi> that many in the ancient Church of Rome, and ſome of the Fathers themſelves had the like hope, but were deceiued, making theire account without Chriſt, who telleth vs, <hi>ye ſhall know them by theire fruits. Do men gather grapes of thornes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 7.26.</note> 
               <hi>or figges of thiſtles?</hi> Chriſtian fruits of Antichriſtian inventions. The goodnes, or corruptnes, of the tree in knowne by the fruite. In the Engliſh reformation, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of the Proteſtant tenets were ingrafted into theeſe Popiſh plants, which is the reaſon, that ſome Biſhops haue brough out ſome fruits to the Proteſtant Religion, or rather to both Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions:
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:1648:20"/> For the Epiſcopall office it ſelfe, that is the ſtocke and body of the tree, and the branches of it, court, canons and cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, beeing Popiſh, muſt needes bring forth Popiſh fruite. The very Greeke Biſhops, though diſſenting from the Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts, haue donne it in the like things, in ambition, ſuperſtition, traditions, factions, and errours, the greateſt difference beeing aboute the ſupremacie (which ſome of them have aimed at) pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie and a few other things: and yet at laſt they were brought to ſubſcribe to thoſe in the councell of Florence.</p>
            <p>As heathen Altars, idols and people, beeing ſuffered among the Iſralites, were a ſnare vnto them Iudg. 2.2. ſo muſt it needes be with theſe popiſh offices, altars and ceremonies, left among proteſtants: The parliaments therefore ſhould have ſtruck at the rootes and ſtocks of the trees, wh ch bring out ſuch fruits in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters both of the church and common wealth: and better they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver did, nor never can bringe foorth in any nation: It is a juſt plague God hath ſent on the Clergie, becauſe like the Angels they kept not <hi>theire firſt eſtate</hi> of preſbyters, nor receive the love of that ordinance. For now ſince the death of the Apoſtles pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Evangeliſts, by the Teſtament of God all degrees of Clergie men that ſince crope in, are not branches of Chriſt the vine, he gave ſome to be paſtors, Teachers and Elders, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any to be dioceſſan Biſhops. Such as are not content with the callings and offices that he hath given for his church, but aſpire to others, that make them Lords of Gods heritage, they abide not in him;<note place="margin">Ioh. 15.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 5, 6.7, 1.</note> and as he ſaith <hi>As the branch cannot beare fruite of it ſelfe, except it abide in the vine, no more can ye except ye abide in me.</hi> Euen as he is the word, he is the vine, and his miniſters are the branches, by which his fulneſſe is ſpread abroade, wherfore he ſaith, <hi>If a man abide not in me, he is caſt forth as a branch, and is wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered.</hi> He ſaith, <hi>abide in me, and I in you,</hi> and ſheweth what that is, <hi>If ye abide in me, and my words abide in you;</hi> and that as well in matter of office and ceremonies according to his ordinances, as in other things: <hi>Herein is my father glorified that ye beare much fruite; ſoe ſhall ye be my Diſciples,</hi> as if he ſaide otherwiſe not. Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops therefore that have not theire callings of him, of his Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:1648:21"/> are branches of ſome other trees, not of Chriſt Ieſus the vine; and that makes them bring out ſuch fruite, as they doe.</p>
            <p>It will be ſaide, if kings may not give Clergie men ſuch ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and power, as Conſtantin, Iuſtinian and other Emperours gave them, where is theire prerogative? And if councels may not give them ſuch authority, as the councell of Nice, and other Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods of thoſe times, gave them; where is Chriſts promiſe of the Spirit? To the firſt I anſwer, wee are willed <hi>to give vnto Ceſar the things that are Ceſars,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 12.21.</note> but <hi>vnto God the things that are Gods:</hi> This, as wee have ſhewed, is a thing that is Gods: And who then would thinke that Chriſtians, if they may be ſo called, would ever teach that Kings, or Synods may g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve a power to Prelates, that ſhall make any of the ordinances of God of none effect, moſt of thoſe prelates, Antichriſts, and one of them the grand Antichriſt? Kings indeede are nurſing fathers to the church; but that is then, to ſee that theire people be fed with the ſincere milke of the word of God, and not with the traditions of men, or leaven of the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes;<note place="margin">Iſa. 52.2.</note> which beeing not the bread of heaven, <hi>ſatisfieth not.</hi> Yet Prelates are ever buzzing Princes in the eares with theire prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative in what they have eſtabliſhed. They may as well reaſon thus.<note place="margin">2. Chro. 12.11.</note> Iehoram <hi>made high places,</hi> and ſo <hi>cauſed men to commit forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation:</hi> He <hi>compelled Iudah thereto:</hi> therfore Kings may ſ t vp dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſan Biſhops and Sees, which are high places, never ordained of God, and ſo cauſe fornications, and compell men to theire obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience:<note place="margin">2. King. 16 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.</note> Ahaz ſaw an Altar at Damaſcus, ſent the faſhion of it to V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ah the Prieſt, made him make ſuch a one, and offer on it. therfore Kings may ſet vp Altars, cauſe ſuch things, and divers others, taken from the heathen, Iewes, or Papiſts, to be vſed in theire churches. Ieroboam ſet vp golden calves, Nebuchadnezar a golden Image, and cauſed all to worſhip it: ergo Kings may ſet vp theſe golden Images the B ſhops, and cauſe them in all theire power, traditions and ceremonies to be obeied, that is worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped. Chriſts Biſhops would rather ſay, Kings are commaunded to write them a booke of the law, <hi>not to depart from it,</hi> as God willeth Ioſha, <hi>but to mediate therein day and night, that</hi> they <hi>may obſerve to doe according to all that is written therein:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſ. 1.2.</note> therfore they
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:1648:21"/> may not make theire ſubjects worſhip the Beaſt and take his marke: not though he pretend that they are the things of the Spirit, either invented or confirmed in councels.</p>
            <p>If Chriſt, by whome Kings raigne, be the King only wiſe, the beſt and nobleſt King, as he is the word and wiſdom that ruleth his; then it is the greateſt and beſt prerogative, to be renued into his image, and ſeeke his kingdom, ſeeing the father ſaith,<note place="margin">Pſa. 2.</note> 
               <hi>J have ſet my King vpon my holy hil of Sion,</hi> to rule all nations in all mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of religion, <hi>be wiſe now therfore o ye Kings</hi> &amp;c.<note place="margin">Col. 3.10. Eph. 4.24.</note> Now his Image is renewed in <hi>knowledge, righteoſneſſe and holineſſe of the truth.</hi> Marke, not holineſſe of mens inventions and traditions, <hi>but ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe of the truth.</hi> The rudiments of the world, as Paul ſheweth, bring men <hi>into bondage</hi> and ignorance;<note place="margin">Gal. 4. Ioh. 8. Chap. 17. Chap. 14.</note> but the knowledge and obedience of the truth and continuance therein, as Chriſt alſo ſaith, <hi>maketh men free and Sonnes of God:</hi> which is the greateſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour that can be. He ſaith, <hi>Thy word is Truth:</hi> I am the Truth. His name is called the <hi>word of God.</hi> Such as yeeld to Gods word, yeeld to this truth, they truly bow at the name of Ieſus, and doe him homage, as the King of Kings. Princes are rightly called Gods Deputies, and truly honourable, when they labour to bring men to this true holineſſe. For there is no true holines, but the holines of the Truth. No man can ſerve two Maiſters, not God and Mammon: much leſſe Chriſt and Antichriſt, who commaund and teach contrarie things. But Chriſt is the Truth. And <hi>every one,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that is of the Truth heareth my voice.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 18.37 Chap. 10.</note> To be of the Truth then, is to be a true Chriſtian. <hi>My ſheepe heare my voice, and they follow me, and a ſtranger they will not follow.</hi> This ſtranger is one that bringeth falſe doctrines, or for doctrines the tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and inventions of men. <hi>His ſervants ye are to whome ye obey:</hi> He ſaith not to whome ye pray, but to whome ye obey:<note place="margin">Rom. 6.16</note> Him ye ſerve &amp; worſhip. whether Chriſt or Antichriſt, God or any other potentate.</p>
            <p>The Papiſts, and all, that teach or obſerve for doctrines com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements of men, will ſay wee worſhip and follow Chriſt. Indeede his is the kingdom the power and the glorie. But as he is the eternal word and wiſdom of God,<note place="margin">Ioh. 12.26</note> he ſaith <hi>If a man ſerve
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:1648:22"/> me, let him follow me,</hi> that is to heare, beleeve and obey me, and me only, as I am God with the father and the holy Ghoſt, or as I only am the word made fleſh that reveale the father: <hi>for thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 4.</note> 
               <hi>and him only ſhalt thou ſerve.</hi> And above all in this, in beleeving his word only, who can not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive nor be deceived. Otherwiſe though thou pray vnto him, and vſe all externall devotions, he will not account that ſervice, or following him, but following a man knowes not who, what, or wherefore <hi>for how ſhall they call on him in whome they have not beleeved?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 10.14.15.</note> And how ſhall they <hi>beleeve in him of whome they have not heard?</hi> there can therefore be no true ſerving him, without hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and beleeving, nor no hearing to ſalvation without hearing of him, nor indeede without obeying or following, for therfore it is added, <hi>But they have not all obeied the Goſpel.</hi> Some obey it not at all, as Iewes: others would ſerve God and Mammon, others Chriſt and Antichriſt; others Gods word and the precepts of men: but this is not to obeie the Goſpell, to follow Chriſt, to worſhip him aright: for he ſaith <hi>In vaine they worſhip me, who teach for doctrines the commandements of men.</hi> Thus doe they who teach that dioceſſan Biſhops ſhould be received and obeied,<note place="margin">Mat. 15 9.</note> which make Gods word of the preſbiterie of none effect, and this they alſo doe by other theire traditions and precepts, which not only croſſe the Goſpel in other things,<note place="margin">See the crowne of a Chriſtian Martyr.</note> but ſerve men for a religion, and ſo make the word of God of none effect. And while they hold that Gods will is that they ſhould be obeied, that is in effect to teach them for doctrines: they are no longer things indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, but neceſſarie; or rather preſumptions that turne from the truth,<note place="margin">Mar. 7.8.</note> and make men lay aſide the word of God: <hi>for laying aſide the commandements of God, ye hold the tradition of men.</hi> As if he ſaide, ye cannot hold the tradition of men, but ye lay aſide the commandement of God, as wee finde true in matter of the preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biterie and other things. Againe, <hi>No man hath ſeene God at any time:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 1.18.</note> 
               <hi>the only begotten Sonne, which is in the boſome of the father, he hath declared him. All things are delivered vnto me of my father: and no man knoweth the father ſave the Sonne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 11.27 Ioh. 15.15</note> 
               <hi>and he to whome the Sonne will reveale him.</hi> But he ſaith to his Apoſtles, <hi>All things that I
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:1648:22"/> have heard of my father, J have made knowne vnto you</hi> ſo he hath fullie declared him. And the Apoſtles have declared vnto vs in the new Teſtament, <hi>all the counſell of God.</hi> If therfore the Sonne,<note place="margin">Act. 20.27</note> have not revealed theſe traditions and precepts of men, in his Teſtament, it is a greate preſumtion to ſay they may be impoſed, or that Gods will is that they ſhould be obeied. For becauſe Chriſt only is the word that revealeth the father; therefore that only ſhould be taught, which he hath revealed by his Apoſtles &amp; Evangeliſts: but he hath not revealed theſe precepts of men, and therfore he ſaith <hi>In vaine they worſhip me, who teach for do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines</hi> commandements of men. As if he ſaide, rejecting God &amp; his word, ye worſhip him whoſe traditions ye receive,<note place="margin">Ioh. 4.</note> and that with, the greateſt and treweſt worſhip. <hi>The true worſhippers ſhall worſhip the father in ſpirit and truth.</hi> Viz. in obeying the truth, and yealding themſelves to be wholly governed by it, as by a perfect and neceſſarie rule, which requireth not a difference of meates, or ſuch triviall things: <hi>but righteouſnes, and peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 14, 16.18.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; ioy in the holy Ghoſt. He that in theſe things ſerveth Christ, is acceptable to God:</hi> He is a true worſhipper. For ſo Paul ſaith <hi>After the way that they call hereſie, ſo worſhip I the God of my fathers, beleeving all things that are written.</hi> To beleeve the Teſtaments and no more,<note place="margin">Obejed.</note> is the true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: This muſt needes be the worſhip vſed by them who are ſaide to worſhip in the Temple of the Tabernacle of the Teſtimonie:<note place="margin">Rev. 11.1.19.</note> becauſe there was nothing ſeene in it, but the Arke of his Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: they beleeved and obeied all things that were written therein, and no more.<note place="margin">1. Sam. 15.22.</note> To beleeve and <hi>to obey is better then Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and to hearken then the fat of rammes.</hi> It is the beſt ſervice and worſhip, as the very Ieſuits prove from this place:<note place="margin">Ignati. de obed. vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute. ſect 5</note> and thereby condemne themſelves, who give this beſt ſervice to theire ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour, by beleeving and obeying him, <hi>as one that can not be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved:</hi> though they cannot perceive, but he commaunds things contrarie to God, and ſo make him theire God. Thus the Pope ſits in the Temple of God as God, or as men ſay moſt maiſter in things: and thus papiſts worſhip the Beaſt and his image. <hi>For his ſervants ye are to whome ye obey.</hi> And yet this worſhip in matters of religion is only due vnto God, whoſe word alone is the ſpirit
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:1648:23"/> that giveth life: yea men have more or leſſe, the Spirit of prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>uld be obeied, as they ſpeake according to that word: and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>fore the Angel ſaith <hi>worſhip God: for the teſtimonie of Ieſus is the Spirit of prophecie.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 19</note> His teſtimonie and no other. For the church is ſubject to Chriſt not to the preceps of men This teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie ye ought to beleeve and obey,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.24.</note> as Paul did, in beleewing <hi>all things that</hi> are <hi>written,</hi> and ſo to worſhip God in Spirit and truth. <hi>For the Father ſeeketh ſuch to worſhip him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Papiſts then in receiving and teaching for Doctrines precepts and traditions of the Pope and Church of Rome, ſo contrarie to the word, do certainly giue them this true and greate worſhip which only belongs to God: and ſo are like them, <hi>who changed the truth of God into a lie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1.25</note> 
               <hi>and worſhipped and ſerved the creature more then the creator, who is bleſſed for ever.</hi> Thus they are ſaide to worſhip the Beaſt and his Image. Many thinke that ſome ſuch thing is done by thoſe in England that defend &amp; teach the authority of the Biſhops, theire hierarchie, Canons, decrees and ceremonies, becauſe many of them are popiſh, and more preſſed by many, then ſome points of the Goſpel. And though divers doe not doe this with a purpoſe to ſet vp poperie, vnleſſe in a few things, neither can be perſwaded that the hierarchie is a limbe of the Beaſt, yet the obedience to it in theſe things, if they, or it, be not of God, is a worſhip to it, and a ſerving the creature more then the creator, which indeede is much more donne by the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts to the Beaſt and his Image. And here by the way it is a thing worthy obſervation, that if in the primative ages of the church, vnder the firſt Chriſtian Emperours, ſome were touched with ſome of the popiſh opinions, as very few were, and thoſe only in ſome things: yet they did neither maintaine them againſt ſuch light of doctrine, as is manifeſted now a daies, nor give theire falſe doctrines and interpretations for lawes, as they have donne in theſe later ages, and ſince the councell of Trent: which is the thing that makes them and theire followers ſo abhominable. Therfore after one Angel <hi>haveing an everlaſting Goſpel to preach</hi> had cried <hi>feare God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 14.6, 7.8.9.</note> 
               <hi>and worſhip him:</hi> and that the ſecond had denounced the fall of Babylon; by which two, ſeeming to be
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:1648:23"/> wicklife Luther and theire followers, came greate light of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, <hi>The third Angel followed them,</hi> and denounced eternall damnation to every one that ſhould after this time worſhip the Beaſt and his Image, and receive his marke. And becauſe ſome would rather ſuffer martyrdom then doe it, that is added. <hi>Here is the patience and the faith of the ſaincts.</hi>
               <note place="margin">vers 12.13</note> 
               <hi>Here are they that keepe the commandements of God and the faith of Jeſus. Bleſſed are the dead which henceforth die in the Lord,</hi> or as others reade for the Lords cauſe.</p>
            <p>Here then wee may ſee theire impietie and danger, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue not in the word, but either more or leſſe receive and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the Doctrine and ſuperſtion of the Pope and Church of Rome, which is not taught in the holy Scriptures, they receive the marke of the Beaſt, and worſhip him and his Image. To re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, and haue which marke, is to receive or have an impreſſion of the Popiſh Doctrine and Religion, in part or in whole, either in profeſſion, which is to haue the marke in the forhead; or by defending or helping the ſame by ſom meanes, which is to haue the marke in the right hand, as will appeare by ſhewing how men haue the Seale, or marke of God. The eternall word and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Father is his expreſſe Image, with which the elect are ſealed in theire forheads, by ſaueing knowledge and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion thereof, with faith and full aſſurance. Which is when they receive the Doctrine of the holy Scripture, and it leaues ſuch an impreſſion in them, that they profeſſe they will receive it and no other, vnder any pretence of the Spirit, vnleſſe it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low from the ſame Teſtament of Chriſt: who to ſhew that the Holy Ghoſt brings no other Doctrine, he, the truth, calleth him <hi>the Spirit of truth,</hi> and ſaith, <hi>He ſhall not ſpeake of himſelfe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 16.13</note> 
               <hi>But he ſhall receive of mine, and ſhall ſhew it vnto you. He ſhall bring all things to your remembrance, whatſoeuer J haue ſaide vnto you.</hi> So he leadeth into all truth. <hi>And he ſhall ſhew you the things to come,</hi> that is touching the generall Apoſtacie vnder Antichriſt, and ſuch other things in the Revelation.</p>
            <p>Councels therefore doe vainly pretend the Spirit, if they ſpeake not according to the Teſtament of Chriſt. The word was
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:1648:24"/> made fleſh:<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.</note> the Diſciples <hi>ſaw the glorie thereof</hi> in his Doctrine and miracles, <hi>full of grace and Truth.</hi> This cannot be ſaide of the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons and inventions of men. <hi>Of his fulneſſe,</hi> ſaith Iohn, <hi>haue all wee receiued: Grace and Truth came by Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Whoſoeuer brings not this word,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 2.24.</note> this truth of God, is a deceiver. <hi>But the anointing which ye haue receiued of him abideth in you, and ye neede not that any man teach you, but as the ſame annointing teacheth you of all things, and is truth and is no lie.</hi> Idaicus taketh Chriſt to be the anointing here meant; and Lorinus on the place giues good reaſons, why the word is ſaide to be the Anointing. Indeede the Spouſe ſaith to him, <hi>Thy Name is an ointment powred forth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 1.3.</note> Now wee know <hi>his Name is called the word of God.</hi> And indeede this eternall word ſeemeth to be the anointing meant, becauſe he ſaith, <hi>it is Truth and is no lie:</hi> And Chriſt that word, becauſe he addeth, <hi>and euen as it hath taught you ye ſhall abide in him,</hi> or it: in the anointing. <hi>And now litle children abide in him, that when he ſhall appeare wee may haue confidence, and not be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med before him at his comming</hi> v. 12. to iudgment: for the word ſhall iudge vs <hi>at the last day,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 12.48.</note> and Chriſt is that word, as Auguſtin proueth on that and many other places of Iohns Goſpel. <hi>As many as receiued</hi> this word, this eternall Truth, <hi>to them he gaue po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to become the Sonnes of God, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to them that beleoue in his Name;</hi> whoſe name is called the word of God: Therefore he ſaith to them <hi>that beleeued on him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 8.31.36.</note> 
               <hi>If ye continue in my word, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are ye my Diſciples indeede, and ye ſhall know the truth &amp; the truth ſhall make you free:</hi> and ſheweth the ſame truth to be the Sonne that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth Sonnes &amp; free, ſaying <hi>If the Sonne therefore ſhall make you free ye ſhall be free indeede.</hi> This comes of the ſaueing knowledge of Gods word.<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.2.</note> Therefore Iohn ſaith <hi>Now wee are the Sonnes of God, and it doth not yet appeare what wee ſhall be:</hi> that is becauſe <hi>wee know but in part: But when he ſhall appeare we ſhall be like him: for wee ſhall ſee him as he is. And euery man that hath this hope purifieth himſelfe, euen as he is pure.</hi> Thus, as Paul ſaith men put on the new man,<note place="margin">Ioh. 17.</note> which is <hi>renewed in knowledge after the Image of him that created</hi> him, and that ſaueing knowledge is the cauſe of loueing and obeying him, and of purifying of a mans ſelfe,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:1648:24"/> as he is pure. Therefore it is that Chriſt ſaith,<note place="margin">M. Dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam Guide to Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe cha. 5. Rom. 10. Pſa. 119.27.33.34.</note> 
               <hi>this is eternall life to know thee, and him whome thou hast ſent.</hi> Saueing knowledge as one ſaith, <hi>beeing the ground of obedience, and the roote of faith and all other graces</hi> For how <hi>ſhall they call vpon him in whome they haue not beleeued? and how ſhall they beleeue on him of whome they haue not heard?</hi> Or haue no knowledge. Divinely therefore ſaith Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid <hi>Make me to vnderstand they way of the precepts, ſo ſhall I talke of thy wondrous works, Giue me vnderſtanding, and I ſhall keepe thy Law.</hi> And therefore Auguſtin ſaith that wee may loue things vnſeene, but not vnknowne. For to ſhew that the firſt converſion of a Chriſtian is wrought by illumination, knowledge and a liuely faith that followeth thereupon, Chriſt ſaith to Paul,<note place="margin">Act. 26.18</note> 
               <hi>J ſend thee to the Gentiles, to open theire eyes, and to turne them from darknes to light:</hi> that is from the power of darkneſſe, to the Sonne of light, as he addeth <hi>from the power of Satan vnto God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ 2.2. chap. 4.18.</note> Wherefore he ſheweth that the Gentiles in times paſt walked after the Prince of the power of the aire, and were aliened from the life of God, <hi>becauſe theire vnderstanding was darkened, through the ignorance that was in them, becauſe of the blindneſſe of theire heart:</hi> that beeing aliens from the common wealth of Iſrael, and ſtrangers from the couenants of promiſe, they were at that time without Chriſt, <hi>haveing no hope, and without God in the world.</hi> Hence it was that they, beeing paſt feeling, <hi>gaue themſelves ouer to worke all vnclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with greedineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which ignorance and blindneſſe, is ſo greate a ſinne, and ſo greate a cauſe of ſinne, that the Pſalmiſt ſaith,<note place="margin">Pſa. 79.6.</note> 
               <hi>powre out thy wrath vpon the heathen that haue not knowen thee,</hi> and vpon <hi>the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms that haue not called vpon thy name.</hi> And the Apoſtle ſaith, that the Lord <hi>Ieſus ſhall come from heauen with his mightie Angels,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Theſ. 1.7 8.</note> 
               <hi>in flaming fire, taking vengeance on them that know not God:</hi> That is, becauſe they care not for this greate favour he vouchſafeth to reueale himſelfe, in revealing his word in theeſe and other things vnto ſinfull men, that by receiving the loue and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of his eternall word and truth, they may be made Sonnes and friends of God, &amp; to obey him better then they haue donne. For as Ioſeph by the favours his maiſter ſhewed him, was
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:1648:25"/> taught to denie to ſinne with his miſtreſſe; So this greate grace of God,<note place="margin">Tit. 1.11.</note> bringing ſalvation hath appeared to all men, <hi>Teaching vs that denying vngodlineſſe and worldly luſts, wee ſhould liue ſoberly righteouſly and godly in this preſent world.</hi> So that the more ſaveing knowledge there is in a man, there will be the more faith, pietie, righteouſneſſe and holineſſe of the truth. The Angels in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, doe Gods will better then we, becauſe they know him bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter rhen we: and wee ſhall doe it better, when wee know him better, when wee ſhall ſee him as he is. Therefore Peter ſaith <hi>Grace and peace be multiplied vnto you, through the knowledge of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.2.3. Chap. 3.18. Exod. 34.6.</note> 
               <hi>and of Ieſus our Lord.</hi> Therefore when Moſes deſired to ſee and know God, he ſhewed himſelfe in theeſe words, <hi>The Lord, Jehouah, ſtrong, mercifull, gracious, long ſuffering, abundant in kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and truth, reſerving mercie for thouſands, forgiveing iniquitie &amp;c.</hi> This beeing a ſumme of the Goſpell. And therefore alſo Paul prayeth for this, as one of the greateſt bleſſings that can be, that <hi>the Father of glorie may giue vnto you the Spirit of Wiſdom and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation in the knowledge of him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.17.</note> 
               <hi>the eyes of your vnderſtanding beeing inlightened, that you may know what is the hope of his calling: and what the exceeding greatneſse of his power to vs ward that beleeve: That wee may be filled with the knowledge of Gods will,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 1.9.</note> 
               <hi>in all Wiſdom and ſpirituall vnderſtanding.</hi> Knowing as was ſhewed, that this worketh ſanctification, that the Image of God is renewed in knowledge;<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.24.</note> and thereby <hi>in righteouſneſſe and holineſſe of the truth.</hi> Not holineſſe of mens inventions and traditions, but in holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the truth. Which is when they are confident, that they neede not that any man teach them, but as the ſame Truth tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth them of all things, and is truth and is no lie. That while Prelates teach other things, it is more then needeth: That wee ſhould all ſpeake the ſame thing, to avoide diviſions: but that muſt <hi>be the Teſtimonie of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.1</note> which the Apoſtles declared vnto vs, otherwiſe diviſions cannot be avoided. For men muſt contend earneſtly for the faith once delivered to the Saints, holding i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> faſt; and when they profeſſe as much, that is to haue the Seale name or marke of God in theire forheads.</p>
            <p>For <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a Character or marke, comes of <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:1648:25"/> which ſignifieth to make a deepe impreſſion. Letters are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore called Characters, becauſe thoſe elements wee firſt learne, leave a ſtronge ſeale in our memories: So doth the Doctrine of God in the heart and Soule, where he promiſed to write it.<note place="margin">Ier. 31.33.</note> 
               <hi>I will put my Law in theire inward parts, and write it in theire hearts:</hi> So doth he his promiſes, whereby wee are made to beleeve &amp; obey, and conſequently ſealed with the marke, or Image of God.<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.13.</note> 
               <hi>In whome alſo ye truſted, after that ye heard the word of truth: in whome alſo after that ye beleeved, ye were ſealed with that Holy Spirit of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe.</hi> Thus the Lord ſealeth men by the miniſtrie or his word, and cooperation of the Holy Ghoſt. God, ſaith Paul,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.3 6 17.18.</note> 
               <hi>hath made vs able miniſters of the new Testament, not of the letter but of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit which giveth life,</hi> and conſequently ſealeth. <hi>Now the Lord</hi> (that is Chriſt the word) <hi>is that Spirit.</hi> Namely which wee adminiſter to the Soule and vnderſtanding, and which ſealeth: Wherefore he addeth,<note place="margin">That is the word of the Lord.</note> 
               <hi>wee all with open face beholding as in a glaſſe the glorie of the Lord are changed into the ſame Image;</hi> and conſequently ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led therewith. And that ſeale is in theire forheads, when they profeſſe it, and that they will receive it, and no other: So it is ſaide <hi>Hurt not the earth, nor the Sea, nor the trees, till wee haue ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Servants of our God in theire forheads.</hi> Theeſe are ſuch as receive the Teſtimonie of Chriſt, and no other Doctrine, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it follow from the ſame. Such, behoulding Romiſh ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, propheſied in Sackcloth; yet could not be hurt by the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſts, the Monkes and Friars; all theire tales of purgaterie affright not them: They haue the Fathers name written in theire for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads, becauſe the word is called his name, and expreſſeth him, as an Image on a Seale doth him whoſe Image it is. <hi>I haue mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fested thy name vnto the men which thou gavest me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 17.6.8.11.</note> that is thy word, as it followeth <hi>I haue giuen them the words which thou gaueſt me, &amp; they haue received them. Keepe through thine owne name thoſe which thou haſt giuen me:</hi> That is through thy word:<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.5. Heb. 1.2.</note> who are <hi>kept by the povver of God,</hi> that is by the word of God, by which all things were made and are vpheld. Now then this eternall and divine word, by which the world was made and is vpheld, is called the Fathers Name, as beeing his word, <hi>the brightneſſe of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:1648:26"/> his glorie, and Character of his ſubſtance,</hi> that is, his expreſſe Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, which expreſſeth him, and wherewith wee are ſealed: which Character or word the Sonne is; therefore they are alſo ſaide to haue <hi>the Sonnes name on theire forheads.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 19.</note> Now on his <hi>head were many crownes and a name written, v.</hi> 12. which ſhewed what he was; and <hi>his name is called the word of God.</hi> Of which there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and for which all Kings ſhould hold theire crownes, and not of the Pope, nor for his traditions and ſervice. Thus Iohn ſaith <hi>He that continueth in the Doctrine of Chriſt he hath both the Father and the Sonne;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Ioh.</note> the Father and his word. Therefore it muſt needes be the marke of God,<note place="margin">Reu. 19. Chap. 15.6. &amp; chap. 11. Reu. 21.17 Chap. 22.</note> which he had, who ſaith <hi>J am thy fellow Servant, and of thy brethren which haue the Teſtimonie of Ieſus.</hi> And that is alſo proved by this, that he is one of the ſeaven Angels that commeth out of the Temple of the Tabernacle of the Teſtimonie, that is out of the Church millitant againſt Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt and his adherents. And if he come thence, he is certainly one of them that <hi>worſhip therein,</hi> keepe his ſayings, and contend for the truth: which things men doe. He is a man: for ſo he ſaith <hi>J am thy fellow Servant, and of thy brethren the Prophets, and of them that keepe the ſayings of this booke;</hi> that haue the Teſtimonie of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus. As all thoſe muſt needes haue, that haue the marke of God: they are ſuch as continue in the word, ſuch as are the true Church, becauſe they continue in the word, defend &amp; ma ntaine it and no other, as the Church doth which is called <hi>the pillar of truth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 3 15</note> And not as ſome in England doe, who ſerve for little elſe then to defend theire owne ambition, canons and ceremonies, and yet would be called the Church of Chriſt. If one of theeſe, through flatterie, grow ſo greate in favour with his Prince, as to rule all as he liſt, to turne Religion into Popiſh complement and ceremonies, to mould it after his owne humour: If therefore many out of feare, flatterie, or hope of favour follow and juſtifie him, is he the Church? not he, nor he and all his flatterers. If he could bring fower, or five, or all the Biſhops to his Religion, are they the Church? They might ſee that ſo the Church of Rome came to be corrupted; That theeſe in the Temple of the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle of the Teſtimonie are onely the true Church, becauſe they
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:1648:26"/> continue in the word, and will receive no other: that the ſame muſt needes be the marke of the true Church, which is here the marke of true Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>Theſe, as wee have ſeene, are ſet out by the Iewes the firſt Teſtament, who neither in doctrine, nor ceremonies, might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive any thing which God had not commaunded, but were to hold in all things to his firſt ordinances and inſtitutions:<note place="margin">Crowne of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr.</note> wherein when they failed, they were plagued: and that it would be ſo with Chriſtians, if they changed Chriſts ordinances, or let in any innovations hath appeared by his conſtant compariſon, to the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Churches and others, of Churches compared to a Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, and an harlot, to the Temple of God, and the Synagogue of Satan, to the inner Temple, and the court without: he will not yeald theeſe later to be Iewes, that is Chriſtians; becauſe of other Lords, they hold other Lawes in Religion, in order, in ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and other things: they doe not hold faſt the word and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances which he left, without receiving innovations or inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of men: therefore they are not of that part of his Temple, which he alloweth to be accounted his Church, but of <hi>the court without, which is giuen to the Gentiles;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu, 11.</note> that is to Antichriſt and others, who in Gods account are as Gentiles, ſuch as in divers things will not heare his word, but make it of none effect with theire dominion and traditions. They hold ſom Chriſtian truths, but not all: Thoſe in England, that are defenders of the hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchie, or Arminians, hold more then the Papiſts, yet not all. Chriſt will not yeald ſom to be Iewes, who perhaps failed in fewer things: Iudge therefore I pray you, whether they be not of that ſort, or like them, of whome Chriſt ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">Chap, 2,</note> 
               <hi>which ſay they are Iewes and are not,</hi> of the true Temple &amp; are not viz. not of thoſe ſecret parts of the Temple.<note place="margin">1, King. 8, 8,</note> As there was <hi>nothing in the Arke ſaue the two tables of Stone,</hi> ſo there is nothing in the church of Chriſt, in this Temple, but the Teſtimonie of Ieſus and his government the Elderſhip; no Popiſh dominion nor traditions: If, there had, Iohn who tooke exact meaſure of it, &amp; ſaw it ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned would haue reuealed it in his Revelation: but there was nothing elſe ſeene ſave that, and <hi>them that worſhip therein:</hi> Who
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:1648:27"/> therefore muſt needes be thoſe that from the heart receive and obey that word, and no other; for there is no other there. This was then ſo greate an honour that Iohn was readie to worſhip him that was ſuch a one, as if that were the beſt nobilitie to be thus ſtamped &amp; ſealed with the Image of God, &amp; in all doctrines and Lawes of Religion,<note place="margin">Act. 17.11</note> to haue recourſe to the Law and to the Teſtament, like the men of Berea, to ſee if the Teachers taught according to this word. And yet in England, he that is ſuch a one is in contempt called a Puritan, hated and ſcorned, and that by the Prelates themſelves; who therefore deſpiſe all that are of this Temple; Becauſe indeede if dioceſſan Biſhops, theire power, canons and ceremonies, be not according to this word, they that are of this Temple care not for them.<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6. Phil. 1.27.</note> They have theire <hi>loines girt about with the Truth;</hi> they <hi>ſtand faſt in one Spirit, with one minde, ſtriveing together for the faith of the Goſpel;</hi> they have the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie of Ieſus, as here one of them ſaith, they continue in his word, and ſo are Diſciples indeede: They confeſſe and profeſſe this word, and ſo have his name and marke on theire forheads: to which the binding of the law, to the hand and forhead, did point in a figure:<note place="margin">Deut. 6.8.</note> and both that, and this, doe ſhew that in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of religion, <hi>the Lord is our Iudge, the Lord is our King, the Lord is our lawgiver.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 1.17. Phil. 3.16,</note> He is <hi>the King only wiſe.</hi> Every man had neede to beleeve and receive this; and to ſay with Paul, <hi>let vs walke by the ſame rule, let vs minde the ſame thing:</hi> for this ye ſee is the marke of a Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>And by the Rule of contraries, the marke of Antichriſt muſt needes be an impreſſion of that his doctrine, law, and ſuperſtitious rites, which is more then the word revealed, or againſt the ſame: the profeſſion and obſervation thereof is the marke, as the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the heatheniſh rites is called <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">2. Mac. 4.20.</note> the chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter or marke of the Grecians. The Pope would that all men ſhould receive defend and profeſſe his doctrine and ſuperſtitious rites, and ſo ſhould receive his marke in theire right hand and forheads. For in the forhead that is by <hi>profeſſion and in the right hand, that is by operation,</hi> as the ordinarie gloſſe expoundeth. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonius alſo and Lyra teach that <hi>A character or marke is a certaine
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:1648:27"/> manner of liveing according to the law of any,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>Ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tho in epiſt. inter acta ſextae Synodi conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nop. Boni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fac. 8. in extran. de maior. &amp; obed.</p>
                  <p>Clement. in lib. 5. ad noſtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in gloſſ. D. 18. c. ſi qui ſunt.</p>
               </note> 
               <hi>whereby men are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguiſhed from others.</hi> So the Pope cauſeth all men to take his marke, for he ſaith, <hi>Everie ſoule that would be ſaved muſt confeſſe the forme of the Roman tradition. Wee affirme, define, and pronounce that it is altogether neceſſarie to ſalvation for every humane creature to be ſubject to the Pope of Rome.</hi> Hereunto agreeth that gloſſe, <hi>It is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that the church is therefore one, becauſe in the vniverſall church, there is one ſupreame head,</hi> to wit the Pope, whome <hi>all that are of the Church are bound to obey: He incurreth therefore the ſinne of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganiſme, whoſoever renounceth obedience to the ſee Apoſtolike.</hi> Thus he cauſeth all to take his marke. If a man would know a litle better, what the marke is; he may ſee the ſame in the Popes new creede of the Trent faith, as it is propounded by the Bull of Pius 4. and that act of the councell of Trent, wherin it was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, <hi>That the Biſhops ſhall in the firſt provinciall councell receive the decrees of the Synod of Trent, promiſe obedience to the Pope,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hiſtor. of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Trent. lib, 8. p. 808.</note> 
               <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematiſe the hereſies condemned, and every Biſhop hereafter promoted ſhall doe the ſame in the first Synod: and all beneficed men, who are to aſſist in the dioceſſan Synod ſhall doe the ſame therein. Thoſe who have the care of vniverſities and ſtudies generall, ſhall indeavour to make the Decrees to be received in them,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and ſhall take a ſolemne oath herein every yeare.</hi> All both ſmal &amp; greate, Prieſts and people, take this ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke in the forhead, who profeſſe the Romiſh or Trent faith; To take it in the hand, that is to maintaine it (in part or in whole) by wit, ſword, power, purſe or otherwiſe, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther openly, as profeſt papiſts, or more privately, as diſguiſed wolves, in the ſheepes cloathing of a proteſtant out ſide, falſe brethren, ſuch as creeping in vnawares, doe more or leſſe practiſe the bringing in of poperie and diviſion, or flatter thoſe that doe: which is the roote of all other vngodlineſſe, preſumptious ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, licentiouſneſſe and corruption, and indeede of <hi>turning the grace of God into laciviouſneſſe,</hi> prevarication, <hi>and following the way of Balaam for reward,</hi> as S. Iude obſerveth in a like caſe:<note place="margin">Iude 3. to 12,</note> and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wiſheth men to <hi>contend earneſtly for the faith which was once delivered to the ſaints:</hi> which ſhewes that the only way to preſerve that good which remaineth; and reforme all things that are amiſſe
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:1648:28"/> is to contend for that puritie and ſimplicitie in doctrine and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline, which God by his Apoſtles ordained in his Teſtament: for therefore againſt all theſe innovators, flatterers and mockers, he ſaith,<note place="margin">Verſ. 17</note> 
               <hi>but remember ye the words which were ſpoken before of the Apoſtles</hi> &amp;c. <hi>building vp youre ſelves in youre moſt holy faith: keepe your ſelves in the love of God: And others ſave with feare, pulling them out of the fire; hating even the garment ſpotted by the fleſh:</hi> much more then the marke of the Beaſt and all appearance of it.</p>
            <p>As for the number of the Beaſt, which is the number of a man, and his number 666. ſome finde it in the word <hi>Romanus,</hi> written in Hebrew characters, and that is the number of a man, beeing the name of one of theire Popes. But Iohn wrote in Greeke,<note place="margin">Irenae, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſ. hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ. l. 5.</note> and to the Greeke churches: therfore the name <hi>Lateinos</hi> written in greeke letters, which was the name of a King in Italie, is more probable: becauſe the Beaſt is latin, and ſo are his body and members, and as Ireneus alſo noteth, <hi>The moſt true kingdom hath this name: for they are latines which now raigne.</hi> And we know that the Dragon which then raigned was to give his throne to the beaſt. The word ΛΑΤΕΙΝΟΣ as King Iames obſerveth, <hi>ſutes well with the Romiſh church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">praemon. pag. 94.</note> 
               <hi>Romiſh faith and latin ſervice.</hi> The la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as I take it, beeing eſpecially meant in this place; as beeing brought into the church by Vitalian, and ſo by the ſecond Beaſt, who alſo firſt ſet vp organs in churches and other ceremonies, and that aboute the yeare 666. Now whereas he cauſeth, <hi>that no man might buy or ſell, ſave he that had the marke, or the name of the beaſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Platina in Vitalian.</note> 
               <hi>or the number of his name:</hi> This ſheweth, that if a man will live in peace among them, he muſt profeſſe the Trent faith. Som Papiſts will not doe this. For as ſom in England are content to ſeeme to be proteſtants, yet are church papiſts, popiſh or newters: ſo are there &amp; ever were, ſom in Spaine, Italie &amp; Rome, who are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent to ſeeme to be Papiſts, yet in theire hearts abhor the Trent faith, &amp; yet are not profeſt &amp; perfect proteſtants; (though the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitors when they finde in any point puniſh them for ſuch) as wanting libertie, and meanes of knowledge. Now if ſuch will not take the marke, helpe, profeſſe and defend the Trent faith, yet muſt they have the name of the Beaſt, be called latin, or Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:1648:28"/> Catholiks, that is vniverſals, of him the vniverſall Biſhop.<note place="margin">Or catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lik.</note> If one be loth to take his name, yet if he will buy and ſell, he muſt at leaſt have the number of the Beaſt come to the latin ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and vſe ſome latin ceremonies, heare the ſinging men &amp;c. as church papiſts have this that they come to the Engliſh churches, though they have no proteſtant religion in them: only they like well of the hierachie, traditions, cathedral ſervice and many ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, knowing whence they came and whither they tend: even to his kingdom &amp; ſervice who obtained of the murtherer Pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas to be called vniverſall Biſhop. For this beeing aboute the yeare 606. ſhortly after, he got the power of that title, and then from thenceforwards Romiſh cuſtomes, though never ſo ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious, were obſerved for lawes. <hi>Antonius</hi> of <hi>Valtelina,</hi> a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minican friar, in the councel of Trent ſaide,<note place="margin">Hiſtor. of the counc. of Trent. l, 6. p. 548.</note> 
               <hi>That it was plaine by all hiſtories, that anciently every church had her perticular Ritual of the Maſse, brought in by vſe and vpon occaſion, rather then by delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and decree; and that the ſmall churches did follow the Metropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litan and greater, which weere neere: The Roman rite had beene to gratifie the Pope received in many provinces. But,</hi> as he proved by a booke called Ordo Romanus, <hi>that of Rome had alſo had greate alterations, both in ancient and later times, within 300 yeares. Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that the veſtments and other ornaments of the Miniſters and Altars, as appeareth by bookes, Statues and pictures, are ſo changed, that if the ancients ſhould returne into the world, they would not know them: Therefore he concludeth that to binde all to approve the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Rites might be reprehended as a condemnation of antiquitie, and of the vſes of other Churches.</hi> Nevertheles the Engliſh Prelates, haveing retained many of them, and divers other Romiſh cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms in theire canons and hierarchie, doe binde all that are in theire Churches to approve and vſe them; and yet will not be perſwaded that this is to worſhip the Beaſt, or in part to haue his marke: Becauſe ſay they it is not donne on purpoſe to ſerve or flatter the Pope or Church of Rome.<note place="margin">Ioh. 16, 2,</note> Chriſt ſaith <hi>it ſhall come to paſſe that he that killeth you ſhall thinke he doth God ſervice,</hi> yet that doth not let, but that therein ſuch a murtherer or perſecutor doth ſerve the devil and his miniſters, I would they that are ſo zealous
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:1648:29"/> to maintaine humane authority, in traditions and ceremonies; would but lay theeſe things to heart. And withall, that it will not ſerve them to ſay,<note place="margin">Fullie.</note> they are fullie ſatisfied with thoſe reaſons which mayſter <hi>Hooker</hi> hath given, in his booke of Eccleſiaſticall politie; or D. Burgeſſe in his bookes againſt D. <hi>Ames,</hi> or any the like Authors, if the Teſtimonie of Ieſus be againſt them. All Fathers, all Authors, all councels, all reaſons, in ſuch caſes, are nothing to the Teſtimonie of Ieſus. On which argument, I ſhall neede to ſay the leſſe in this Treatiſe, becauſe of late divers works haue beene publiſhed that convince them of errour: in ſuch caſes as the curtaine of Church power.<note place="margin">The Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of Church power.</note> 
               <hi>A freſh ſuite againſt humane ceremonies in Gods worſhip,</hi> by that learned and godlie witneſſe D. Ames, a litle before his death: Alſo <hi>the crowne of a Chriſtian Martyr.</hi> A worke which he that loveth the Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and the ſafety of his owne Soule, hath reaſon to examin, becauſe the will of God, in theeſe caſes, is therein infalliblie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved;<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.2.</note> and as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Grace and peace is multiplied</hi> to men, <hi>through the knowledge of God and of Jeſus our Lord.</hi> Out of whoſe Teſtimonie, it is there manifeſted, that as the true Iewes, the true Chriſtians, ſo the true Ieruſalem, the true Church, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth of thoſe that keepe the commaundements of God, &amp; the faith of Ieſus, that hold faſt or defend the Doctrine, Diſcipline and ceremonies, which he left; Whence it muſt needes follow, that by ſo much as men maintaine, or approve, the inventions and preſumptions of men in Gods ſervice, by ſo much are they fallen into the ſinnes and fornications of Babylon, whereof one is ſtill the roote ſeede or ſpring of another; the leſſer wedges and cracks make way for the biggar; the ſmaler theeves, thruſt in at a window or hole, open the doores to the greater: Therefore though ſom ſay, ſo long as the Goſpell is well preached in ſom Pariſhes, why ſhould wee ſtumble at ſtrawes, or trouble our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves with trifles? yet wee ſhall finde, that in corrupt waters, men that thinke to goe but vp to the ancles, and no de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>per, do oft be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are aware of it, ſtep vp to the knees, then to the loines, and at laſt over head and eares: and ſo in ſuperſtition, ignorance, and errour: A few ſparks neglected do oft kindle a greate fire,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:1648:29"/> and as the Apoſtle ſaith <hi>A litle leaven leaveneth the whole lumpe?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5.9.</note> How then dare men defend ſtaines and corruptions to be ſmale matters?</p>
            <p>And what are theſe ſmale matters and trifles, which they ſay men doe ſoe vainly and fooliſhly ſtand vpon? The Lord by his Apoſtles <hi>ordained Elders in every church by election,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 14.</note> made them Biſhops, overſeers of the flock, to feede the church, to hold faſt that which Chriſt left, to govern according to his ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and keepe the church as a chaſt Ieruſalem from the inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and preſumtions of men: That men ſhould yet ſet vp dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſan Biſhops, who by bringing in a world of ſuperſtition and tyrannie into the church ſhould make theſe of none effect, and the church to become a Babylon, are trifles with them. They are trifles with them, that dioceſſan Biſhops ſhould have the power to admit into the miniſtrie, and to places of cure, whome, and vpon what conditions, they will, to enforce a conformitie and ſubſcription to theire hierarchie and ceremonies; though it be proved, that they take theire hierarchie, ſurpleſſe, coapes, Altars and other things from the Romaniſts, as they from the heathen, that theire cathedrall ſervice, and many of theire canons, are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from Babylon; as likewiſe theire power in theire offices and courts, to impoſe the oath, <hi>ex officio,</hi> to ſilence, ſuſpend, impriſon and deprive of cure and miniſtrie, for non-conformitie in theſe things: to enforce all to vſe a forme of praier, which is nothing but the maſſe in Engliſh, in ſom things refined, but not in all; the ſurpleſſe and other popiſh cuſtoms beeing ſtill retained: And though it be proved that the Papiſts doe much glorie in it, that theſe things ſtrengthen them in theire religion; that D. Iackſon and other Arminians, have alleadged it with ſuch authority; as men vſe to alleadge the Scriptures; that ſom things in it ſeeme to approve ſuch opinions: that ſuch things doe, by ſuch meanes, get into the place of the Scriptures; yet all muſt ſtill be maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: and that though it be alſo proved, that this forme of praier and ceremonies, doe oft ſerve drunkards, adulterers, prophane mockers, meere civill wordlings, vſurers, oppreſſors, and a world of earthly men, for a religion: though they have no true
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:1648:30"/> love to the preaching of the word, to knowledge, faith and the like graces, but ſcorne and perſecute ſuch as have, yet if they can but pretend love to the common praier, they are ready to count themſelves the better Chriſtians, the better ſubjects; they may the ſooner be choſen parliament men, or into any other office of the church or common wealth: and ſo they may come to beare greateſt ſway in proteſtant churches, who are church papiſts, ignorant in the ſpirituall government of Chriſt, &amp; other divine things, or greate enemies of the reformed religion: That non re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents, double benificed men, and dumbe miniſters, make this theire colour and defenſe, that they have in theire churches the common praier, and all the ceremonies; that Biſhops and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, whoſe example the greater part are ſubject to follow, do more favour theſe, then painfull and conſcionable miniſters; knowing that theire canons allow many to have two liveings: Becauſe alſo they finde, that ſuch men, will either defend theire hierarchie, and all theire doeings, or connive at them: That what ſoever the word of God ſay, yet if they can but get the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority &amp; aide of Princes, in any matter, they may ſilence all that withſtand them therein: that by this meanes they magnifying the power of Princes, and Synods, may get them into the place of the Pope, to defend any thing, and make it paſſe for lawfull in religion: And laſtly that all theſe things may ſerve church Papiſts and other perſecutors for a colour, that if they come but to the church, ſpeake well of the ſervice and ceremonies, who dare ſay they are not converts and proteſtants, vnder colour of hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Biſhops againſt puritans, they may vndermine the proteſtant religion, if not betray it abroade, yet doe by it at home, as Iehu did by the religion of Baal, make men thinke they are for it, when theire deviſe is by degrees to change and deſtroy it. Theſe, and many ſuch evils, beeing the branches and fruits of the hierarchie and ceremonies, are the trifles they talke off: wherein men ever heape to themſelves a multitude of teachers, according to theire owne affections, and grow ſo hardened by cuſtom, that they will not ſee with theire eies, nor heare with theire eares, any argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that, faithfully drawnen from the Scriptures, might con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:1648:30"/> and convert them: but ſtopping theire eares againſt the voice of the charmer, charme he never ſo wiſely, that curſe ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to be on them, which was laide on the Iewes for like ſinns, <hi>ſay vnto this people, ye ſhall heare indeede,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 6.9.10</note> 
               <hi>but you ſhall not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand,</hi> &amp;c. For if becauſe of theſe things, men deſire to follow the reformed churches, and have things reformed according to the ordinances of the new Teſtament, and the churches in time of the Apoſtles: this they call fooliſh nicenes, ſcrupuloſitie, and factious, ſtraining at gnats and trifles: and if any, by this meanes, be brought to heare the voice of Chriſt, and to leave them; they take on like a Beare robbed of her whelpes: and leaſt Princes and many others ſhould doe the like, they preſently looke on theire hierarchie, as on a citie beſieged: they fortifie it with men, with ſtout champions, and with words of mans wiſdom or power; with feigned words, rewards or threats, they guard mens eares from hearing the teſtimonie of Ieſus, that daily lies in bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie againſt it. Men ſhould therefore doubt that thoſe, which they count ſmal alterations, may doe greate miſchiefe; and that the devil will be ready to worke it out of the leaſt digreſſions from Chriſts inſtitutions; and rather then faile, vnder colour that ſom good either hath, or may, come by them.</p>
            <p>But howſoever, be they never ſo ſmal matters, the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and ceremonies God ordained muſt be obſerved, they may not be changed: for churches are willed to hold faſt that which they had received and heard.<note place="margin">Rev. 3.3.</note> The devil that made the Iewes to ſinne in one extreame, ſeeing chriſtians take heede of that, makes them to ſinne in another. Many Iewes ſtood all upon ceremonies, and obſerving of ſmal matters, as <hi>tithing of mint anniſe and cummin,</hi> and obſerving outward ſacrifices, ceremonies and ſhaddowes, they let the ſubſtance goe: ſo doe ſom Chriſtians, that ſtand and pleade earneſtlie for the ceremonies of the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive church, and that ſo continually, that they ſeeme to neglect the ſubſtance of religion; yea ſo vndiſcreetly, that they rather ſeeme to harden, and ſtrengthen the Adverſaries, then by good reaſons to convince them. Many heare this gladly, and with both theire eares: But their owne fault, in the meane while, is as
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:1648:31"/> greate, or greater: and theſe are two ſorts. 1. Some ſtand all, as they ſay for the ſubſtance of religion, and letting the ceremonie goe, doe in effect ſay, it mattered not for that, men might change, or alter it at pleaſure: Chriſt, taxing them both, ſaith of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and weightier things, <hi>Theſe ought ye to have donne, and not to have left the other vndonne.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 23.</note> Neither indeede can it be ſaide, that the preſbiterie or the ceremonies of the Goſpel, are ſmale things and not of the ſubſtance of religion, but might be changed. For though it be true, that, if it be aſked, what ſhall wee doe to live for ever? wee muſt have moſt reſpect to the fruite of the tree of life: yet if wee will be Iewes indeede, chriſtians indeede, ſuch as have right to the tree of life, wee muſt thinke wee can not have it, vnles wee take it with its proper barke and leaves; wee muſt not ſay the barke and leaves are not of the ſubſtance of the tree, or but ſmale matters: for the verie <hi>leaves of the tree are for the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the nations;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 22.</note> therefore no ſmalle matters, nor changeable: and the ſap and nouriſhment, which bringeth true fruite, goeth vp betweene the barke and the ſtock, ſo that, it may not be cut away or changed, as Babylon changed both the one &amp; the other, and ſo loſt her right to the tree of life. Her members and follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers did not keepe theire garments vndefiled, they did not walke with Chriſt in white; they were not righteous as Zacharie and Elizabeth, who <hi>walked in all the commaundements and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of the Lord;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 1.</note> they did not ſo keepe Gods commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as to have right to the tree of life. If, as they ſay, they are ſmale matters, they are the eaſier kept. Speaking of mens de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed hierarchie and ceremonies, they ſay, keepe and obſerve them, as ye would preſerve the life, fruite and ornament of a tree; if theeſe be broken off, the tree will die, all true religion decay and wither: chriſt may ſay, <hi>Hypocrite, out of thine owne mouth I will condemne thee:</hi> why then doe ye not looke to preſerve the tree of life among you, the new Teſtament, and the fruite of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, by preſerving or reſtoring the barke and the leaves, the preſbiterie and ceremonies of the Goſpel? when theſe were bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and changed, men loſt theire right to the tree of life, and the fruite of it, and in ſteade thereof were nouriſhed with cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:1648:31"/> ſuperſtition, ignorance, and errour: And ſo it will be where ever the reſtoring of theſe things is neglected or ſcorned, and the firſt humane inventious and preſumptions maintained. There, while ſuch things are made trifles as aboveſaide, all things muſt needes grow worſe and worſe. For Chriſt ſaith,<note place="margin">Luk. 16.</note> 
               <hi>He that is faithfull in the leaſt, he is alſo faithfull in much; and he that is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfull in the leaſt, he is alſo vnfaithfull in much:</hi> and indeede, becauſe men receive not the love of the truth in ſuch things, God gives them over to ſtrong deluſions to beleeve popiſh and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minian lies in greater: they will not heare of Chriſts raigning over them in the preſbiterie, in the firſt ordinances and ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies; therefore God gives them over to the rule of Prelates, Lords of Gods heritage, ſuch as daily burthen men with popiſh power, and ceremonies, and ſo get dominion over theire faith, as daily experience begins to manifeſt in England.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Hence it is, that as many Iewes were ſo zealous of ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies ordained of God, that they let goe the ſubſtance, and made them the greateſt part of theire Religion. So others, now adayes, ſtand all for a hierarchie of Dioceſſan Biſhops, and theire tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and ceremonies, deviſed or confirmed by men, ſom within two or three hundred yeares after the Apoſtles, and ſom ſince: when, as if the former had beene too plaine &amp; ſimple, if not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient, other more ſolemne and magnificent were thus inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that ſhould be of greate vſe, and haue notable ſignifications, <hi>whereby you might be edified,</hi> if you will beleeue them: They are ſo zealous of theeſe things, that they let the ſubſtance goe, and make them the greateſt part of theire Religion, which therefore muſt needes be a fault much worſe then that of the Iewes, and bring forth worſe fruite: becauſe the one were ceremonies or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained of God, the other deviſed by men:<note place="margin">Ier. 6.16.</note> And yet in zeale of theeſe, they tell vs, this is the old and good way, and abuſing that place of Ieremie, ſay wee ſhould <hi>walke in it,</hi> and are to be repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved if wee will not, as if theeſe were the leaves and barke of the tree of life, and all tree Religion would be loſt, if theeſe be not obſerved. But a liar muſt haue a good memorie. For when on the otherſide, wee tell them, the Apoſtles ordained Elders to be
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:1648:32"/> Biſhops in everie Church, to rule by the word, and that this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance was to be, as the barke to the tree of life, that betweene the ſame, and the ſtock of the tree, the ſap might paſſe ſo, as the fruite of righteouſneſſe might be brought forth, and the prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per leaues of the tree, kept greene, and in eſteeme, that this tree, had its propper leaves, the new Teſtament its proper ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, in the primitive age: In Churches then eſtabliſhed, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion was compleate;<note place="margin">Col. 2.5.</note> things were donne decently, in ſuch order, and with ſuch due ceremonies, as was Pauls joy to behold; they ſcoffe vs with noveltie, and ſay they were never ſince the time of Chriſt, or his Apoſtles. But by theire leaves, this ſcoffe proves them to be the old and good way that ſhortly after began to be changed to another, framed and ratified by the depths of Satan, as they ſpake: That to the Bride <hi>is graunted to be araied in pure and fine linnen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 19.</note> 
               <hi>white and cleane,</hi> by beeing redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to this old way, to this old righteouſnes of the Saints, by walking in <hi>all the commaundements and ordinances of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 1.</note> as Zacharie and Elizabeth did; and indeede as not onely the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Smyrna, and Philadelphia, but divers in Sardis did, who held faſt that which Chriſt left,<note place="margin">Reu. 3.</note> without receiving other: ſeeing the beſt of mens inventions and preſumptions are but <hi>ſtumbling blocks,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om. 14.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>and occaſions</hi> laide in mens wayes (by the cunning of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than) to make them fall to greater preſumption and ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as both hath appeared, and will yet further appeare, by thoſe which are received in England: and therefore indeede to draw the Bride, and all others, to the puritie and ſimplicitie of the firſt Chriſtians, it is added; <hi>for the fine linnen is the righteouſnes of the Saints:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 19.</note> The firſt government, the preſbiterie, the firſt cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, with the old order in choyce of miniſters, are then reſtored: It is then graunted to the Church to come to this righteouſnes of the Saints. Whatſoever is ſpoken of them, and theire Churches, and ordinarie orders, theeſe are all <hi>the true</hi> ſayings of God, to be obſerved. Humane inventions, will wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and preſumptions in Gods ſervice, as lies deviſed by men, are to be rejected.<note place="margin">Reu. 22.</note> And therefore it is added, <hi>Bleſſed are they that doe his commaundements</hi> (he doth not ſay mens, but <hi>his</hi> in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:1648:32"/> to theyres) <hi>that they may haue right to the tree of life:</hi> as if he ſaide, otherwiſe they can haue no right to the tree of life, nor to enter <hi>through the gates into the citie:</hi> but doe remaine without among dogges, <hi>ſorcerers</hi> and others: they are there ſo called, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they neither are, nor will wee be arayed in that white lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen, which <hi>is the righteouſnes of the Saints,</hi> ſuch as thoſe in Smyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, Philadelphia, and ſom in Sardis, who held faſt that which Chriſt left, but are enemies to ſuch righteouſnes, and yet do vainly beleeve that they are holy, and as good Chriſtians as the beſt becauſe they loue common prayer, and ſome other things. If God had ordained that verie forme of prayer, as he did the Iewiſh ſacrifices; yea if it were ſo greate a part of true religion, that, as theſe ſacrifices, it were oft put for the whole: yet they, in other things changing the ordinances, and breaking the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting covenant, muſt know, that of ſuch it is ſaide,<note place="margin">Pro. 15.8.</note> 
               <hi>The ſacrifice of the wicked is abhomination to the Lord. But the prayer of the righteous in acceptable to him:</hi> Theire prayer onely is his delight: that of others is abhomination to him: Much more, if in this theire ſacrifice theire fear towards God be taught after the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions and precepts of men; with ſopperies and ceremonies, which he commaunded not: theeſe make theire ſacrifice, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they thinke to pleaſe God, abhominable.</p>
            <p>The Church of England ſpeaking of ceremonies <hi>deviſed by man, why ſom be aboliſhed and ſom reteined,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Preface to the booke of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prayer in fol. Epheſ. 4.15.21.24.</note> confeſſeth that <hi>Chriſts Goſpel is not a ceremonial Law (as much of Moſes Law was) but it is a Religion to ſerve God, not in the bondags of the ſigne or ſhadow, but in the freedom ef the Spirit.</hi> They might haue added, beeing content onely with the ceremonies of the Goſpell, and <hi>to grow vp vnto him in all things which is the head, even Chriſt: If ſo be ye haue heard him and haue beene taught by him as the Truth is in Jeſus:</hi> Fot ſo ye <hi>put on the new man, which after God is cceated in righteouſnes and holines of the truth.</hi> But they adde, <hi>beeing content onely with thoſe ceremonies, which doe ſerve to a decent order a godlie Diſcipline, and ſuch as be apt to ſtirre vp the dull minde of man to the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of his duty to God, by ſome notable and ſpeciall ſignification, whereby he might be edified.</hi> And never conſidering that the church
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:1648:33"/> of Rome, who invented or eſtabliſhed and impoſed them ſayes the like of all other her ceremonies, they wilfully take the croſſe in baptiſme to be of this nature, and therefore ſay, <hi>wee ſigne him with the ſigne of the croſſe in token that hereafter he ſhall not be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to confeſſe the faith of Christ crucified, and manfullie fight vnder his banner againſt ſinne the world and the devill, and to continew Christs faithfull ſouldier and Servant vnto his lives ende.</hi> (In the times of Antichriſt, God indeede requireth theeſe excellent duties of all Chriſtians, but not this ſigning) as if beeing thus ſigned, he ſhould be the leſſe aſhamed to confeſſe the faith of Chriſt cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and more manfully ſight vnder his banner, then others that are not ſo ſigned; and as if this were a ceremonie and ſigne which would make him doe that dutie of a Chriſtian the better, which Chriſt requireth when he ſaith,<note place="margin">Rev. 2.</note> 
               <hi>him that ouercommeth &amp;c.</hi> For neither the Biſhops, who make all to be thus ſigned, nor the Engliſh in generall, haue proved more conſtant confeſſors and ſouldiers of Chriſt then the preſbiters and theire people in France and Germanie: they haue not more denied themſelves in ſinnes and worldly luſts of covetouſnes, ambition, vaine honour, dominion and the like, they haue not more ſtriven againſt po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie, Arminianiſme, ignorance and errour; nor in theeſe late wars for the defenſe of Chriſts religion and members, they haue not more ſtirred vp theire Princes to follow Chriſt: for they haue not donne it themſelves, nor ſuffered others that would, both in theeſe and in matters of the preſbiterie: So they make men take a pretended ſigne of ſuch a confeſſion and warfare, yet will not ſuffer them to doe the thing prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to be ſignified, but ſcorne and perſecute them that doe: They therefore whome for theeſe things, they call puritans doe truly beare the croſſe of Chriſt fot the Teſtimonie of Ieſus; while the Prelates, who in the meane, live in pompe and pleaſure, onely impoſe on others, and take on themſelves a beggarly ſigne with the hand, ordained, as they thinke, in greate Wiſdom: which yet doth never a whit the more ſtir them vp to theire duty, as is pretended. For in theeſe caſes, they mock and oppoſe the reaſons of Chriſts Souldiers the reformiſts, and haue rather ſided with ſuch againſt the parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:1648:33"/> as were rockoned trecherous and verie corrupt in reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; and therefore it is but a mockerie, and, as other things, onely carried out by humane Lawes, terrour and authority. They haue not in theeſe caſes obſerved that <hi>the fooliſhnes of God is wiſer then men;</hi> that he ſaith <hi>let no man deceive himſelfe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.25. chap. 3.18.</note> 
               <hi>If any man among you ſeemeth to be wiſe in this world, let him become a foole that he may be wiſe: for the Wiſdom of this world is fooliſhnes with God: He taketh the wiſe in theire owne craftineſſe. The Lord knoweth the thoughts of the wiſe that they are but vaine,</hi> as wee ſee in this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular. For God gives a better bleſſing to them which doe not ſeeke to ſtirre vp mens mindes to ſuch duties by ſignes; but by the Scripture, which is ſufficiently <hi>proffitable for doctrine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.16.17.</note> 
               <hi>for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe, for inſtruction in righteouſnes, that the man of God may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſect, thorowly furniſhed vnto all good works.</hi> What neede then is there of theeſe beggarlie deviſes? Signing with the ſigne of the croſſe doth not doe this, though they give ſuch a reaſon of it. Much leſſe can they prove that the vſe of coapes and hoods in ſervice, Altars, organs, ſinging men, whome few or none vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, or Antemes, whereof no ſuch ſpecious reaſons can be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, as beeing in ſavour heatheniſh, or Iewiſh, or popiſh, are apt by notable ſignifications to ſtirre vp men to theire duties to God. For they are rather offences or ſtumbling blocks, making men to fall to heatheniſme, Iudaiſme or poperie in ſom things: They cannot juſtifie them by the old Teſtament: for that ſerves as well to prove that ſacrifices and other Iewiſh ceremonies ſhould be ſtill obſerved, which to ſay were to lay a greate ſtumbling blocke, ſeeing they are all aboliſhed, and wee are to vſe no more then the new Teſtament alloweth. Howſoever the Engliſh, as ye ſee, haue not better donne theire duties, but more failed, then the reformed churches, who have none of theſe things. Now therefore whereas they alſo ſay,<note place="margin">Vbi ſupra.</note> 
               <hi>That ſom ceremonies entred into the church by vndiſcreete devotion, and ſuch a zeale as was without know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and for becauſe they were winked at in the beginning, they grew daily to more and more abuſes, which for theire vnproffitableneſſe, and becauſe they much blinded the people, and obſcured the glorie of God, are wortly to be cut away and cleane rejected,</hi> wee ſee that theſe
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:1648:34"/> are ſuch, that the ſigne of the croſſe is of this nature, &amp; by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves made ridiculous:<note place="margin">Rom. 14.13.</note> Such is theire Wiſdom. They doe not in this caſe obſerve that rule, <hi>that</hi> no <hi>man put a ſtumbling block</hi> or an occaſion to fall in his brothers way. And ſo alſo in matter of the ſurpleſſe: By theire rule, this is alſo apt to ſtirre vp the dull minde of man to the remembrance of his duty to God, by ſom notable ſignification, whereby he might be edefied. And therfore they bring Scriptures for it.<note place="margin">Reu. 6.9.</note> 
               <hi>They that were ſlaine for the word of God, and for the Testimonie which they held, had white roabes given vnto every one of them.</hi> It is therfore ſay they no hurt to impoſe the wearing of white, ſeeing peradventure in the Church of Martyrs this was deviſed to ſtir vp the dull minde of man to this duty.<note place="margin">Chap. 15.</note> 
               <hi>The ſeaven Angels come out of the Temple, haveing ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven plagues, clothed in pure and fine linnen:</hi> They as wee ſaw, haue the Teſtimonie of Ieſus, the marke of God; and indeede nothing is pure and white without it, And ſo haue thoſe alſo, of whome is ſaide,<note place="margin">Chap. 19.</note> 
               <hi>The armies which are in heauen followed him vpon white horſes, clothed in pure and white linnen.</hi> Which is not onely meant of thoſe, that helpe to get the victorie over Rome and the Beaſt by the ſword, but of thoſe alſo that doe it by the word of God: all theeſe haue white roabes. I anſwer, all this doth not warrant the Biſhops to impoſe on men a ſigne of this, much leſſe, as our Biſhops doe; and yet in divers particulars abovementioned, they, as the Popiſh Biſhops before them, doe not ſuffer them to doe the thing ſignified: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>herefore it is but a Popiſh tricke, and a moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerie to make men retaine, and weare that which at firſt was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, and is at this day vſed with ſuperſtition by the Papiſts. They cannot ſay theeſe are the fruits of the Spirit. <hi>For the fruite of the Spirit is in all goodnes and righteouſnes and truth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.9</note> Marke in Truth: not then in ceremonies, ſignes and ſhewes. They ſay, white is a note of puritie, innocencie, victorie, and gladneſſe: and ſo indeede it is: yet, as wee have ſeene, they are far enough from that white linnen, or puritie, which is <hi>the righteouſnes of the Saints</hi> there meant: And indeede, they are not more innocent, victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and pure, then other Proteſtants, that doe not weare the white garment, but rather more Popiſh and corrupt. They doe
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:1648:34"/> not now, neither in Doctrine, diſcipline, nor manners, ſo hold faſt the word, as the Saints did in ſom of the ſeaven Churches: Men Popiſh may not onely come to theire communions, but even knowne drunkards, fornicators, Prophane mockers of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious excerciſes, and other like wicked men.</p>
            <p>It was an ordinance of the ceremoniall Law,<note place="margin">Exod. 28.2.40.</note> 
               <hi>thou ſhalt make holy garments for Aaron thy brother, for glorie and for beautie:</hi> And for Aarons Sonnes, <hi>thou ſhalt make coates and girdles, and bonnets, for glorie and for beautie.</hi> Theeſe, beeing commaunded, might then ſtir vp the dull minde of man to remembrance of his dutie: for God then taught them by ceremonies and ſhaddowes: But now they cannot, ſuch Lawes beeing aboliſhed, and the truth cleerely preached; to vſe them is greate preſumption: &amp; to deviſe others, <hi>for glorie and for beautie,</hi> more then were in time of the Apoſtles, whether they be ſurpleſſes, coapes, or Rochets, and the like, is far greater preſumption: and namely to chooſe rather to be edified, by ſhaddowes of humane invention, then by the cleere and all-ſufficient Truth of God, revealed in Chriſt: yea, to deceive our ſelves, becauſe the ſurpleſſe, wee ſee, doth nothing ſtir vp mens mindes to doe the duties of thoſe, who are ſaide to weare white, as the ſeaven Angels, the bride, and thoſe that follow Chriſt, on white horſes. For among others, the preſbiters ſit round aboute Chriſts throne in white raiment,<note place="margin">Reu. 4.4.</note> which ſetteth forth the puritie of theire order; yet Prelates, and theire defenders, are ſo far from following that government, that they cannot abide to heare of it. This therfore pretended to be donne to edifying, is but like the dog in the fable to catch, and make others catch, at the ſhadow, &amp; let goe the ſubſtance: they will not ſuffer men to take the marke of God in ſome points.</p>
            <p>It is in the caſe of Euangelicall precepts, as in that of the ten commandements; the beſt do many times of infirmitie breake them; and ſo ſinne againſt the Teſtimonie of Ieſus, which alſo hath many rules; and therfore theeſe that weare the white roabes, haveing no doubt ſome ſtaines of infirmitie, are faine to <hi>waſh theire roabes, and make them white in the blood of the lambe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 7.14.</note> Now the fault of the Prelates is not of this kinde; but as when
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:1648:35"/> a man breaketh any of the commandements. And teacheth men ſo, though he be zealous in all the reſt, yet this is abhominable before God,<note place="margin">Gal. 3.1.</note> that therein he <hi>will not obey the Truth,</hi> nor heare of it; O <hi>fooliſh men who hath bewitched you that ye ſhould not obey the Truth?</hi> If the queſtion be asked to thoſe of the Church of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland; the anſwer is ready, Surely the honours and proffits of this world. For as the Galathians did not obey it in ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, no more doe theeſe in others. Many not onely of the Romiſh, but even of the Engliſh Miniſters that are conformable haue in other things <hi>the Teſtimonie of Jeſus,</hi> and in many points hold it with zeale againſt Hereticks, but in the matter of the preſbiterie, the power that God gaue to each Church or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, and things that are againſt the hierarchie and ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, they change and breake the ordinance of God, and teach men ſoe. Such is the fruite of the hierarchie, it makes, men feare and flatter the Prelates, and haue the truth of God in reſpect of perſons;<note place="margin">Pro. 28.23</note> and as the Scripture ſaith, <hi>to haue reſpect of perſons is not good: for, for a peece of bread that man will tranſgreſſe.</hi> Much more, that he may get or hold a liveing; and moſt of all for a Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrick or denarie. They doe not in this caſe obſerve that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of the old and new Teſtament,<note place="margin">Zach. 8.16 Eph. 4.25.</note> 
               <hi>ſpeake ye euery man the truth to his neighbour.</hi> The Biſhops do in this caſe, as the Papiſts doe in this and others, they will not ſo much as ſuffer Princes, much leſſe other men, to heare of the Preſbiterie, and the grounds and reaſons that ſhow it ought to be maintained, but ſcorne and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute thoſe that ſeeke or defend the truth. So they <hi>withhold the truth in vnrighteouſneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1.14</note> 
               <hi>and change it into a lie.</hi> They hold that though God ordained the preſbiterie, gaue each Church power to chooſe theire miniſter, and him to receive the gift by laying on of the hands of the preſbyterie, to excomunicate &amp;c. Yet as the Church was enlarged, another government might be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, and now he is better pleaſed with theire hierarchie, tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions and ceremonies, that is, that wee turne againe to weake and beggarlie rudiments, be againe in bondage to them, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve dayes and times &amp;c. And ſo that he ordaineth or allo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth theeſe. Yea ſom of them change the truth of God into
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:1648:35"/> a lie, while they wilfully take that to be ſpoken of dioceſſan Biſhops, which is ſpoken of the preſbiters. And beeing driven from that, for want of more divine warrant, they are ever telling men of the Queenes injunctions, of the ſtatute and proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the peace the Engliſh have ſince enjoied, knowing that men dare not ſpeake ſo boldly againſt theſe, as themſelves doe againſt the preſbiterie ordaind of God; without any feare, that he may ſay vnto them, <hi>wilt thou diſanull my judgment,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 40.8.</note> to eſtabliſh thy owne, or the inventions of men? <hi>wilt thou condemne me, that thou</hi> or they may <hi>be righteous?</hi> What good doe ye to your Kings, by flattering them with the emptie name of a prerogative in things ſo many waies againſt me, and good government? Can they get any good by that, or by making Iſrael to ſinne? Doe not you your ſelves run away with the wordly proffit and honour of it? Have I not manifeſted how the church of Rome became the greate whore?<note place="margin">Gal. 4.25.</note> and ſhewed you of a new Ieruſalem that is to <hi>come downe from God, as a bride prepared for her husband</hi> and arraied in white; which is, when the church gives the kingdom in all things vnto her God, when ſhe is neither defiled, burdened nor in bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage vnder precepts and inventions of men; that the Ieruſalem <hi>which is from above, is free,</hi> and will ye yet be in bondage, and pleade to bring others to ſuch bondage? Will ye yet give the Kingdom and dominion to men in theſe things? Will ye pretend your ſelves to be ſpirituall, Biſhops, miniſters, or Chriſtians for me, and yet mock at this Ieruſalem, at this bride, and thoſe that deſire to ſee her ſo adorned? ye have no ſuch affections, ye doe not put them on, as a wedding garment, but to terrifie and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie them that doe, or would, ye thunder in talke of proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Statutes and inventions, like them that with trumpets, drums, or the like things, made a noiſe when they ſacrificed theire children vnto Idols leaſt theire cries ſhoud move pitie and remorſe. All your pretences and thundrings are for Kings and councels, for theire prerogatives and lawes in theſe caſes. Let others prove what they will for me, theſe muſt make them ſpeechles now, what ever make you ſpeechles herafter for not haveing on a wedding garment. Ye talke of faith: but ſhew me
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:1648:36"/> your faith by your workes or affections in this cauſe. Will true faith ſtand with oppoſing &amp; ſcorning me in theſe things? Whome doe ye deſpiſe, againſt whome doe deſpite and make war in all theſe things?</p>
            <p>Herein they have no way to avoide Antichriſtianiſme, but to ſay with Cardinal Cuſanus <hi>that the vnderstanding or ſenſe of the Scripture goeth with the practiſe of the church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">C. Cuſan. ad Bohem. epiſt. 2. &amp; epiſt. 7.</note> and ſo in effect that Gods minde is changed in theſe things: or which is all one, that notwithſtanding his ordinance of the preſbiterie, he hath left the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to Princes and councels, they might ordaine dioceſſan Biſhops, traditions and ceremonies. Now is it not a greate diſhonour to God, to ſay that his minde is ſo changed that they might ordaine them, and ſo change the government? For while they ſay they ought to be obeied in all theſe things, they withall tell vs, that Gods will is that it ſhould be ſo: which is in effect to corrupt the word of God, and to ſay his minde is in theſe things mutable. One of the firſt and greateſt hereſies was that of Ebion, who as Euſebius and Irenaeus ſhew vs,<note place="margin">Hiſtor. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. l. 3. c. 24. Iren. adve. haereſ. l. 4. prolog.</note> 
               <hi>denied Chriſt to have beene alwaies God, and the word and wiſdom of God, and refuſed part of the new</hi> Teſtament. And of them indeede Irenaeus ſaith, <hi>They blaſpheme againſt the Lord, ſevering and dividing Ieſus from Chriſt, and Chriſt from the Saviour, and againe the Saviour from the word, and the word from the only begotten.</hi> Now if the Biſhops doe not ſever the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour from the word, and the word from the only begotten, yet it is an hereſie ſomwhat a kin to this, to change the truth of God into a lie, to refuſe part of the Teſtament, touching the preſbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie, and to ſay that the ſame ordinances aboute this, and the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of each church to chooſe miniſters and excommunicate, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>the power of Chriſt,</hi> are not now his word and ordinances, nor the power of Chriſt to be followed of all churches: that theſe things might be taken from them, and given to one in a dioceſſe, which is indeede to take them from Chriſt, who hath truſted the churches with them: that they are things indifferent, that councels and Kings might change them, or ſet vp others that turne from the Truth, and are ſoe contrarie; that his will is that theſe ſhould now be obeied and followed, and not thoſe which himſelfe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained:
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:1648:36"/> which is to ſay his will is changeable. All this, beeing in effect affirmed by them, is downright the marke of the Beaſt. For ſo papiſts argue in the ſame caſes, and in thoſe of Images, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in one kinde, the primacie and the like. And yet we know that the new Teſtament, and all the ordinances thereof are from everlaſting, yea eternall and vnchangeable Mat. 13.35. Rom. 16.35. Epheſ. 1.9.11.2. Tim. 1.9. Ioh. 12.48. and Ioh. 1.1.2.3.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.7. &amp; Heb. 13.8.</note> And ſo the Apoſtle ſaith <hi>Ieſus Chriſt yeſterday and to day and the ſame alſo for ever.</hi> Thus they that in the Revelation weare white, hold <hi>faſt the teſtimonie of Jeſus:</hi> The Biſhops neither doe ſo, nor ſuffer others that would, but with flaterie and threats make many preach, and write in defenſe of theire power, traditions &amp; ceremonies, and ſo to make war againſt the lambe. Biſhops them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves therefore had neede of one in theſe caſes <hi>to open theire eies to turne them from darkneſſe to light;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.8</note> 
               <hi>and from the power of Satan vnto God. For as Iannes and Iambres withſtood Moſes, ſo doe theſe alſo reſiſt the Truth; men of corrupt mindes:</hi> and by theire tyranous impoſing of theſe things, <hi>cauſe diviſions and offences,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 17.</note> 
               <hi>contrarie</hi> to the Apoſtolike doctrine, and therein <hi>ſerve not the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, but theire owne bellie, and with faire ſpeeches deceive the hearts of the ſimple.</hi> I would they that are counted both learned, and wiſe, were not as commonly deceived by theire flatteries and falſe gloſſes.</p>
            <p>They likewiſe make men bow toward the Altar, and at the name of Ieſus, not at other names of Chriſt, or God his father, and kneele at the receiving of the Sacrament, as if they did more reverence and obey Chriſt the word, then others that doe not theſe things; though as wee ſhewed, it is but a popiſh, and a late deviſe: And yet they themſelves can not bow to Chriſt in his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of the preſbiterie, and the power he gave to each church, nor endure to heare of it, but hinder others that would: Can they be Chriſts Biſhops? When Elijah heard the voice of God, <hi>he wrapped his face in his mantle,</hi> for the reverence that he bare to Gods word. When the Spirit of the Lord came vpon Iehazel,<note place="margin">1. King. 19.2. 2. Chro. 29 14.18.</note> ſo that he ſpake the word of the Lord, <hi>Iehoſhaphat bowed his head with his face to the ground, and all Iudah fell before the Lord, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:1648:37"/> the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. King. 20.19.</note> And when a ſentence was pronounced againſt Hezechiah for his ſinne, yet he ſaide, <hi>Good is the word of the Lord that thou haſt ſpoken.</hi> And Iohn ſo reverenced the word of God that he was ready to worſhip the Angel that ſhewed it him; who thereupon ſaide, <hi>ſee thou doe it not: worſhip God.</hi> All theſe and the like places ſhew the greate reverence that is due to the word. It is, the name of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Rev. 19.</note> 
               <hi>His name is called the word of God.</hi> A name that could never be given to any other, a name above all names: and therefore this is that name of Ieſus, at which every knee ſhould bow: where yet it is not ſo much meant of bodily worſhip with the knee, as receiving the word with faith and obedience: obeying the truth is the true worſhip. Thoſe that doe not this, are called ſtifnecked, ſuch as will not bow. And ſuch are the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops,<note place="margin">Act. 7.</note> who yet in the meane mock God with a beggarlie ſigne of ſuch obedience: which therefore is not apt to ſtir vp the dull minde of man to a remembrance of this duty to God, but is a meere complement, a ſhew: And indeede this and other theire ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, inſteade of doeing good, ſerve thouſands for a reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, or a ſhew of one, and in place of that wich God comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth.</p>
            <p>For brevitie ſake, I omit to ſpeake of other cathedrall cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, and to obſerve the like poperie, tyranie and abuſe in many of theire canons, courts and cuſtomes as is ſhewed in the Curtaine of church power,<note place="margin">Curtaine of Church power.</note> certaine it is, that many have litle re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion beſides, and that many who defend them, doe it on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, to make them inductions to other poperie, and becauſe they are fit maſkes to cover theire popiſh, or prophane practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. So that beeing thus grosſly abuſed, they may, and by theire owne rule ought to be taken away and cleane rejected. But they will have nothing reformed, or changed: yet they themſelves, as others before them, have changed the ordinance of God, which is a moſt adulterous fact: and therfore whereas ſom ſay, if wee goe aboute to alter, or reforme any thinge, wee ſhall never be quiet, till all be brought to Annabaptiſme, or Browniſme. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer this is, as if one ſhould ſay, you may not turne a woman from poperie or adulterie, for feare ſhe turne Annabaptiſt. They
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:1648:37"/> ſhould therefore deale plainly with vs, and ſay, to maintaine theire hierarchie, the greatnes of a few Prelates; theire pompe, theire coaches and pallaces, the truth muſt be ſuppreſſed, the church and common weale corrupted, and the whole world di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed.<note place="margin">Mic. 3.11.</note> 
               <hi>The heads thereof judge for reward</hi> &amp;c. <hi>yet they leane vpon the Lord, and ſay, is not the Lord among vs? None evill can come vpon vs. Her prophets are light and trecherous perſons:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zepha. 3.4. Eze. 22.26 Haba. 1 3.</note> 
               <hi>her prieſts have pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted the ſanctuarie, they have done violence to the law. There are that raiſe vp ſtrife and contention. Therfore the law is ſlacked, and judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment doth never go forth: for the wicked compaſſe aboute the righteous: therefore wrong judgment proceedeth.</hi> They ſo wreſt the truth to maintaine theire hierarchie and traditions and will not ſee the truth of God in theſe things, that almoſt all men after theire ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample turne prevaricators.<note place="margin">Mic. 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>O thou that art named of the howſe of Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, is the Spirit of the Lord ſtreitened? are theſe his doings? do not my words doe good to him that walketh vprightly?</hi> Therefore <hi>trust ye not in lying words, ſaying, the Temple of the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 7.4.</note> 
               <hi>The Temple of the Lord are theſe:</hi> as the Engliſh crie, the church, the church, The church of the Lord are theſe Biſhops and theire defenders.<note place="margin">Chap. 18.18.</note> 
               <hi>For the law ſhall not periſh from the Priest, nor counſell from the wiſe, nor the word from the prophet.</hi> The Lord anſwereth ſuch proud men, <hi>How doe ye ſay, wee are wiſe, and the Law of the Lord is with vs.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chap. 8, 8.9.</note> 
               <hi>They have rejected the word of the Lord, and what wiſdom is there in them? for from the least to the greateſt every one is given to covetouſnes; from the prophet to the prieſt every one dealeth falſly. For they have healed the hurt of the daughter of my people, ſleightlye; ſaying, peace, peace, when there is no peace. They are wicked in theſe things;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 57.21.</note> 
               <hi>and there is no peace to the wicked ſaith my God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therfore whereas ſom ſay; there are ſtill ſome good prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, yea ſom that are conformable. I anſwer, ſo were there in thoſe firſt ages after Conſtantine. But the zeale of theſe Canons and inventions did more and more take vp mens mindes, and eate out the other. It is true in this caſe, as in that of riches: The church hath brought forth riches, dignities, dioceſſan dominion, Canons, ceremonies, cringes; Altars; maſſes, &amp;c. The daughters have devoured the mother in Romiſh churches, and ſo they will
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:1648:38"/> in England, if God prevent it not. And therefore whereas others ſay, ſo long as wee may have the Goſpel well preached in ſom pariſhes, why ſhould wee trouble our ſelves with theſe things? I anſwer ought not ſuch men to take care, that the Goſpell may be continued to them and theire children in that puritie &amp; ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie, wherein it was left by the Apoſtles? Which, as ye ſee, can not be,<note place="margin">Ier. 2.35.</note> if thoſe things be not reformed: for they <hi>turne from the Truth, yet thou ſaiest, Becauſe I am innocent, ſurely his anger ſhall turne from me.</hi> Conſtantius could never have ſpread the Arrian hereſie, ſo far as he did, but by the helpe of Biſhops. For a Biſhop beeing like a King, or a Pope in his dioceſſe, the moſt will out of feare, or flatterie, follow him, as he doth the Prince or mightie fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourite, what ever his religion be, becauſe he can either raiſe him to more honour, or trouble him. And therfore it may be ſaide of the hierarchie, ceremonies and ordinances, and theire defenders, If they be not with Chriſt and his kingdum, in theſe caſes they <hi>are againſt him;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 12.30.</note> 
               <hi>and if they gather not with him,</hi> they <hi>ſcatter</hi> &amp; helpe the Adverſaries. For in theſe times thoſe that are Chriſts ſeeke to <hi>get the victorie over the Beaſt, and over his marke.</hi> Some by prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching or writing,<note place="margin">Rev. 15.2.</note> others by theire lawes and ſwords, and others by theire profeſſing, and contending earneſtly for the faith which was once delivered to the ſaincts: others by theire praiers, and other honeſt indeavours: While on the other ſide, Papiſts and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelings contend as earneſtly for the obſervation and authority of trad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tions and ceremonies; which is the marke of the Beaſt, though they covering the matter, call them the vnwritten word of God.</p>
            <p>Bellarmin in his 4. booke of the vnwritten word of God Chap. 2, maketh three ſorts of traditions. <hi>1. Divine, which were ſpoken by Chriſt, but not written; 2 Apostolike, ſpoken by the Apostles, but not written. 3. Eccleſiaſticall, which, he ſaith, are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced from ancient cuſtomes by the Prelates, or by the people, and creepingly by the ſilent, &amp; vnquestioning agreement of the people, have gained ſtrength of law.</hi> And indeede have at one time or other beene confirmed by councels. A man may here ſee, what miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe followed the firſt vnqueſtioning agreement and conſent
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:1648:38"/> of the people. For of this ſorte, as the fountaine of all the reſt, is the authority of dioceſſan Biſhops, theire power in theire Courts and Canons, excommunicating, impriſoning &amp;c. and ruling both the ordinarie paſtors and people with force and crueltie in divers things; which, as was ſhewed, did creepingly by the ſilent and vnqueſtioning agreement of the people gaine the ſtrength of law, and ſupplanted the preſbiterie ordained of God, and the power of each congregation in chooſing theire miniſter and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicating the refractarie; and ſo made of none effect that law of Chriſt, <hi>Tell the church,</hi> the preſbyters and people.<note place="margin">Ezech. 34.2. to. 12.</note> And then the dioceſſan office ſerved not to feede <hi>the flock of God, but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves:</hi> the flock became a prey to ſuch Shepheards: yea dioceſſan power, beeing thus invented and eſtabliſhed, became <hi>a ſnare, and net,</hi> as the Prophet ſaide to <hi>the Prieſts, and howſe of the King.</hi> For then followed theire traditions, the diſtinction of meates,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 5.1.</note> the obſervation of holy daies, feaſts and faſts, wearing the ſurpleſſe, and more then ſixe hundred yeares after Chriſt the latin ſervice, ſinging antemes by the ſound of the organs, ſetting vp of Altars, bowing to them, and at the name of Ieſus, building, guilding, adorning, and conſecrating of cathedrall churches, endowing them with greate revenues, ſigning themſelves with the ſigne of the croſſe, ſetting vp Images in churches to a religions vſe, and likwiſe candles, invocation of Saints, and praying vpon beades; the Popes ſucceſſion in Peters chaire, ſingle life of Prieſts, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie, and perſecution to thoſe that would not beleeve theſe &amp; the like things. All which were introduced fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ancient cuſtomes, by the Prelates or people, and creepingly gained ſtrength of law one after another; and in ſhort time ſerved men for a reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; the defence of the firſt making way for all the reſt, as men do now begin to perceive in England; where, as the hierarchie it ſelfe, ſo divers of theſe things, beeing popiſh, are preached by Biſhops and others, and begin to get the ſtrength of law, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally to make way for the reſt, and indeede to ſerve men for a religion, if God prevent it not:<note place="margin">2. Cor. 11.3.</note> So ſoone doth <hi>the Serpent through his ſubtiltie beguile men, and corrupt theire mindes from the ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie that is in Chriſt,</hi> for as wee ſhewed, they doe not tend to edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:1648:39"/> as is pretended, but to deſtruction, ſeeing Biſhops by them doe rule men with force and crueltie Ezech. 34.4.</p>
            <p>The word of God, &amp; ſuch obſervations as rightly ariſe from it, doe truly edifie, ſo doe the Sacraments, to men that know the truth: the inventions and ordinances of men, haveing but a ſhew of godlineſſe, and Wiſdom, are but beggarly rudiments, yea <hi>turne from the Truth:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 1.23. Gal. 4.8. Tit. 1.14.</note> And yet ſo things goe, as if the authority of the Prelates, which puts all men to ſilence, or makes them flatter, might give them the ſtrength of Law, and make men beleeve that Gods will is, that they ſhould be obeyed, which is in effect, to make them his vnwritten word: For his will is his word. But this is as the vnwritten word, the Papiſts talke of; and ye ſee they doe but talke of it: For they confeſſe theeſe things were intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced from ancient cuſtomes, and creepingly by the ſilence of the people, who were vrged to conformitie by the flattering and menacing clergie, and loth to be counted Schiſmatikes, Refra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctarie &amp; Puritans, they gained the ſtrength of Law, ſome ſooner, ſome later, but all in a like manner, as beeing the inventions of ambition, will worſhip, ſuperſtition and tyranie: to which God gaue them over, becauſe like the Angels, they kept not theire firſt Eſtate,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.20</note> 
               <hi>they did not like to retaine God in theire knowledge,</hi> they did not abide in the truth, nor in theeſe caſes received the love thereof; but as the flattering defenders of the Engliſh hierarchie and traditions, they ſcorned and mocked all that oppoſed them, and ſought puritie in Religion, as fooles, Schiſmatikes, and hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crits, that ſtrained as they ſay, at gnats, and made ſchiſmes aboute trifles: this mocking was that which gaue all manner of corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſtrength and in creaſe as it doth in England. Where he is reckoned a wiſe able divine that knows how to ſcoffe ſuch men out,<note place="margin">Gal. 5.9.</note> as Papiſts did. <hi>A litle leauen leaveneth the whole lumpe:</hi> They thus corrupted, were given ouer to beleeue lies.</p>
            <p>This averſion from the creators word, was a converſion to the word of creatures, to the decrees of men, in Synods and councels:<note place="margin">Ier. 2, 13.</note> It was a <hi>forſaking of the Lord, the fountaine of liveing waters, and hewing them out broken ciſterns that can hold no water:</hi> And becauſe they did not take the marke of God, to contend
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:1648:39"/> earneſtly for the faith once delivered to the Saints, and ſeeke to get the victorie over the Beaſt, and his Image and marke, as all Chriſtians ſhould, God gaue them over to take the marke of the Beaſt, to worſhip him and his Image, and to drinke of the golden cup, which the greate whore holdeth, <hi>full of abhominations,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 17.</note> 
               <hi>and filthineſſe of her fornication:</hi> Such honour, offices, dominion, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, worſhip ceremonies and Religion, as God never ordained. But what cared they, ſo they could but, by theire flatterie and falſe gloſſes, get the conſent and helpe of Princes, and make them beleeve this was to defend the Church, which either as they did, or omitted, God would proſper or puniſh them: For thus they made Emperours &amp; Kings take pleaſure to aſſiſt them: and ſo as the Prophet ſaith,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 7.3.</note> 
               <hi>They make the King glad with theire wickedneſſe, and the Princes with theire lies:</hi> And ſo indeede did the falſe Prophets in Ieremies time, and likewiſe in the time of Ahab and other Kings. And therfore the Angel ſeeing the greate wickedneſſe of the whore of Babylon in theeſe things, and the deſtruction that was ready to fall on her for them ſaith,<note place="margin">Reu. 18.2.3.</note> 
               <hi>Babylon the greate is fallen, is fallen, and is become the habitation of deuls, and the hold of euerie foule Spirit, and a cage of everie vncleane and hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full bird: for all nations haue drunke of the wine of the wrath of her fornication.</hi> (viz. to which God in his wrath gaue her and them over) <hi>And the Kings of the earth haue committed fornication with her</hi> (enforcing her Lawes and errours on th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ire ſubjects) <hi>and the Marchants of the earth are waxed rich through the abundance of her delicacies:</hi> that is, which ſhe had neede of for the maintaining of the pompe of her Prelates, ceremonies and Tempels; <hi>The merchandiſe of gold, and ſilver, and precious ſtones,</hi> and of <hi>pearles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">ver. 12,</note> 
               <hi>and fine linnen, and purple, and ſilke, odours and frankencenſe &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now obſerve this committing of fornication with her is of two ſorts. 1. When Kings and States give theire power and ſtrength to the Beaſt and Church of Rome, fighting his battailes, and enforcing her Lawes, cuſtoms, and errours on theire people. 2. When they commit ſome of the ſame evils, or the like, though not all, as ſhe doth: Kings commit fornication with her, who doe it in ſom things, though not in all: Yea though
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:1648:40"/> they doe them not in obedience to her, or to pleaſe or ſerve her. Henrie 8. denied the Popes ſupremacie, yea, was at difference with the Church of Rome, in ſom things, yet ſtill committed fornication with her in other things, by houlding and maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning divers other of the Romiſh Lawes, errours and cuſtomes. Any man holdeth the Doctrine of Balaam, that layeth a ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling block before the people, though it be not the verie ſame kinde of ſtumbling block; which Balaam taught, but ſom other. To be guiltie of Ierobams ſinne was not alwayes to ſet vp calves: but he departed not from the ſinnes of Ieroboam, who by any other invention, or preſumption, made Iſrael to ſinne. Som follow the way of Kaine,<note place="margin">Iude 11.</note> ſome periſh in the gainſaying of Corah, and ſome are caſt away by the deceitfulnes of Balams wages, though not in the ſame particulars, nor in the ſame manner, but in a like. So do ſome Kings commit fornication with Babylon, who maintaine any of her preſumptions, or any like them. The Greeke Churches, from the yeare 607. that the Pope had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to be called vniverſall Biſhop, haue ſeperated from the Church of Rome; denying not onely the ſupremacie but euen worſhipping of Images, and ſom other Romiſh errours: Yet in retaining the hierarchie of dioceſſan, Provinciall, and Patriar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chall Biſhops, the maſſe, &amp; divers other Romiſh cuſtoms, errours, and ceremonies, both before the yeare 607. and ſince, they haue committed fornication with her. While in theeſe things theire feare toward God is alſo taught by the traditions and precepts of men, they haue cauſe to feare, Chriſt will not finde them to be of his Ieruſalem, but of Babylon the greate, not of his true Church, but of the Synagogue of Sathan: For he reckoneth all to be of the one or the other. The ſecond councell of Nice taught and commaunded worſhipping of Images: And then the Greek Emperour with his mother <hi>Irene</hi> and many Greekes, committed fornication in that particular with Babylon. M. Moulin obſerveth how abſurd and weake the reaſons of thar councell were:<note place="margin">Buckler of the faith, in preface,</note> Yet if Kings and councels once maintaine ſuch errours, how weake and fooliſh ſoever theire reaſons be, many are ſoone ready to follow and flatter theire pernicious wayes: So
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:1648:40"/> likewiſe in matter of the Lords day, or any other commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, if they giue allowance to Prophane or breake it; you doe in vaine tell theire flatterers of Gods Law: they will ſtop your mouth, or crie you downe with vrging the Lawes of men, the Kings injunctions, or the like ſhifts, the common refuges of the moſt ſuperſtitious and Prophane men: How abſurdly doe ſuch in theire much magnified common prayer ſay, <hi>Lord haue mercie vpon us and encline our hearts to keepe this Law,</hi> when they thus allow and defend the breach of it?</p>
            <p>It is a verie poore honour to maintaine a power and Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative in ſuch caſes againſt the Lord, and his ordinances and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants: Kings doe at laſt take theeſe things into conſideration, when after the new Ieruſalem is manifeſted, they bring theire glorie and honour to it. They then begin to ſee that the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is on Chriſts Shoulders; that men ought to obſerve his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances onely in matters of Religion: that for want of holding this firme, many abhominations have entred into churches and nations: That all theſe evils follow that errour, that the church hath power to ordame, change or abrogate ceremonies, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any neceſſity, like that, where, in ſome countries, by reaſon of theire coldnes, the body is not dipped in Baptiſme, but ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kled. For when Prelates have once got this concluſion to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, that <hi>wee are bound to the ceremonies and inſtitutions of the church, ſo that whoſoever doth wittingly neglect them is guiltie of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience, and breach of the firſt commaundement;</hi> as it pleaſeth them to infer; they can not reſt there: but then they get more ground of vs, and taking it for granted that themſelves are the church, they ſay <hi>wee are to aſcent to the opinions of the church in controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies of faith, and may not forſake theire definitions, although they doe not agree to our owne particular opinions therein.</hi> And that they will call our owne particular opinions, which, though it have the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie of Ieſus, agreeth not with theires; men that by theire ſeeking after wealth, honour, and authority ſhew that they are of this world: And when they have alſo got this tenet to be once received, they can, at the pleaſure of any that may, advance them, introduce any errour of the Romiſh church, or other wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:1648:41"/> men, and by theyre power carrie it out againſt the moſt learned and zealous. They will boldly affirme the office of dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſan Biſhops to be of divine inſtitution: That the Sacraments confer grace <hi>ex opere operato:</hi> ſo of other things, wherein they will vnder one pretext or other, forbid refutation of ſuch errours: knowing that if they can but get the countenance of Princes, though never ſo ignorant in ſuch things, the moſt will out of feare or flatterie follow them, and the reſt will be forced to hold in their heads; and ſo they eaſily get a dominion ouer mens faith: ſuch ſhamefull lukewarmenes, errour and tempori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing doth the defenſe of the hierarchie and ceremonies bring forth, and ſo greate a ſtumbling block are they to make men fall to other Romiſh corruptions and errours: which indeede are the naturall fruits of that tree. Councels and Kings doe not thinke of thoſe things, <hi>why tempt ye God to put a yoake vpon the neck of the Diſciples,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 15.10 Rom. 14.13.</note> 
               <hi>which neither our fathers nor wee were able to beare. Iudge this rather, that no man put a stumbling blocke or an occaſion to fall in his brothers way.</hi> But as if theeſe precepts did not binde them, they put heavie yoakes on the necks of Chriſtians, and manifeſt ſtumbling blocks in mens waies, as Babylon hath donne and therefore no marvaile if the Angel ſay, <hi>The Kings of earth have committed fornication with her.</hi> Of whome therefore, and theire flatterers, God may demaund, as ſomtime of the Iewes <hi>what iniquitie they or theire fathers had found in him:</hi> what want of wiſdom or perfection in his Teſtament and ordinances, <hi>that they were gone from him after theire vanities</hi> and inventions. It is true, that when Kings are entertained into cities in triumph, they are oft pleaſed with theire magnificent pageants and ſhewes, becauſe they are new inventions: but God is not as man: He hath in all things preſcribed vs a forme of worſhip and ſervice, he hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven vs a tree of life, that hath its propper leaves: and therefore Kings and Magiſtrates ſhould know that mens inventions, how ancient ſoeever they be, are dangerous: that they are not Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours againſt, or beſides, but vnder God in theire dominions, to ſee his will performed: and withall that they are ſo much the more juſtly called Gods, and truly honourable, as they rightly
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:1648:41"/> ſeeke to doe, and have all things donne, according to his revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led word.</p>
            <p>When on the other ſide they enforce on theire people mens inventions, and countenance defenſes of them, which are not of the truth: for <hi>no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lie is of the truth,</hi> noe errour,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 2.21. Ioh. 8.</note> and therefore not of God, but of him that is the father of lies; it is not God, but Sathan that hath a throne in them: they maintaining theeſe things, in ignorance and obſtinacie, doe not make the Church in theire dominions a Ieruſalem, but a Babylon, as<note n="*" place="margin">See the crowne of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Martyr.</note> the Teſtimonie of Ieſus in the Revelation doth abundantly manifeſt: And ſeeing the Kings of the earth do in this commit fornication with her: Such as are Iewes indeede, Chriſtians indeede, will rather ſuffer any thing then be enforced to ſerve God after ſuch inventions &amp; precepts of men. <hi>Here is the patience of the Saints,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 14.</note> 
               <hi>here are they that keepe the commaundements of God, and the faith of Jeſus.</hi> There are many in greate Britaine and other parts, who haue left Babylon in many of her abhominations, but not in all. Some of theeſe are verie zealous againſt other errours of Babylon, and yet either defend a hierarchie, traditions and ceremonies, which are Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh, or elſe are cold againſt them; becauſe they are maintained by Kings and convocations of Prelates: who by theire power keepe theeſe men from the knowledge of Gods will in theeſe caſes, who otherwiſe were like enough to follow it, if they might be ſuffred to ſee the proofes thereof. Becauſe theeſe men are not wholy out of Babylon, therefore that voice of God is ſurely addreſſed to ſuch, <hi>come out of her my people,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chap. 18.</note> 
               <hi>that ye pertake not of her ſinnes, and that ye receive not of her plagues.</hi> Which certainly is not onely ſpoken to ſuch favourers of the Proteſtant Religion, as live in Italie and other Popiſh Kingdoms, but to thoſe alſo, who haue left Babylon in many things, but not in all, and ſo ſeeme to haue one foote out of her, and another in her. The voyce crieth to theeſe, becauſe the Lord knoweth, that vnleſſe they can ſay to God in ſincerity of ſoule,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.</note> 
               <hi>with my whole heart haue J ſought thee, o let me not wander from thy commaundements: I hate vaine inventions, but thy Law doe I loue,</hi> they are not Iewes indeede, they neither haue right to the tree of life, nor can enter
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:1648:42"/> in through the Gates into the new Ieruſalem, but doe indeede remaine without, with dogges, ſorcerers &amp;c. Rev. 22.14.15. And if they had no care of theire Soules, yet in regard of thoſe plagues of Babylon, whereof they may pertake in this world, they haue cauſe to leave her follies, and come out of her: <hi>For her ſinnes haue reached vnto heaven,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 18.</note> 
               <hi>and God hath remembred her wickedneſſe.</hi> Certainly in theeſe late wars of Germanie and other parts, he hath begun to avenge it, and to ſhew that the ſixt vial beeing powred out, ſuch are the effects of it. Greate rewards doth God offer to him that overcommeth, and that queſtionles as well by war, as ſpirituall weapons. He that is called <hi>faithfull and true,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chap. 19.</note> 
               <hi>doth in righteouſneſſe judge and make war</hi> againſt her that ſitteth on many waters: and ſo doe theſe that fight his battails. To them that voyce crieth, <hi>Reward her as ſhe hath rewarded you, and double vnto her double according vnto her works. In the cup &amp;c. For ſhe ſaith in her heart, I ſit as a Queene and am no widdow, and ſhall ſee no ſorrow: Therefore ſhall her plagues come in one day, death and mourning and famine, and ſhe ſhall be vtterly burnt with fire: for ſtrong is the Lord who judgeth her.</hi> Notwithſtanding that ſhe ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth daily to ſtrengthen her ſelfe by plots, deviſes and friends, by Ieſuiticall and Spaniſh practiſes; yet fall ſhe muſt. Many thinke this cannot yet be, becauſe England doth not yet ſet againſt her, as if God could not fulfill his worke without the ayde of lukewarme helpers,<note place="margin">Ioh. 18.</note> and newters: Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Euerie one that is of the truth heareth my voyce:</hi> Therefore if Engliſh Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates and others that beare ſway there, doe not heare it in theeſe things, they haue cauſe to doubt that they are not in all things of the truth, nor quite come out of Babylon. I wonder how they can evince vnto themſelves, that they are not of Babylon the greate, nor pertake of her ſinnes, who haue no more zeale againſt her. Marvaile not that they doe not deſire to have ſwords draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en againſt her, who ſcarce endure that the ſword of the Spirit ſhould be vnſheathed againſt Babylon, much leſſe againſt thoſe tenets of theire owne, which are Romiſh and Antichriſtian.</p>
            <p>The miniſters of the french and dutch churches, though they be not wholly excerciſed in points controverted, which were no
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:1648:42"/> wiſdom, ſeeing there are many other points of faith and ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wherein the people are alſo to be built vp and fortified; yet they ſcarce make a Sermon, but in ſomthing or other, they confute poperie, and eſtabliſh the people in the truth, as God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth. If Engliſh Prelates have not made this courſe to be in a ſort forbidden, yet men ſay that by diſcountenancing of ſuch preaching, they have at leaſt put it out of faſhion, as fooliſh and vnproffitable; while in the meane, they are contented and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous that men ſhould preach and contend for the authority of theire hierarchie, traditions and ceremonies, if not for Arminian tenets. (A thinge that pleaſeth papiſts, who looke for fruite of them, knowing them to be popiſh) yea many are ſo fooliſh, as to love and praiſe this kinde of preaching, and to loath the confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of it, as God complained of the Iewes,<note place="margin">Ier. 5.31.</note> 
               <hi>The prophets pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie falſly, and the Prieſts beare rule by theire meanes, and my people love to have it ſoe: and what will ye doe in the end thereof?</hi> That is, when deſtruction comes on you for it. It is ſtrange that men will not ſee that this theire preaching and contending, for humane inventions and errours, is to offer ſtrange fire, and the entrance &amp; way to all corruption, as it was in the Church of Rome; whoſe ſuperſtition &amp; errours crept in by degrees, &amp; by degrees did eate out true Religion. It will be ſaide, it hath not yet donne ſo in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland: both the citie and countrie haue many zealous Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, yea many that are conformable. I anſwer, true, yet they are verie few in reſpect of the reſt, and ſuch as beare the Sway: who count zeale againſt poperie, puritaniſme, and are ready to ſay with them in the Goſpell,<note place="margin">Ioh. 7.48. Act. 28.20</note> 
               <hi>Have any of the Rulers or of the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> run this courſe? <hi>but this people who knoweth not the Law, are cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</hi> Becauſe they walke not after the high Prieſts, the Biſhops. <hi>For as concerning this ſect, wee know it is every where ſpoken againſt.</hi> And howſoever theſe called puritans, whether they be confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable, or peaceable reformiſts, are ſuch as will be religious, whether the Biſhops like it or noe, as ſom Iewes would be Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples for all the high Prieſts Elders and Phariſes: therefore this is no thanks to Biſhops, no fruite of theire government: who like better of civill and ceremonious men, ſuch as pretend love of
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:1648:43"/> common prayer, though they haue neither knowledge, true loue of the word, nor affection to defend religion againſt Papiſts and theire practiſes, and like hypocrites doe but pretend a love to prayer: For in thoſe prayers they ſay that in <hi>knowledge of him ſtandeth our eternall life. Graunt vs in this world knowledge of thy truth:</hi> And yet are enemies to this knowledge, and the meanes of it, preaching, hearing, conference and reading of ſome good bookes. They pray for <hi>increaſe of grace to heare meekely his word, receive it with pure affection, and bring forth the fruits of the Spirit:</hi> Yet theire life and actions ſhew that they are ſo far from loveing theſe things, that they mock and perſecute all thoſe that doe, as knaves and hypocrites: Yet in ſome caſes, as God ſaith of ſuch men,<note place="margin">Iſa. 58.</note> 
               <hi>they ſeeke me daily and delight to know my wayes, as a nation that did righteouſnes, and forſooke not the ordinance of theire God: they aske of me the ordinance of juſtice: they take delight in approching to God:</hi> They faſt, and like the Biſhops looke God ſhould regard them for it. But though men be never ſo religious in obſerving ſome of Gods ordinances, if they deſpiſe or neglect the reſt, or any of them,<note place="margin">Deut. 15.21. chap. 17.1.</note> the Lord hateth that Religion, as a lame ſacrifice. <hi>Theire hands were full of blood,</hi> and in other things they had <hi>tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed the Lawes, changed the ordinance and broken the everlaſting covenant:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 1.11.12.13.14.15,</note> therefore he ſaith <hi>to what purpoſe is the multitude of your ſacrifices to me? I am full of the burnt offerings. Bring no more vaine oblations: incenſe is abhomination vnto me: New Moones, Sabbaths and appointed feasts, my ſoule hateth. And when ye make many prayers J will not heare.</hi> He counteth all this but complement all religion; and would not heare them in theſe things, though he had commanded them; who would not heare him in others. Like the Prelates who ſay well, that in baptiſme wee promiſe to forſake the world, <hi>and all the pompe and vanitie</hi> thereof: Yet can not be perſwaded by Gods word to caſt theire crownes theire offices, and the pompe and vanitie of them, at the feete of Chriſt, though it be proved that they are not of God, but of men, of the world, Romiſh and doe much miſchiefe: but inſteade of confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, they perſecute ſuch as pleade Chriſts cauſe in proveing theſe things, terryfying all men of that profeſſion, more then any other
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:1648:43"/> with theire power in the high commiſſion, as the Papiſts doe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants with the iniquiſition; ſtriveing to make them hatefull to Princes, and yet keepe theire proofes from theire eyes, as if they were worſe then the tenets of Papiſts and Arminians, which are not ſo ſtraitly prohibited, nor ſo narrowly looked vnto.<note place="margin">B. London march. 6. 1632.</note> Yea a greate Biſhop in a ſermon before the King, charged one that writ for the preſbyterie with Arianiſme; whether truly or no, I know not; for he namd not the man, nor the book; for feare leaſt his proofes of the preſbiterie ſhould be looked into: So much do they bewray the rottenneſſe of theire cauſe, that will not endure touching, nor to be looked vpon: and in the meane call vpon men to frequent common prayer, be obedient and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to theire mother the Church &amp;c. Beeing willingly ignorant, that when of old, ſom began to finde fault with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of ſuperſtition and tyranie in Romiſh Prelates &amp; Canons, they reckoned them Schiſmatikes, willed men to ſeeke peace, ſtirred them vp to love of common prayer, conformitie in cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies and externall devotions, building of Churches &amp;c. Whereby ignorance increaſed, and the truth was daily more and more betrayed and ſold, till it was too late to reforme them.</p>
            <p>Princes and noble men could not doe it: becauſe they, beeing nouriſhed in this ceremonious, and ſuperſtitious part of religion, fell themſelves into ignorance, and ſo into many quarrels and noiſom luſts, like the Prelates, one growing diſſolute, another vſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ping, another circumventing, killing, warring; as in France betweene the Kings and the Duks of Burgundie and other Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: In England betweene the howſes of yorke and Lancaſter, the Kings and Rebels: they had not a Goſpell truly preached to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and aw them: ſo they could not ſee that all theſe errours in the Clergie, and indeede in themſelves, came from altering the preſbyterall government, and giveing ſuch authority to Biſhops, who for theire owne ends were readie to ſide with any of them.</p>
            <p>So Proteſtants in other countries have obſerved, that when the Palatinate was looſing, the churches in Germanie, France and other parts in greate miſerie; yet the church of Prelates, &amp; theire adherents in England, did litle helpe them, but rather hindred
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:1648:44"/> ſuch as would, ſiding with the Duke and others, charged by the parliaments, to practiſe ſecretly for the popiſh partie, or a new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tralitie, vnder colour that they were conformable to the Engliſh diſcipline, and therfore Proteſtants: but at the beſt, that is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede, ſuch as the hierarchie bringeth forth; either newters, or men of a mixed religion, partly popiſh in the hierarchie, Canons and ceremonies, moſt followed and maintained, and partly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant, in ſom points of faith, more coldly defended by the moſt, who alſo ſeemed to thinke it dangerours to maintaine ancient and honeſt priveliedges, as free elections, free ſpeaking and parliamentarie power in ſearching out, and reforming cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions in church and common wealth; both the one and the other beeing, by ſom factious, cunningly accounted a puritani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call zeale, and a trenching vpon the prerogative of Princes: when indeede the prerogative, themſelves ſought to maintaine, was only that of corrupt Prelates and favourits, who have abuſed our Kings with ſuch incenſings and whiſperings, as the proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the parliaments laboured to manifeſt. It is no neede to tell how they were prevented, or that thereupon greate diviſions followed both at that time and ſince, eſpecially in religion: The Prelates not enduring that the howſe of Commons ſhould medle with it, nor with the moſt notorious delinquents that did but fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour theire partie, who thus ſtrove to helpe and vphold one another, what ever became of the cauſe of Chriſt at home or abroade.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5.9.</note>Not to mention what boldnes and corruption this hath ſince bred in other inferiour bodies and government. <hi>A litle leaven leaveneth the whole lumpe.</hi> The french and other Proteſtants ſay theeſe are the fruits of maintaining the hierarchie and cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, which are Popiſh, and ſo ſerve many for a cloak of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie, or trecherie, or Arminianiſme, or prevarication, or perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or newtralitie, or what a man will: whereby the Engliſh haue beene brought into greate contempt, theire peace thus attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, beeing ſcorned, as ſavouring of corruption, or Newtralite, in Religion, and as more helping to ſupport, then ruin Babylon, and her chiefe fort and wall, the howſe of Auſtria; and as thus ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veing
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:1648:44"/> loſt theire honour both abroade and at home. The Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops could cover all this, and turne the fault vpon the puritans, that would not flatter, as themſelves did. And yet in all this, like the Romaniſts, they bluſter with the name, authority and wiſdom of Chriſts Church, whether they be truly of it or the world.</p>
            <p>The name Church, if the Greeke word be conſidered ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth <hi>coetus evocatus,</hi> a companie, or people, called out,<note place="margin">Coetus evocatus.</note> as Iſrael out of Egypt, or men out of darkneſſe, ignorance, or worldli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. How few are thus called out of poperie, temporiſing and earthlineſſe? I know divers Miniſters that have ſubſcribed are in all other things of the reformed Religion, and thorowly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led out of poperie, ſave onely that for feare of looſing theire liveings, they dare not ſee one part of it, in the caſe of the hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie things that are againſt the preſbiterie: But conſider the Church of England, as the Biſhops, that govern it, account it, in themſelves and theire adherents, in a Synod, called the Church repreſentative, and maintaining theire power, canons and cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies with the fruits and practiſes of them, who can ſay it is <hi>coetus evocatus?</hi> Much leſſe if you vnderſtand it of halfe a dozen of Prelates that are courtiers, &amp; in a manner ruling all, are follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and flattered by many temporiſing Clergie men, and a world of ignorant gentlemen and people. And what if one corrupt Biſhop get into ſuch favour as to rule all the reſt, ſhall he like the Pope account himſelfe the Church? Not onely all theſe ill fruits, but all that are in the Church of Rome came from altering that order of Biſhops which the Apoſtles left, by ſetting one preſbyter of a greate citie over the reſt, and giving him firſt a litle authority, as Preſident of theire councell, and then a litle more, till he came to be accounted the ſole Biſhop of a dioceſſe. And therfore as cunning Clarks, as they make themſelves, our ſaviour may in theſe caſes ſay of them, <hi>If you were blinde,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 9.41.</note> if ye did confeſſe your blindneſſe; if ye had not the light of Gods word to ſhew it to you, <hi>ye ſhould haue no ſinne; But now ye ſay wee ſee;</hi>
               <note place="margin">chap. 101.</note> 
               <hi>therfore your ſinne remaineth. He that entreth not by the doore into the ſheepefold, but climeth vp another way, the ſame is a thiefe and a robber. I am the doore.</hi> As he is the word of the father, that revealeth him, ſo is
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:1648:45"/> he the doore. If a man come with any other Doctrine then the word revealed, or enter by any other way to be a Paſtor, or Governour of the Church, then ſuch lawfull election and miſſion, as is ordained in the word; if he enter by any other rule, office, authority, or title, then ſuch as the word alloweth, <hi>he is a theefe and a robber</hi> that <hi>commeth not but for to ſteale,</hi> a hireling, as the Phariſes were. They complaine of lecturers, as vnlawfull, yet none muſt complaine of them. Men will not ſee theeſe things, <hi>This peoples heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 13.15</note> ſaith he, <hi>is waxed groſſe and theire eares are dull of hearing, and theire eyes haue they cloſed &amp;c.</hi> When Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth he will diſtinguiſh the ſheepe from the goates, and know them by this mark, as himſelfe ſaith. My ſheepe heare my voice. <hi>If ye continue in my word, then are ye my Diſciples indeede,</hi> my ſheepe indeede; otherwiſe not. This is as well true of them, that are at Synods, as at Sermons, both the one and the other beeing but conventicles, if they continue not in the word, but teach or receive for doctrines precepts of men.</p>
            <p>A dioceſſan Biſhop would, like a player, ſeeme to be that which he is not, namely a Biſhop of the new Teſtament, when yet he makes them of none effect, and ſo is an hypocrit by his office, one that ſaith not againſt him that would have preſbyters reſtored, this man is againſt Gods ordinance, but againſt the Doctrine of our Church, a cuſtom, or a canon of a councell, and therfore an hipocrit: but if Chriſt, ſhall ſay to this vſurper <hi>depart I know you not,</hi> I ordained no ſuch offices, no ſuch canons, who is then the hypocrit? It is true indeede that among the many orders of the Popiſh Religion, dioceſſan Biſhops and theire officials are the moſt ancient: and that ſecular Prieſts, which anciently were preſbyters, did before the Nicene councell differ litle from the preſbiters Chriſt ordained, ſave that Biſhops had wrunge moſt of the government <hi>out of theyre hands: but</hi> when looſing power in excommunication, they alſo became ſubject to the Biſhops, and to be governed by theire Lawes, Rules and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, as they all by the Pope, they left and loſt Chriſts marke, &amp; tooke on them the marke of the Beaſt: But then as they had
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:1648:45"/> made the preſbiterie of none effect, ſo the Regulars ſupplanted them.</p>
            <p>There are many orders of theſe Regulars or Monles, who, haveing obtained of Boniface 4. and others after him, to have the adminiſtation of the word and Sacraments, got the hearing of mens confeſſions, and by degrees ſtole from Biſhops and Prieſts all that reputation, which they had with the people, and became the ſtouteſt champions of the papacie in all the deſignes thereof, as is at large proved in Pleſſes his Hiſtorie of the papacie, progreſſ. 51. &amp;c. Theſe were the Auguſtines, Benedictines, Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobines, Heremits, Carthuſians, but eſpecially the Dominicans and Franciſcans, Cordiliers, and Capuchins, and laſt of all the Ieſuits and fathers of the Oratorie: Theſe and others have all theire ſeverall Rules, and ſo are ſeverall Religions: Yet they all have the marke of the Beaſt: They all hold of him, and for him, not of Gods word, nor for it, And ſo ye have ſeene alſo that Engliſh Biſhops and theire officials, Deanes, Prebends, Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deanes, Archdeacons, pettie canons and the like, doe not hold theire authority and right in theire orders, to execute theire offices, from Gods word, but from other rotten principles; and have taken them from the cuſtom and authority of the Pope &amp; Church of Rome, or from a child, or a woman, Edward 6. or Queene Elizabeth; &amp; that to hold them vpon any ſuch humane authority, or to ſay the word of God giveth leave ſo to hold them, is to change the truth of God into a lie, and to worſhip &amp; ſerve the creature more then the creator. For of Chriſts Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they doe not, nor cannot, hold them. If they ſay from the Nicence councell, wee have ſeene the weaknes of that hold in this perticular; and indeede that, as well many of the ancient, as of the later, councels have in many things beene carried by mens private intereſts and practiſes, as appeareth, among other Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, by an Epiſtle of Biſhop Iewel, annexed to the Hiſtorie of the councell of Trent: and further that Biſhops had not then theire courts, and ſuch power as afterwards, and as they now have in England, where in the Reformation, it was ſet vp in the ſame power the Popiſh Biſhops had enjoyed, if not in greater, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:1648:46"/> they were freed from the tyranie of the Pope: and laſtly that none of all theſe have the Teſtimonie of Ieſus for theire orders, offices and Rules: They are not of that Temple, or Church militant which Iohn ſaw; but of the owter court, though neerer the Temple and Altar then the Papiſts. For all that are of that Temple have the Teſtimonie of Ieſus, as well for theire offices as Doctrines, which you ſee none other have but preſbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Paſtors, helpers and Deacons: Not excluding ſuch Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates and people as are of the reformed Religion: theſe church orders and no other have his marke, who when he is ready to powre out his laſt plague on Babylon, and other cities ſaith, <hi>behold I come as a theife:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 16.15.16.</note> Where I thinke he meaneth in that laſt plague againſt all Antichriſtian adverſaries, and in the voyces, thunders, the exceeding greate earthquake and haile, and the fall of Babylon, which are of it, accompanie it, or follow ſoone after it, as Revel. 2. <hi>Repent or elſe I will come vnto thee quickly, and will fight againſt them with the ſword of my mouth.</hi> For then it is that the Angel crieth, <hi>Babylon the greate is fallen, is fallen, and is become the habitation</hi> of deuils &amp;c. Then Babylon comes in remembrance before God to give her the cup of the wine of the firceneſſe of his wrath: and therefore he addeth, <hi>Bleſſed is he that watcheth and keepeth his garments, leaſt he walke naked, and they ſee his ſhame,</hi> that is in luſts and ignorance, or worſhipping the Beaſt, or his Image, or receiving his marke, in part or in whole. For they that would not doe this, though they may come into trouble for the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Ieſus, and for the word of God, yet theſe ſeaven plagues take not hold of them,<note place="margin">Luk. 21.36</note> they watch and are thought <hi>worthy to eſcape theſe things;</hi> they raigne with Chriſt, and have part <hi>in the firſt reſurrection.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 13.</note> God therefore ſends vs to ſee when this vial is powred out, or at leaſt to heare that voyce, <hi>It is donne,</hi> or that <hi>Babylon is fallen, is fallen &amp;c.</hi> Which ſeeme to follow cloſe after the powring out of the ſeaventh vial that it may drive vs to repentance before ſuch lamentable iudgments fall on vs, at leaſt on all them, who pertaking with her in her ſinnes are ſure to receive of her plagues, a thing that is not enough regarded by many in England.</p>
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:1648:46"/>
            <p>Chriſt alſo comes as a thiefe in the laſt day. And then when he ſhall looke on the ſoules of many, who have had voices in Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods, upon the ſoules of many a preacher, of many an officer, and many a hearer, and ſhall ſee there is little in them, but the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons and ceremonies of the pretended church, and a reverent o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of them, becauſe of theire pretended antiquitie; or if they have knowledge and zeale in many other things (as the Papiſts have in ſome) they withall have zeale and ignorance in theeſe, and theire feare towards him hath beene taught by the precepts of men; doe you thinke he will ackowledge this for his marke, or that it may ſtand together with his (as ſome thinke it may in Papiſts, who hold the Chriſtian faith and truth in many things) and that he will not rather ſay unto them, <hi>who required theſe things at your hands?</hi> And not rather to abide in the word, and ſuffer your wayes to be reproved by it,<note place="margin">Ioh. 18.37</note> 
               <hi>for every one that is of the truth heareth my voice;</hi> he watcheth and keepeth his garments; that ye would not doe in theſe things, but perſecuted them, that, haveing the marke and teſtimonie of Ieſus, would have drawne you to it: but ye have mocked at theire arguments, and rejoiced to ſee them prohibited and trodden vnder foote, ſo wretched is the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of many of the Prelates and theire defenders in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</p>
            <p>And indeede nothing doth more ſhew the Rottenneſſe of theire cauſe, and that they are not of God, then theire forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of bookes, written in defenſe of Gods ordinances, about the preſbiterie, and power he gave each church in election of preſbyters, excommunication, &amp;c. wherein they have beene ſuch cruel adverſaries, that they have, by ſuppreſſing all bookes and preachers that doe but touch on theſe points, left men no meanes of defending, or knowing, the truth in ſuch caſes, like the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtins, who ſuffered <hi>not a Smith in the land of Iſrael, ſaying,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 13.19.</note> 
               <hi>least the Hebrewes make them ſwords or ſpeares.</hi> This thing alone ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that ſo great power, as Biſhops have in the church, can not be of God, and that it ſerveth chiefely to ſuppreſſe the truth, and forbid the defenſe thereof in theſe things, and in thoſe others, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Gods free-grace in election, free will, perſeverance of the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:1648:47"/> ſaints, or any thing elſe that either they doe now, or may hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter prohibit in doctrine, diſcipline, or ceremonies, as in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the church of Rome did in one thing or other, till at laſt ſhe became full of abhominations and filthines: the firſt ſteps where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of were the eſtabliſhing and increaſing the power of Biſhops a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the preſbiterie, &amp;c. which gave them power to effect theire pleaſures in theſe and all other things. <hi>About the yeare 400 a councell in Carthage did forbid to reade the bookes of the Gentiles, but allowed them to reade the bookes of the Heretiks; the Decree whereof is amongſt the Canons collected by Gratian.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hiſtor. of the counc. of Trent p. 472.</note> 
               <hi>This,</hi> ſaith a learned Author, <hi>was the first prohibition by way of Canon: for in the church of Martyrs there was none. The bookes of Hereticks, containing doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, condemned by Councels, were often forbid by the Emperours for good government: So Conſtantine forbad the bookes of Arrius; Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cadius thoſe of the Eunomians and Maniches; Theodoſius thoſe of Neſtorius; Martinus thoſe of the Euticheans, and in Spaine King Ricardus thoſe of the Arrians:</hi> But this is no warrant for Kings, or Prelates, to forbid thoſe which are written in defenſe of the preſbiterie, or any of Gods ordinances. <hi>It ſufficed the Councels and Biſhops to ſhew what bookes contained damned or Apocryphal doctrine.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem.</note> 
               <hi>So did Gelaſius in the yeare 494. and went no further, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it to the conſcience to avoide them, or reade them to a good end. After the yeare 800. as the Popes of Rome aſſumed a greate part of the politik government, ſo they cauſed the bookes, whoſe Authors they did condemn to be burned, and forbad the reading of them. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing one ſhall finde but few bookes forbid in this ſort, till this age. Martin 5. doth in a Bull excommunicate all the Sects of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes, eſpecially Wicklifiſts, and Huſſites, not mentioning thoſe who reade theire bookes, though many of them went aboute. Lev. 10. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning Luther, did with all forbid his books upon paine of excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication. After Popes did the like. The Inquiſitors made Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logues of thoſe whome they knew. Philip King of Spaine was the first that gave a more convenient forme in the yeare 1558. making a law that the Catologue of bookes, prohibited by Inquiſition, ſhould be prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. After this example Paul</hi> 4 <hi>cauſed an Index, compoſed by that office to be printed in the yeare 1559.</hi> At laſt all they pleaſed were fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:1648:47"/> into this number, <hi>to deprive men of all meanes of knowledge. A better myſterie was never found then to vſe religion to make men inſenſible.</hi> So doe Engliſh Biſhops, who though they follow not the ſame forme, yet they vſe another as rigorous and prevalent: They have the licencing and cenſuring of bookes in theſe caſes, and ſo are both Iudges and parties; they can ſcoffe ſuſpend, fine, impriſon; ſilence and degrade whom they pleaſe; yea men in theſe caſes goe in jeopardie of theire liveings and lives: by which meanes, as by the weapons of their warfare, they muſt needes obtaine their cauſe, as the Romaniſts have theires; ſo like are they in ſom things to Babylon the mother of Harlots,<note place="margin">Ioh. 8.43.44.</note> and to thoſe Iewes, to whom Chriſt ſaith: <hi>Why doe ye not vnderstand my my ſpeech? even becauſe ye cannot heare my word, ye are of your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the devill, and the lusts of your father ye will doe: he was a mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer from the beginning, and abode not in the truth: he is a liar and the father of it. And becauſe I tell you the truth, ye beleeve me not. He that is of God heareth Gods words: ye therefore heare them not, becauſe ye are not of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Iudge therefore whether it be not with good cauſe, that ſom Engliſh, who hold with the Geneva and french reformations, have ſaid that the Engliſh hierarchie, dominion, and practiſe of the Prelates, and many of theire canons, cuſtomes, courts, and ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, are popiſh, and a parte of the marke of the Beaſt; not ſo much in thoſe, who have of infirmitie ſubſcribed, yet doe not defend them, as in them that maintaine theſe things, ſcorne them that doe not, and will not ſee the miſchiefes that follow; that in theſe caſes men cannot without great trouble freely ſpeake, or write the truth to convince them: that they bring forth popiſh fruits, flatterie, ſuperſtition, ignorance, non reſidencie, ambition, prophane mocking, newtralitie, Epiſcopal tyranie, wicked poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, Arminianiſme and the like; and that therefore they ought to be aboliſhed: That theſe evills doe ſo increaſe through theire power and practiſes, that they may juſtly feare, that Chriſt will one day ſhew them to theire coſt, that this maintaining of them againſt the reaſons and proofes of them that in the reformed churches hold the ordinances of God, is not to ſavour <hi>the things
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:1648:48"/> that are of God, but thoſe that are of men;</hi> not to have the marke of God but rather that of the Beaſt: that at leaſt ſom of them are in divers reſpects Popiſh, and tend to poperie; and that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if to maintaine that they ought to be obeyed, be neither directly nor indirectly to worſhip the beaſt, and his Image, or take a part of his marke, yet they have theire originall, and firſt authority, from her, who taxing the offices and ordinances of Chriſt of inſufficiencie for the government of the Church, is <hi>the mother of fornications and abhominations of the earth,</hi> that the myſterie of iniquitie began to worke in theſe things, and when they are vtterly confuted or taken away, it will begin to ceaſe working.<note place="margin">Rev. 16.17.</note> In that theire laſt plague, this voyce will be heard, <hi>It is donne:</hi> That while Chriſt is thus ſpoken againſt in his officers and ordinances, <hi>the hearts of many are diſcovered,</hi> that they ſtand not ſo much for the truth of God, as the traditions of men: That they in England, who make theſe things indifferent, innocent and trifles, doe <hi>cover with a covertng, but not of his Spirit,</hi> they full of wrath, doe not favour the powring out of the laſt vial, much leſſe pray for it: though it be a greate mercie to his people, and onely full of wrath, to his enimies. That the Kingdom of God and the righteouſnes thereof, which all Chriſtians ſhould ſeeke, doth ſuffer more prejudice by ſuch temporiſing and daubing, then by the malice of ſuch as are the profeſt enemies of religion: That they have hereby ſo vpheld the power and rigour of the Prelates, that men begin to crie out, that vnder colour of main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining theire authority, they ſhake the defence of Religion againſt Papiſts, and bring in the defenſe of Altars, Images, &amp; ſuch preciſenes in ceremonies, that wee are like to be cooſoned of our Religion, and looſe it in the fire of humane inventions, dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſan power, ſuperſtition, avarice, ambition and perſecution, as by the ſame meanes, and the like, the Church of Rome loſt the love of the truth, and was given over to ſtrong deluſions to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve lies, vnto the everlaſting ruin of many millions of Soules; which is an evill ſo greate, and ſo ſure a roote of all evils, that the Church of England, and all the Soules therein, ſhould rather ſeeke to prevent it by watchfulnes and due reformation, then by
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:1648:48"/> mocking and ſcorning the reaſons of reformiſts, as groundles opinions, full of curioſitie, ſchiſme and puritaniſme, to diſcover theire owne ſhame, and keepe the way broade to her owne cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption and ruin; or at leaſt to the corruption and deſtruction of many thouſands of Soules, who live in the pale of that Church, and covering themſelves vnder the vaile of conformitie are Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh, or newters, or meere civil men, or Prophane, or perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and will not be made to ſee, that in this manner the church of Rome began to be Babylon.</p>
            <p>And yet in the meane by her proſperitie, and deliverance from heathen perſecutions, ſhe iudged her ſelfe to be beloved of God, and that he was well pleaſed, with the authority of her Prelates, traditions, inventions and ceremonies; as Philip King of Spaine, hardly eſcaping a danger at ſea, <hi>ſaide,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hiſtor. of the counc. of Trent lib. 5. pag. 417.</note> 
               <hi>he was delivered by the ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar providence of God to roote out Lutheraniſme, which he preſently ſought to doe,</hi> as Engliſh Prelates thinke God hath longe preſerved them in theire pompe and power, to roote out reformiſts, called puritans, and iudge of the favour of God toward them, &amp; theire hierarchie and traditions, by the deliverances from the Marian perſecution, the Spaniſh invaſion, and the longe time of peace and proſperitie they, the Church hath enioyed, when all other Churches have beene vnder the croſſe. <hi>A ſtrong evidence,</hi> ſay they, <hi>that God was therewith well pleaſed</hi> (which is the argument of them that burnt incenſe to the Queene of heaven: <hi>for then,</hi> ſay they, <hi>wee had plentie, and were well and ſaw no evill</hi>) Not conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that in the Spaniſh invaſion and the powder treaſon, the axe, for ſome ſinnes was laide to the roote of the tree; that though God, ſeeing ſome in that land did ſeeke the truth, and mourne for the abhominations that were donne therein, did in mercie ſpare the ſame, yet his mercie and longe ſuffering leadeth to repentance: That Rome and Italie, from the time of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine to the inundation of the Gothes and Vandals, enjoyed as greate peace and plentie, and no doubt glorified her ſelfe therein, that her hierarchie, traditions and ceremonies, which then had not donne much more hurt to the Kingdom and truth of God, then the Engliſh now have, were pleaſing to God, ſeeing while
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:1648:49" rendition="simple:additions"/> other Churches were plagued, ſhe was at reſt. Athanaſius &amp; Baſil travailing in the Eaſt, and groaning vnder the burden of the Arrians and other miſeries, writ to the Biſhops of Italie and France,<note place="margin">Baſil. Epi. 70. Epiſt. 78.</note> 
               <hi>It beeing impoſſiblo,</hi> ſay they, <hi>that they ſhould be ignorant of our miſerable eſtate, ſo well knowne through out the world:</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they redoubled theire letters, conjuring them to <hi>informe the Emperour of theſe troubles in the East:</hi> from whome, and not from Damaſus, they hoped for redreſſe. But in the meane, the Churches of Rome, Italie and France, beeing in proſperitie, neglected theire afflicted brethren,<note place="margin">Epiſt. 10.</note> and were no comfort to them: <hi>For if the Anger of God,</hi> ſaith Baſil, <hi>continue ſtill vpon vs, what comfort will the pride of the west afford vs? who neither do know, neither yet will have the patience to be rightly informed of the truth of things &amp;c. wee have,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>venerable brethren ſet our eyes vpon you; but our hope hath proved vaine: &amp;c. And yet this thirteene yeares longe do wee continue in this war.</hi> Which in effect hath beene the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of the french and German Proteſtants to the Prelates of England, from whome they have found as litle pitie, and helpe in theire diſtreſſes: The arme is oft let blood to cure ſom part of the body.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.17</note> 
               <hi>If iudgment,</hi> as it oft doth, <hi>begin at the howſe of God, what ſhall the end be of them that obey not the Goſpel?</hi> Therefore ſeeing in the Engliſh reformation, many Popiſh things were left vnreformed, ſhe hath cauſe to feare, it will be ſaide of her, as ſomtime of Iudah:<note place="margin">Ier. 3.10,</note> 
               <hi>Yet for all this her trecherous ſiſter hath not tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto me with her whole heart, but fainedly, ſaith the Lord.</hi> But let the Church of England therfore take heede, that ſhe do not now glorifie her ſelfe as fooliſhly, as the Churches of Rome and Italie then did,<note place="margin">Rev. 18. Chap. 3.</note> and now doe, to ſay, <hi>J ſit as a Queene, and am no widdow and</hi> ſhall ſee no ſorrow, or like Laodicea who ſaide; <hi>I am rich and increaſed with goods and have neede of nothing,</hi> and knew not that ſhe was <hi>wretched, and miſerable and poore, and blinde and naked.</hi> When the laſt plague is ready to be powred out, Chriſt ſaith <hi>Behold I come as a thiefe:</hi> That is to judge and plague ſuch ſecure ones: And indeede as now, ſo in thoſe dayes, the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Italie were in greater pompe and proſperitie, then any other Chriſtian Churches, but withall theire feare toward God
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:1648:49" rendition="simple:additions"/> was more taught by the precepts of men, there was more ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition and Eccleſiaſtical tyranie; therefore they were not more happy, but indeede more miſerable, as the ſpirituall miſerie doth far exceede the bodilie and temporall.</p>
            <p>Is it not ſo in the Churches of greate Britaine, in compariſon of other Proteſtant Churches? I am afraide, that as in that Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian eaſe and reſt, there was a flood preparing for them, which ſoone brake out in the inundation of the Gothes and Vandals, and many ſtrong deluſions, wherein they ſtill remaine inſecuritie: So there may be ſom other a brewing for the Churches of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland and Scotland: As I can not conceive what they ſhall be: For that is a ſecret in the power of God, who onely holdeth ſuch cups of affliction and puniſhment in his hand, tempers them, &amp; when he pleaſeth maketh a nation drinke the dregs of them: So I cannot ſee how ſuch evils ſhould poſſiblie be avoided without a ſerious and effectuall repentance and reformation. Let not men deceive themſelves to thinke, becauſe the Prelates preach ſome good things, that therfore all both is, and will goe well enough, For ſo, you may be ſure, did the Prelates of Rome and Italie in thoſe times: as Hierom ſaith, <hi>There is the confeſſion of Christ:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hiero. ad Marcell. Viduam.</note> 
               <hi>but there is alſo ambition and tyranie.</hi> They had the knowledge of God in many things, and taught it, but in matters of the preſbiterie, and the contraries, Prelates, canons and ceremonies, they could not abide it; nor that Emperours and Princes ſhould come to the knowledge of it. They geered, ſcorned and perſecuted ſuch as laboured to bring them to that which was once delivered to the Saints: cunningly putting theire owne fault vpon theire ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, making them hypocrits, <hi>filthie dreamers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iude. 8.11.12.</note> ſuch <hi>as speake evill of the things they know not,</hi> and are as Iude ſpeaketh, <hi>Cloudes without water, carried about with windes, raging waves of the Sea, and wandring ſtars:</hi> Such as can <hi>make a man an offendour for a word,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 29.21.</note> 
               <hi>and turne aſide the juſt for a thing of nought;</hi> and calling them here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, or ſchiſmatikes, ſeemed to ſhew mercie to them that they puniſhed them no more.<note place="margin">Hoſ. 6.4.5.6.</note> But theire mercie was <hi>as a morning cloude.</hi> They ſacrificed to God of theire owne inventions and will worſhhip: But, ſaith he, <hi>I deſired mercie, and not ſacrifice, and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:1648:50" rendition="simple:additions"/> the knowledge of God more then burnt offerings: But they like men have tranſgreſsed the covenant, there have they dealt trecherouſly with me.</hi> The Italians doeing it in matters of Eccleſiaſticall govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and traditions, it was the roote of all evils, ſpirituall and temporall. And is it not ſo in England, and Scotland? of whom God may alſo ſay, as ſometime of Iſrael and Iudah, <hi>Ephraim what ſhould I doe vnto thee? O Judah what ſhould J doe vnto thee?</hi> For <hi>thy mercie is as a morning cloud, &amp; as the early dew it goeth away</hi> I pray God that the churches of England and Scotland, beeing in ſinnes like theeſe, and indeede like thoſe of Italie, in the times of Damaſus and Syricius, be not alſo like them in puniſhments, ſpirituall and temporall: and that as Ieremie ſaith, in a like caſe, becauſe <hi>they were not aſhamed when they had committed abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> as in theſe particulars of Biſhops,<note place="margin">Ier. 6.15.16.</note> traditions, and ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies; wherein though the voice of God have cried both to the one and the other. <hi>Stand ye in the wayes, and ſee and aſke for the old pathes, where is the good way, and walke therein, and ye ſhall finde rest vnto your ſoules;</hi> and hath often by his ſervants proved the preſbiterie to be the old and good way: yet be it never ſo old, never ſo good, <hi>they ſay, non ambulabimus in ea, wee will not walke in it.</hi> I have conceived ſom hope of the churches and people of great Britaine, that they will alſo now at the laſt begin to leave the church of Rome in theſe things, which are part of her ſinnes (and the roote of them all) leſte ſtill pertaking with her in them, they alſo receive of her plagues: and therfore I thought it my dutie, ſo far as God hath enabled me, to doe mine endeavour to make them ſee the things that belong to their peace. The Lord of his mercie ſtir up and enable men to further ſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie a worke, and <hi>grant vnto vs that wee beeing delivered out of the hands of our ennemies, may ſerve him without feare, in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe before him all the dayes of our life.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 1.74.</note> 
               <hi>Now unto him that is able to do abundantly above all that we can aſke or thinke, according to the power that worketh in vs, vnto him be glorie in the church by Chriſt Ieſus, throughout all ages world without end.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:1648:50"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
